<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of the iudge of controuersies. Written in Latin, by the R. Father Martinus Becanus of the Society of Iesus, Professour in Diuinity. And Englished by W.W. Gent</title>
            <title>De judice controversiarum. English</title>
            <author>Becanus, Martinus, 1563-1624.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1619</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 221 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 99 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A06606</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 1707</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S101284</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99837100</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99837100</idno>
            <idno type="VID">1409</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A06606)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 1409)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1057:01)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of the iudge of controuersies. Written in Latin, by the R. Father Martinus Becanus of the Society of Iesus, Professour in Diuinity. And Englished by W.W. Gent</title>
                  <title>De judice controversiarum. English</title>
                  <author>Becanus, Martinus, 1563-1624.</author>
                  <author>Wright, William, 1563-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 170, [4] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>English College Press] Permissu superiorum,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Saint-Omer :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.DC.XIX. [1619]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>W.W. = William Wright.</note>
                  <note>Translation of: De judice controversiarum.</note>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>With two final contents leaves.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of the iudge of controuersies.</note>
                  <note>reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Authority --  Religious aspects --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Susie Lorand</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:1409:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1409:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF THE IVDGE OF CONTROVERSIES.</p>
            <p>WRITTEN In Latin, by the R. Father <hi>Martinus Becanus</hi> of the Society of Ieſus, Profeſſour in Diuinity.</p>
            <p>AND <hi>Engliſhed by W. W. Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device (?) containing Jesuit emblem (IHS with a cross resting on the crossbar of the H; three nails below)</figDesc>
               <head>IHS</head>
            </figure>
            <p>Permiſſu Superiorum. M. DC. XIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:1409:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:1409:2"/>
            <head>THE PRINTER TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>ENTLE Reader, hauing peruſed this short Treatiſe, tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted into English, and ſent vnto me by a friend; I was ſtraight moued with earneſt deſire to ſet the ſame forth in Print, hoping that many wold reape great benefit by reading it, &amp; come to be reſolued in the may neſt of the Controuerſyes that now diſturbe the Chriſtia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:1409:3"/> world: yea ſuch a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſy, as the knowledge therof is the beginning of al Truth, &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarywiſe Errour therein the fountaine of all Contentions. For if both ſides, Proteſtants as well as Catholikes, would ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit ſome viſible Iudge, liuing on earth, endued with full au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority to decide their contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſyes, about the ſenſe of holy ſcripture, by ſentence infallible &amp; not obnoxious vnto deceit, Contentions might be ſoone ended, and an vniuerſall peace throughout Chriſtendome, for in matters of Religion, eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shed.</p>
            <p>Now the contrary currant
<pb facs="tcp:1409:3"/> perſwaſion, That Scripturs are cleare and perſpicuous in all points of Controuerſy, and their true ſenſe apparent &amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uious to euery ſimple man, that shall attentiuely peruſe the Text; hath opened a wide gap for all Hereſyes to enter into Chriſtendome, rending in pee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ees the Peace &amp; Vnity therof, and depriuing the ſame of all meanes by which Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tentions may be brought to ſome finall end. For men being once per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded, that they ſee the Truth in all points of Religion con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerted, no leſie cleerly shi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in the Holy Scriptures, then the Sunne doth at noone
<pb facs="tcp:1409:4"/> day; they muſt needs condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, as erring, &amp; wanting the light of Gods ſpirit, all others that shal vnderſtand the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures otherwiſe then they do. And this ſo peremptorily, as they will contemne the ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce of any Paſtour or Paſtours, that shal ſit in iudgment vpon the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſy.</p>
            <p>This preſumption of light to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the Scriptures a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue their Elders, ſo much proclaymed in Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, makes our Aduerſaryes diſagree implacably, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out hope of reconcilement, not only fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs, but alſo betweene themſelues: Yea (as a Proteſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t
<pb facs="tcp:1409:4"/> of great name, well acquainted<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Hook. Eccleſ. folis. pag.</hi> 119.</note> with the proceedings of their Churches, complaines) <q rend="margQuotes">this conceit hath made thouſands ſo headſtrong, euen in groſſe &amp; palpable errors; that a man, whoſe capacity will ſcarſe ſerue him to vtter fiue words in ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible manner, blusheth not, in any doubt concerning matter of Scripture, to thinke his own bare <hi>Yea,</hi> as good as the <hi>Nay</hi> of all the wiſe, graue, and learned iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts that are in the whol world: which Inſolency muſt be repreſſed, or it willbe the bane of Chriſtian Religion.</q> Thus he.</p>
            <p>This inſolent doctrine is
<pb facs="tcp:1409:5"/> in this Treatiſe ſolidely, brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; perſpicuouſly confuted, and the neceſſity of a liuing Iudge, aſſiſted by Gods ſpecial prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce infailibly to decide the Controuerſyes of Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, is ſo cleerly demonſtrated, that I conceaue great hope, that many by the peruſal ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, will caſt off the foreſayd proud Hereticall perſwaſion, which themſelues are forced to confeſſe to be the bane of Chri<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtianity. I pray God this my wish may take effect, and thou that art a Chriſtian, reape as much comfort by the reading thereof, as I wish vnto thee.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:1409:5"/>
            <head>OF THE IVDGE OF CONTROVERSIES.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>EERE We treat of the Iudge of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies in matters concerning Faith &amp; Religion: about which we Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes, and our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries do differ. Our Aduerſaries for the moſt part do hould, that Scripture alone is the Rule and Iudge of all Controuerſies in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of faith and religion: And that out of it alone all controuerſies Whatſoeuer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:1409:6"/> may be decided and ended, without any other Traditions, or authority of the Church. This they proue three wayes.</p>
            <p>Firſt becauſe God in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment did ſend the Iewes to Scripture only, as vnto their Iudge; for we reade<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 20</note> in the Prophet <hi>Iſaias: To the law and teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony.</hi> The ſame alſo doth Chriſt in the<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Ioan.</hi> 5. 39.</note> new, when he ſayth, <hi>Search the Scriptures.</hi> And the men of <hi>Beroea</hi> followed this counſell of Chriſt, of whom it is written, <hi>that they were daily ſearching the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Act.</hi> 17. 11.</note> 
               <hi>Scriptures if theſe things were ſo.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly becauſe God in the ould Teſtament hath commanded that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing ſhould be added to the Scripture,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 2.</note> 
               <hi>you shall not ad to the word</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that I ſpeake to you.</hi> And againe, <hi>VVhat I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Deut</hi> 12. 32.</note> 
               <hi>thee, that only do to our Lord: neither adde any thing nor diminish.</hi> Likewiſe Chriſt him ſelfe and his Apoſtles, in the new Law do condemne all Traditions, &amp; will haue vs to be ſatisfied with Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only; as in <hi>S. Matthew, You haue</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Mat.</hi> 15. 6.</note> 
               <hi>made fruſtrate the commandement of God for your Tradition.</hi> And againe. <hi>I perſecuted the</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Galat.</hi> 1. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Church of God</hi> (ſayth S. Paul) <hi>being more
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:1409:6"/> aboundantly an emulatour of the traditions of my ſore-fathers.</hi> And alſo: <hi>Beware leaſt any</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Colloſſ.</hi> 2. 8.</note> 
               <hi>man ſeduce you by Philoſophy, and vaine fallacy according to the tradition of men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, becauſe <hi>S. Paul</hi> plainly doth confeſſe, that only Scripture by it ſelfe is ſufficient, when he ſaith, <hi>All</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</note> 
               <hi>ſcripture inſpired of God, is profitable to teach, to argue, to conuert, to instruct in iustice: that the man of God may be perfect, inſtructed to euery good worke.</hi> And the ſame Apoſtle accurſeth them who thinke that any thing ought to be added to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. <hi>If any</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>Euangelize to you beſides that which you haue receiued, be he ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thema.</hi> The ſame alſo <hi>S. Iohn</hi> doth wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>I teſtify</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>to euery one hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the words of the Propheſy of this booke, if any man shall ad to theſe things, God shall ad vpon him the plagues written in this booke.</hi> So far our Aduerſaries.</p>
            <p>But Catholikes make a diſtinction betwixt the Iudge and the Rule. They call that the Iudge which giueth ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence betwixt them that contend. And that the Rule according to the which ſentence is giuen by the Iudge. They ſuppoſing this diſtinction teach three
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:1409:7"/> things. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt that the Church is the Iudge of Controuerſies. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly that the Rule which the Church doth fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low in giuing of ſentence, ought not to be the Scripture only, but ſcripture and tradition togeather. <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly that the Church according to this rule, may pronounce ſentence two wayes: eyther by the Pope<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> who is Head and Paſtour of the Church: or els by generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells approued by him, the which do repreſent the Church. By both which meanes the ſentence cannot but be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible. For neyther is it poſſible that the Pope ſhould erre in faith, to whom it is ſayd in the perſon of <hi>S. Peter, I haue praied for thee, that thy faith may not ſaile:</hi> Neyther the Councells lawfully aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled, by reaſon of the promiſe of Chriſt; <hi>Behould I am with you alwayes, euen to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummation of the world.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now to the end I may the better confirme this opinion and conuince the other, I purpoſe to vſe ſix argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments by the which I will manifeſtly proue that the ſcripture only is not ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient to be the Iudge of all Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. The Firſt ſhalbe taken from the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:1409:7"/> office of a Iudge which cànot be giuen to the Scripture. The ſecond from the Scripture it ſelfe, in the which two things are to be conſidered, the bare letter, and the meaning therof. The <hi>bare letter doth kill,</hi> as the Apoſtle ſayth: the meaning or ſenſe is obſcure and hard to be vnderſtood, and therefore it nec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth ſome other Iudge or interpreter. The third ſhalbe drawne from the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies themſelues which are in que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, for there are ſome controuerſies which cannot be decided by ſcripture ſeing there is no mention at all made of them in the ſcripiture. The fourth ſhalbe taken out from the vſe and practiſe of the old teſtament, in the which not the ſcripture but the high Prieſt is acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged to be Iudge. The fift out of the like vſe and practiſe of the new teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. The ſixt is gathered out of the Analogy or proportion of the Ciuill Iudge, concerning the queſtions and controuerſies which fall out in the ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill gouerment or Common Wealth. For the written law is not the Iudge of ſuch controuerſies, but the Prince or ſome peculiar Iudge appointed by him
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:1409:8"/> or his Counſell.</p>
            <p>Moreouer I will examine the te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimonies of the Scripture, brought in againſt vs in the beginning. By the exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mining of the which I will infer three things. Firſt that ſome of them do ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make for the Catholikes then for the Proteſtants, and eſpecially that of the which moſt of all they bragge and boaſt, <hi>Search the ſcriptures.</hi> Secondly that others of them belong nothing to the matter of which we ſpeake. And laſtly that the Proteſtants, who only ſeeke to obtaine the victory out of the ſcripture, are altogether ignorant of the ſenſe or meaning of it. But now I will begin with our owne arguments.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Scripture alone is not the Iudge of Controuerſies, concerning matters of Fayth and Religion.</head>
               <div n="1" type="argument">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I. ARGVMENT,</hi> Drawne from the Office of a Iudge.</head>
                  <p>THE firſt argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t which is drawn from the office of the Iudge thus I propound. He that is the Iudge betwixt
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:1409:8"/> two at variance, ought in ſuch manner to pronounce the ſentence that both of them may plainly perceiue what the ſentence of the Iudge is, ſo that the one may ſee it is for him, and the other that it is againſt him, otherwiſe the aduer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries will neuer leaue of their conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, but both will ſtill continue de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fending their cauſe. But the Scripture cannot do this, therefore the Scripture cannot be the Iudge of al controuerſies. The Maiot is cleare. The Minor I proue; Becauſe the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and the Caluiniſts for theſe many yeares haue iarred and warred concerning all theſe articles.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The Baptiſme of Children.</item>
                     <item>2. The reall preſence of Chriſt in the Holy Euchariſt.</item>
                     <item>3. Predeſtination.</item>
                     <item>4. The perſon of Chriſt.</item>
                     <item>5. Exorciſmes.</item>
                     <item>6. The number &amp; Canon of books of the Scripture.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And yet notwithſtanding the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture which they would haue to be Iudge, could not hitherto, nor can de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide or put an end to theſe controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. Hitherto it hath neuer beene heard
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:1409:9"/> that euer ſentence was ſo pronounced by the ſcripture, that eyther the <hi>Luthera<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> or the Caluiniſts haue confeſſed, that it was pronounced either againſt the one or the other of them. And this is plaine. For as yet they both go forward, moſt bitterly ſtriuing &amp; contending. Which doubtleſſe they would neuer do, if they did perceiue that the ſentence were plainly giuen in their controuerſies; for then either the parties condemned would ceaſe from contending any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, and ſubmit themſelues to the ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, or els they would appeale to ſome other Iudge, pretending them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues to be vniuſtly condemned. But neither of theſe do neyther.</p>
                  <p>Now therefore that the force of this argument may more plainly ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, two things are to be conſidered: The one is, that the <hi>Lutherans</hi> and <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiniſts</hi> do openly confeſſe, that they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg no other Iudg then ſcripture only. Which they affirme to be plaine, mainfeſt, euident, and ſufficient by it ſelfe to decide all controuerſies what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer in matters of faith and religion, &amp; that no falſity or errour can be found
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:1409:9"/> in it. The other is, that although they haue this Iudge, yet notwithſtanding they obtaine nothing by, it but that their contentions ſtill grow greater, &amp; greater, and they themſelues become more hatefull to each other. Out of which it followes, that eyther the ſcripture hath not hither to pronoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced clearly, euidently, and ſufficiently that ſentence, or if it haue, that eyther the <hi>Lutherans</hi> or the <hi>Caluinists</hi> are very ſtubborne and obſtinate, who will not yield to ſo manifeſt and ſo euident a ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, of which two let them make their choyce.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="argument">
                  <head>
                     <hi>II. ARGVMENT,</hi> Drawne out of the Scripture it ſelfe.</head>
                  <p>IN the Scripture two things are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies to be conſidered, to wit the bare letter, and the ſenſe, euen as in a man, the ſoule and the body. Of theſe two, the holy Apoſtle as ſome inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pret doth ſpeake, when he ſaith, <hi>the letter killeth but the ſpirit quickneth,</hi> as though<note place="margin">21 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 6.</note> he had ſaid, if thou follow the true
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:1409:10"/> meaning and ſenſe of the Scripture, which is like the quickning ſoule and ſpirit, it will helpe thee to ſaluation. But if thou neglect the true and lawfull ſenſe thereof, and ſticke only to the plaine, bare, and outward letter, and ſtriue to make that the meaning and ſenſe, which the bare letter only ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth to import, without doubt very often thou wilt fall into errour; This interpretation <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> doth approue. <hi>Oftentymes</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>O my dearely beloued</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Aug ſer. 7 de temp.</note> 
                     <hi>brethren, I haue admonished your Charity, that in the Leſſons which theſe daies are read in the Church, we ought not to attend only to that which we are taught by the bare letter, but that we must ſeeke faithfully (remouing away the veile of the letter) a true quickning ſpirit: for the Apoſtle ſaith, that the letter killeth, but the ſpirit quickneth. For the vnhappy Iewes, and the more vnhappy Heretikes whilſt they regard the meere ſound of the letter, as a body without the ſoule, ſo they remaine dead, without the quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſpirit</hi> The like he hath in his third booke of Chriſtian doctrine in the 5. Chapter.</p>
                  <p>This preſuppoſed two things are to be proued. The one is that the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:1409:10"/> if we reſpect the bare letter cannot poſſibly be the Iudge of controuerſies. The other is, that albeit we marke alſo the ſenſe and meaning of it, yet neither ſo it can be the Iudge. The former part is certaine, for that which leadeth men into errour and hereſie, cannot be the infallible Iudge of all controuerſies, but the ſcripture if we reſpect the bare letter thereof leadeth men into errour and hereſy, therefore it cannot be the infallible Iudge of controuerſies. The <hi>Maior</hi> is plaine of it ſelfe, becauſe we ſeeke an infallible Iudge to the end we may not erre: therfore that which lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vs into errour is not an infallible Iudge. The <hi>Minor</hi> is euident out of the Apoſtle: becauſe the ſcripture according to the letter killeth, which is as much to ſay, it leadeth vs into errour.</p>
                  <p>So it killed the Iewes who vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood all thoſe things which were fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tould of Chriſt, according vnto the bare letter, and did not perceiue the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſenſe thereof. Of whom the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle ſpeaketh ſaying, <hi>for euen vntill this</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>day when</hi> Moyſes <hi>is read, a veile is put vpon their harts:</hi> that is, yet the Iewes do not
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:1409:11"/> vnderſtand <hi>Moyſes</hi> whom dayly they read, by reaſon that they do not ſearch into the inward ſenſe and meaning of him, but are ſatisfied with the bare let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. Or els more plainly: They do not acknowledg Chriſt, who is hidden in <hi>Moyſes</hi> from their ſight vnder the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ceremonies and ſacrifices euen as vnder a couering veyle. For euen yet they ſticke in the veyle, not conſidering what doth ly hid vnder it.</p>
                  <p>And this is it that Chriſt reprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth in ſaying: <hi>Search the ſcriptures, for you thinke in them to haue life euerlaſting: And the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioan.</hi> 5. 39.</note> 
                     <hi>ſame are they that giue testimony of me, and you will not come to me that you may haue life.</hi> As though he had ſayd, If you deſire to know certainly that I am the <hi>Meſſias</hi> promiſed of God (of whom <hi>Moyſes</hi> and the Prophets haue written) you muſt not only content your ſelues with rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the ſcripture, but alſo ſearch di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligently into the inward ſenſe &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, which lieth hidden vnder the outward letter as vnder a certaine figure and ſhaddow. But this hitherto you haue not practized. For although you be perſwaded that euerlaſting life is to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:1409:11"/> be found in the Scriptures, yet in what particuler manner you are to ſeeke it there, that you may find it, hereof you are altogether ignorant. It is not placed in the outward letter, or in the exter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall figures and ceremonies, as you imagin but in the ſpirit, ſenſe and ſecret miſteries thereof: There ſeeke me, and you ſhall finde me.</p>
                  <p>But the letter killeth not only the Iewes, but alſo the heretikes. For many therefore haue died in their owne er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, becauſe they hauing forſaken the true ſenſe of ſcripture, which the holy &amp; Catholike Church doth follow, tooke hold of another ſenſe according to the outward bare letter. The which I will breifly make plaine by ſetting downe ſome few examples.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Sabellians</hi> held that there were not three diuine perſons of the B. Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity but one only, to the which they gaue three diuers names in regard of three diuers offices or operations. For they called the ſame perſon the Father, the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt but in a diuerſe reſpect. The Father for that he was the author of all crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:1409:12"/> the Sonne becauſe he tooke our humaine nature of the B. Virgin, the holy Ghoſt for that he ſanctified vs, by his euerlaſting grace. Out of their own opinion therefore is neceſſarily infer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that God the Father did dye and ſuffer. For if there be but one perſon which is called the Father, Sonne, and holy Ghoſt, and that perſon did dye &amp; ſuffer, it followeth thereupon that God the father did dye and ſuffer; For this<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug. lib. de h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>r. cap.</hi> 41.</note> opinion they are called by <hi>S. Auguſtine, Patropaſſians:</hi> but from whence procedeth this ſo great an errour? Truly from the letter that killeth. For according to the outward letter they vnderſtood that place of <hi>S. Iohn, I and the Father am one,</hi> that<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioan.</hi> 10. 30.</note> the Father and the Sonne (and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently the holy Ghoſt) were one in perſon, and yet in the ſenſe of the holy Church, although they be but one in nature, yet they are two in perſon.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Arians</hi> ſayd that Chriſt was not God, but inferiour to him. But from whom had they this errour, but becauſe they forſaking the ſenſe of the Church expounded the words of Chriſt<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioan. 14. v.</hi> 28.</note> according to the letter. <hi>The Father</hi> (ſayth
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:1409:12"/> he) <hi>is greater then I,</hi> as if he had meant, to wit the Father is abſolutly and in euery reſpect greater then he. But the ſenſe of<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide Ath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. ora. 2. cont. Arian. Hila. lib. 5. de Trini. Auguſt. lib. 3. cont. Maxi. cap. 24. &amp; 25. &amp; lib. de Trin. c.</hi> 7<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> the Church is that Chriſt according to his humaine nature only is leſſe then God the Father, but equall according to his diuine. In the former ſenſe is that to be vnderſtood, The Father is greater then I: in the other this, I &amp; the Father are one, and ſo all do agree very well together.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Macedonians</hi> did deny the holy Ghoſt to be God, but out of what grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d? Out of the killing letter: for expounding that of the Apoſtle according to the <hi>law the ſpirit ſearcheth all things, yea euen the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fundities</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 2. v.</hi> 10.</note> 
                     <hi>of God.</hi> Wherhence they inferred<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> He that ſearcheth ſeeketh, he that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth doubteth, he that doubteth is ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant, he that is ignorant is not God.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>See Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philact. D. Thoman<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> &amp; others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vpon that place. 1. Paral. 28. v. 9. Pſal. 7 10. Iere.</hi> 17. 10.</note> Therefore the holy Ghoſt is not God. But the Church interpreteth that place thus. <hi>The ſpirit ſearcheth all,</hi> that is, doth penetrate orpiere and comprehend all. In the which ſenſe God the Father alſo is ſayd to ſearch all. <hi>God doth ſearch the harts of all. God ſearching the harts and reynes. I the Lord ſearching harts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="16" facs="tcp:1409:13"/>
                  <p>The <hi>Manichees</hi> did affirme that the ould Teſtament was contrary to the new, and wherfore? Becauſe they ſquared all according to the outward letter, into the which only if we looke, the one may ſeeme to diſagree with the<note place="margin">Gen 1. 1. Ioan. 1. 3. Gen 1. 27. Ioan. 8. v. 44. Gen. 2. 2. Ioan. 5. 17. Auguſt. lib. cont. Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mant.</note> other. For the old ſayth that <hi>God created all things;</hi> the new, that <hi>the VVord created all.</hi> Againe the old ſayth, that <hi>God made man according to his image.</hi> But the new that <hi>man is of the diuell.</hi> In like manner the old ſayth that <hi>God did reſt the ſeauenth day from all his worke.</hi> The new, <hi>that God worketh vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till now.</hi> But <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> ſhe weth out of the ſenſe of the Catholike Church how all theſe places agree well together, the which ſeeme to be contrary according to the letter. For it doth not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ugne that God made all, &amp; notwithſtanding that alſo all were made by the Word, as by the arte and example of God. Neither doth it repugne, that man was made according to the image of God in reſpect of his nature, and neuertheleſſe was of the diuell in reſpect of his ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lice, and that God did ceaſe the ſeauenth day from the worke of creating the world, yet now doth alwayes worke
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:1409:13"/> in gouerning, and conſeruing the world.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Pelagians</hi> did deny originall ſinne, affirming that the ſinne of <hi>Adam</hi> did only hurt himſelfe, but not his poſterity. But from whence do they proue this? Out of the bare letter that killeth, becauſe it is written, that <hi>the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ezech.</hi> 18. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>child shall not carry the iniquity of his Father.</hi> But the true ſenſe of this place, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the expoſition of the Catholike<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide Aug. in lib. poſt. collation. cap.</hi> 7.</note> Church, is, that the ſonne who is not partaker of the ſinne of his Father, ſhall not carry the iniquity of his Father. But if he be partaker of it he ſhall of neceſſity carry it. But now it is certaine that all <hi>Adams</hi> poſterity were partakers of his ſinne, according to that of <hi>S. Paul, in whom all ſinned.</hi> But in what manner<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> all ſinned in <hi>Adam,</hi> is to be taught in another place: yet here in the meane tyme I ſay that all ſinned in <hi>Adam,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe God conditioned with him as with the firſt origen, common roore &amp; head of his whole poſterity, that if the commandement which God had giuen him, to wit that he ſhould not taſte of the fruit forbidden, both he and his
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:1409:14"/> poſterity ſhould remaine in Paradiſe, but if not, then both he and all his poſterity being guilty &amp; tranſgreſſours of Gods law ſhould be caſt out of para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, which afterwards ſo fell out.</p>
                  <p>There were alſo ſome ancient He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>retikes, who altogether denied the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of our fleſh, becauſe they found it written, <hi>It is the ſpirit that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, the flesh profiteth nothing.</hi> Which place<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioan:</hi> 6. 63</note> they vnderſtanding only according to the outward letter, not ſearching any<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Refert. Tertull. in lib dereſur. car. c.</hi> 37.</note> further into the inward ſenſe and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning thereof, argued in this manner: To what purpoſe ſhould the fleſh riſe at all, ſith it profiteth nothing? And out of the ſelfe ſame place the <hi>Caluiniſts</hi> conclude againſt another verity. To what purpoſe (ſay they) ſhould Chriſt impart to vs his fleſh in the Euchariſt, if the fleſh profit nothing? But truly they both are deceaued by looking only into the bare letter which killeth: O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe one might conclude in like manner, if the fleſh doth profit nothing<note place="margin">Vide Mal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>donatum in cap. 6. Ioan.</note> at all, to what end did Chriſt take fleſh to redeeme man? To what end was the word made fleſh? To what end did he
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:1409:14"/> ſuffer in it vpon the Croſſe? Certainly he did not all this to no purpoſe.</p>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>That the Scripture according to the ſenſe and meaning thereof, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be Iudge.</head>
                     <p>BVT this being ſufficient about the former part, where it is manifeſt both by the authority of the Apoſtles and alſo by diuers ſundry examples, that the Scripture if we reſpect only the bare and outward letter thereof, cannot be the infallible Iudge in matters of Controuerſy, becauſe that the bare let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter killeth, and bredeth great errours and hereſies: But now let vs proceed to the latter part of this our argument, wherein I wil declare, that if we regard the very ſenſe and meaning of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the ſame can be noe competent Iudge of all Controuerſies in matters of fayth and Religion. The which I proue in this manner: The Scriptures according vnto the true ſenſe thereof often tymes is obſcure, and very hard to be vnderſtood, &amp; oftentymes about diſcerning the true ſenſe and meaning
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:1409:15"/> of it great Controuerſies do ariſe. But euery Controuerſy doth require ſome iudge to determine the ſame, it is there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore neceſſary that ſome Iudge be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poynted who certainly may determine which is the true ſenſe of the Scripture, which cannot be the Scripture it ſelfe, for of the ſenſe and meaning thereof there is Controuerſy: and therefore it is neceſſary that ſome other be aſſigned beſides the Scripture. In this diſcourſe are certain principles grounded, which are to be explicated and proued in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticuler one after another. The firſt is.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>That the Scripture often tymes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the ſenſe, is obſcure &amp; hard to be vnderstood.</head>
                     <p>THIS <hi>S. Peter</hi> doth teſtify in his later Canonicall Epiſtle, where ſpeaking of the Epiſtles of <hi>S. Paul</hi> he<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet. 3. 16. Luc.</hi> 24. 27.</note> vſeth theſe wordes. <hi>In the which</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>there are ſome things hard to be vnderſtood.</hi> Alſo it may be confirmed diuers waies. Firſt by the example of the diſciples going vnto <hi>Emaus,</hi> who vnderſtanding not the Scriptures, were taught by Chriſt.
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:1409:15"/> Secondly by the <hi>Eunuch</hi> in the 8. Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Acts 13. verſe, who being asked of <hi>S. Philip,</hi> whether he vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> which he was then reading, anſwered in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner, <hi>How can I</hi> (ſayd he) <hi>vnleſſe ſome man shew</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 8. 31.</note> 
                        <hi>me.</hi> Thirdly by the example of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles, who vnderſtood not many<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 13. 36.</note> things which Chriſt had taught them. For his Diſciples coming to him ſayd,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat,</hi> 16. 11.</note> 
                        <hi>expound vs the Parable of the Cockle ſeede.</hi> Againe, <hi>why do you not vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d that I ſayd not</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc.</hi> 18. 34.</note> 
                        <hi>of bread to you? and they vnderſtood none of theſe things, and this word was hid from them, &amp; they vnderſtood not the things th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t were ſayd.</hi> Fourthly by the common conſent of all the interpreters. For if the Scripture were eaſy, what neede were there of ſo many interpreters? ſo many com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentaries? ſo many queſtions and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies. Fiftly by many particuler places and bookes of Scripture I proue it hard: For who doth not perceaue <hi>Ezechiels</hi> propheſy about the viſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the foure beaſts to be moſt obſcure? Moreo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it plainly appeareth <hi>Daniels</hi> propheſy of the 70. weekes, and of the abhomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of deſolation to be moſt hard,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:1409:16"/> ſith that in the ſearching into it and in the explaining of it, it hath hitherto &amp; euen yet doth put many to their wits end, as concerning the which Chriſt himſelfe ſayd, <hi>he that readeth let him vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 24. 15.</note> Furthermore euen in the whole Apocalips of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> many obſcure pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces and full of ſecret myſteries may be found. And <hi>S. Hierom</hi> alſo affirmeth in a certaine epiſtle of his to <hi>Paulinus,</hi> that in it there are as many Sacraments or ſecret myſteries as wordes.</p>
                     <p>But that in the other bookes of Scripture alſo, many obſcure and diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cult places are to be found, is wel known to ſuch as read them: &amp; to omit others let them ſpeake who in tymes paſt, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding their daily reading of Scripture with great diligence, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed themſelues to haue beene very ignorant in many paſſages thereof, in which to be inſtructed and reſolued they had re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe to <hi>S. Auguſtine, S. Hierome,</hi> and other moſt learned Fathers of the Church. Whereof the Epiſtles of the auncient Fathers themſelues do giue ample teſtimony, out of the which I will put downe ſome.</p>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:1409:16"/>
                     <p>We reade then, that Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi> asked counſell of <hi>S. Hierome</hi> about theſe Queſtions.</p>
                     <p>1. What ſignified this, <hi>whoſoeuer shall</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Gen. 4. 15. Epiſt. 124. 125. inter Epiſt. Hiero. Ibidem.</note> 
                        <hi>kill Cain, shalbe punished ſeauen fould.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2. If all things which God had made were very good, to what end did he commaund <hi>Noë</hi> to take into the Arke as well thoſe beaſts which were vncleane, as thoſe which were cleane, ſith that nothing can be good which is vncleane.</p>
                     <p>3. Wherefore did <hi>Abraham</hi> receaue Circumciſion for a ſigne or ſeale of his fayth? And wherefore did <hi>Iſaac</hi> though<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> a iuſt man, and deare to God, deceaued by errour, bleſſe not whom he would, but whom he would not.</p>
                     <p>4. What was the interpretation of <hi>Iſay</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 142.</note> the Prophets viſion, concerning the <hi>Seraphim</hi> and <hi>Triſagio.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Euagrius</hi> asked of the ſame <hi>S. Hierom,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 126.</note> Whether <hi>Melchiſedech</hi> who bleſſed <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> were of a more diuine nature, and not be taken for a man.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Dardanus</hi> alſo inquired as concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 124.</note> this. What that Land of promiſe was from whence the Iewes returning
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:1409:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <pb n="25" facs="tcp:1409:17"/>
                        <pb n="24" facs="tcp:1409:18"/> out of <hi>Aegypt</hi> are ſayd to haue poſſeſſed, ſeing that it could not be <hi>Paleſtine,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe that was poſſeſſed of their aunce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtours before, and might ſeeme rather to be reſerued then promiſed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Vital<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> demaunded of the ſame great<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 132.</note> Doctour; Whether it were true which we find recorded in Scripture, that <hi>Salomon</hi> and <hi>Achaz</hi> begat children when they were but eleuen yeares ould.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 39.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Cyprian</hi> asked what was the true ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition of that moſt hard Pſalme, which beginneth thus: <hi>Domine refugium factus es nobis.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Marcella</hi> a noble woman of <hi>Rome</hi> amo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>g others propoſed theſe queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s to him.</p>
                     <p>1. What <hi>Ephodbad,</hi> &amp; <hi>Teraphim</hi> ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 130.</note> in the <hi>Hebrew</hi> tongue?</p>
                     <p>2. What was the ſignification, of<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 137.</note> 
                        <hi>Alleluia, Amen Maranatha?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>3. What was <hi>Diapſalma.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt. 138. Epiſt.</hi> 141.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>4. Wha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> was <hi>Panisdoloris?</hi> what <hi>filij excuſſorum,</hi> of the which is made menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in the 126. pſalme.</p>
                     <p>5. What are thoſe things which neither eye hath ſeene, nor eare hath heard, nor haue aſcended into the hart of man, which God hath prepared for
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:1409:18"/> them that loue him. And how againe<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 148.</note> the Apoſtle doth inſer: But God by the holy Ghoſt hath reueiled vnto vs. And if it were reueiled to the Apoſtle, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he alſo did repeale it to others.</p>
                     <p>6. When the Apoſtle ſayth: <hi>Then</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 4. 17<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>we that liue, that are left, withall shalbe taken vp together with them in the clouds to meete Chriſt into the ayre.</hi> Whether this is to be vnderſtood of ſome that went to hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen with Chriſt before they dyed, ſeing that <hi>Henoch</hi> and <hi>Elias</hi> ſhall die, as it is ſaid<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> in the Apocalips of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> leaſt that any may not be ſayd to dye.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Principia</hi> a Virgin of <hi>Rome</hi> deſired of<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 140.</note> him the expoſition of that pſalme, <hi>Eru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctauit cor meum verbum bonum.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 135.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sunia</hi> and <hi>Fretella</hi> requeſted by wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting whether in that Contention in the which the <hi>Latins</hi> diſſent from the <hi>Grecians</hi> concerning Dauids Pſalter, the Iewes agree more with the <hi>Grecians</hi> the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with the <hi>Latins.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hedibia</hi> a noble woman of <hi>France</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 150.</note> ſent to <hi>S. Hierom</hi> by a Pilgrime to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe theſe doubts.</p>
                     <p>1. How that place of Chriſt ſhould<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 26. 29</note> be vnderſtood, to wit, <hi>I will not drinke from
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:1409:19"/> henceforth of this fruit of the vine, vntill that</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                        <hi>day when I shall drinke it with you new in the Kingdome of my Father.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2. Wherefore <hi>S. Mathew</hi> ſayd, that Chriſt roſe in the euening, and <hi>S. Marck</hi> in the morning.</p>
                     <p>3. What that ſignified which was<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> written in <hi>S. Mathew: the veile of the temple was rent into two peeces from the top euen to the bottome?</hi> And that which followeth.</p>
                     <p>4. How it happened that Chriſt, in <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> breathed the holy Ghoſt v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon his Apoſtles, and yet we reade in <hi>S. Luke</hi> that he promiſed to ſend them the holy Ghoſt after his Aſcenſion.</p>
                     <p>5. How that of the Apoſtle is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpreted, <hi>what shall we ſay then? Is their</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Ibid.</note> 
                        <hi>iniquity with God? God forbid:</hi> and all to the other place, <hi>vnleſſe the Lord of Saboath</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 14.</note> 
                        <hi>had leſt vs ſeede, we had beene made like So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Algaſia</hi> alſo another French woman by the ſame <hi>Pilgrime</hi> propounded theſe other doubts vnto him.</p>
                     <p>1. Wherefore did <hi>S. Iohn</hi> ſend his diſciples to Chriſt to aske him: <hi>Ar thou</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 151.</note> 
                        <hi>he who art about to come, or do we expect ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther?</hi> Sith that he before that tyme, had
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:1409:19"/> ſpoken of Chriſt, ſaying: <hi>Behold the lambe of God, behold who taketh away the ſinnes of the world.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibid. Math.</hi> 12. 20.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>2. What Chriſt did meane by theſe wordes. <hi>The reede bruiſed he shall not breake, and ſmoaking flax he shall not extinguish.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>3. What alſo is the meaning of<note place="margin">Ibid. Math. 16. 24. Ibid. Math. 24. 19. Ibid.</note> our Sauiour ſaying. <hi>If any will come after me, let him deny himſelfe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>4. How is to be vnderſtood that he ſayth: Woe to them that are with child, and that giue ſuck in thoſe daies.</p>
                     <p>5. In what ſenſe that place of <hi>S. Luke</hi> is to be taken. <hi>And it came to paſſe whiles the dayes of his aſſumption were accom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plishing, and he fixed his face to go into Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi> And a little after where he ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth of the Sacraments. <hi>And they receiued him, not becauſe his face was to go to Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>6. Who was the Bayliffe of iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibid. Rom.</hi> 5. 7.</note> whom our Lord praiſed.</p>
                     <p>7. What the Apoſtle meant when he ſayd. <hi>For ſcarce for a iuſt man doth any die: for perhaps for a good man durst ſome man did.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibid. Rom.</hi> 7. 8.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>8. What the ſenſe was of that ſpeach of <hi>S. Paul. But occaſion being taken,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:1409:20"/> ſinne by the commandement wrought in me all Concupiſcenſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But now omitting many and diuers ſuch like queſtions of Scripture, which were brought to <hi>S. Hierome</hi> to be reſolued out of many parts of the Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world, I come to <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> to whom no fewer were brought then to the other.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Voluſianus</hi> asked his counſell in this,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. Epiſt.</hi> 2.</note> How the immortall God could be ſhut vp in the wombe of a virgin: And whether in the meane tyme he left of all eare of the world.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Marcellinus</hi> asked him, wherefore<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt. 4. &amp;</hi> 5.</note> God did alter the Sacrifices of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> which he had once before ordained? ſith that thoſe things which are once ordained well ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be altered but vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iuſtly.</p>
                     <p>The ſame <hi>Marcellinus</hi> propounded<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 7.</note> vnto him this other queſtion alſo. How it came to paſſe, that the Magitians of <hi>Pharao</hi> could find any water to change into bloud, ſith that before that tyme all the water of <hi>Aegypt</hi> was changed into bloud by <hi>Moyſes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Bonifacius</hi> the Biſhop alſo asked him
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:1409:20"/> this queſtion, Wherefore the fayth of parents is profitable for their children in baptiſme, ſeeing that their impiety after their Baptiſme is nothing hurtfull to them? And how the God fathers, in Baptiſme could promiſe that the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants beleeue, ſith they do not then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue, and it is vncertaine whether euer they will beleeue or no.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Dardanus.</hi> How it may be beleeued<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 23.</note> that Chriſt is now in heauen, ſeing he ſayd to the thiefe vpon the Croſſe: This day thou ſhalt be with me in Paradiſe:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt.</hi> 57.</note> And whether from hence do follow that Chriſt, God and man, is euery where.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Paulinus.</hi> What is that which is ſaid<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt. 58. &amp;</hi> 59.</note> in the 15. Pſalme, <hi>Sanctisqui ſunt in terra eius mirific<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> omnes voluntates me as inter illes.</hi> To the Saints that are in his land he hath made all my wills meruailous in<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 67. 22.</note> them. In like manner what is the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of that in the Pſalme: <hi>Veruntamen &amp;c.</hi> But yet God wil breake the heads of his enemies: the hairy crowne of them that walke in their ſinnes.</p>
                     <p>Likewiſe when the Apoſtle ſayth:<note place="margin">Epiſt. 4. 11. Ibid.</note> 
                        <hi>He gaue ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:1409:21"/> ſome Euangeliſts and ſome Paſtours &amp; Doctours:</hi> His Queſtion was how theſe names might be diſtinguiſhed, and alſo what office and function was due to each one: What office for the Apoſtles, what for the Prophets, what for the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts, and what for Paſtours and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctours.</p>
                     <p>Moreouer he asked him this, that<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibidem. 1. Tim.</hi> 2. 1.</note> ſeing the Apoſtle writeth, <hi>I deſire there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, firſt of all, that obſecrations prayers, postu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, thankſgiuings be made for all men,</hi> what difference could be made in theſe wordes.</p>
                     <p>Alſo what that ſignified, that the<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibid. Rom.</hi> 11. 28.</note> Apoſtle ſayth of the Iewes: <hi>According to the Ghoſpell indeed enemies for you, but accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the election moſt deare for the Fathers.</hi> Againe. What that other place of <hi>S. Paul</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibid. Colo.</hi> 2. 18.</note> meant: <hi>Let no man ſeduce you, willing in the humility and religion of Angells, walking in the things which he hath not ſeene, in vaine puffed vp by the ſenſe of his flesh,</hi> and not holding the head.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Euodius</hi> the Biſhop asked of him,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt. 98. &amp; 99. 1. Pet.</hi> 3. 19.</note> what ſpirit it was of whom <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſpake, in his firſt Canonicall Epiſt. <hi>In the which ſpirit comming he preached to them
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:1409:21"/> alſo that were in priſon.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Epiſt. 120. Pſal.</hi> 120.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Honoratus</hi> alſo, what that ſpeach of our Lord ſignified, <hi>Deus Deus meus, quare me dereliquisti.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Moreouer how that other place of<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibid. Eph.</hi> 3. 17.</note> 
                        <hi>S. Paul</hi> was interpreted: <hi>Rooted and founded in Charity, that you may be able to comprehend withall the Saints, what is the breadth, and length, and height, and depth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Who were alſo the fiue fooliſh Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gins, and who were the wiſe. <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. 2.</p>
                     <p>Againe, what was the outward<note place="margin">Ibid.</note> darkneſſe <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 13. And how that place of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> was vnderſtood, <hi>the word was made flesh. Ioan.</hi> 1. 14.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Simplicianus</hi> asked him, what that<note place="margin">
                           <hi>lib 1. ad Simpli. quaeſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Rom.</hi> 7. 7.</note> place of the Apoſtle meant, where he ſayth, <hi>VVhat shall we ſay then? is the law ſinne? God forbid:</hi> and to that, <hi>vnhappy man that I am, who shall deliuer me from the body of this death.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibid. quaeſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap> Rom. 9. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> lib. 2. quaeſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. 1. Reg. 10. 10. 1. Reg.</hi> 16. 24.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>What was the meaning of that in <hi>S. Paul: But Rebecca conceiuing of one copula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Iſaac our Father,</hi> and all the reſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward to that, <hi>Vnleſſe the Lord of Saboath had left vs ſeed.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And how it is ſayd in one place that, <hi>the ſpirit of our Lord ſeized vpon Saul,</hi>
                        <pb n="32" facs="tcp:1409:22"/> ſeing in another place it is written, <hi>that a wicked ſpirit vexed him.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibid. queſt. 2. 1 Reg. 15. 21. Ibid. quaeſt.</hi> 3.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>And in what ſenſe it is ſayd by God in the booke of Kings, <hi>it repenteth me that I haue made Saul King.</hi> And againe. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther that vncleane ſpirit which was in <hi>Pythoniſſa</hi> could make <hi>Samuel</hi> who was dead before come to ſee <hi>Saul,</hi> and ſpeake with him?</p>
                     <p>Alſo he asked him as concerning<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibid. quaeſt. 5. 3. Reg.</hi> 17. 20.</note> that ſpeach of <hi>Elias, O my Lord, what euen the VVidow alſo by whom I am after a ſort ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteyned haſt thou afflicted, that thou would st kill her ſonne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Now by theſe queſtions it appeareth manifeſtly that the Scripture in many places is obſcure and hard to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood. And that many moſt learned men of whom we haue here made mention confeſſed themſelues not to vnderſtand many things without being inſtructed by more learned then themſelues. Now therefore let vs go forward in explica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting what may be the cauſes of ſo great obſcurity.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="33" facs="tcp:1409:22"/>
                     <head>What are the cauſes why the Scripture is obſcure?</head>
                     <p>I find two cauſes eſpecially. The one is drawne from the things them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues which are treated of in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The other from the manner of treating of them. The things of the which the Scripture treateth, are of foure kindes. 1. Hiſtories, as in the booke of <hi>Geneſis, Exodus, Numeri, Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teronomi, Ioſue,</hi> the bookes of <hi>Iudges,</hi> of <hi>Kings, Paralipomenon, Eſdras, Iudith, Tobias, Hester,</hi> the <hi>Machabees,</hi> &amp; alſo the Ghoſpel, and the Acts of the Apoſtles. Secondly Propheſies, ſuch as for the moſt part are contained in the pſalmes, in the greater and leſſer Prophets, and in the Apocalips of <hi>S. Iohn.</hi> Thirdly miſteries of our faith, eſpecially about the bleſſed Trinity, the Incarnation of Chriſt, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout predeſtination, and reprobation, about the force and efficacy of the holy Sacraments, about the preſence of Chriſt in the Euchariſt, about iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fayth, about the Reſurection of the dead, &amp; ſuch like other poynts. Fourth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:1409:23"/> Precepts and morall documents, as concerning vertues and vices. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit that neyther in theſe, nor in hiſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, there is perchance any great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcurity in regard of the things treated of; yet notwithſtanding there is great obſcurity in the propheſies, and miſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of fayth. For theſe are aboue mans capacity and vnderſtanding, ſo that we<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 13. 12.</note> cannot perceiue them but after a darke manner, as the Apoſtle ſayth.</p>
                     <p>Now the manner of treating of theſe things oftentymes is obſcure, for theſe cauſes. Firſt becauſe there be ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny improper ſpeaches in the Scripture as figures, allegories and parables, vnder the whichly hidden many truthes, the which are not preſently vnderſtood of the reader.</p>
                     <p>Alſo the obſcurity thereof is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by ſome word, which is taken ſometymes in the ſame ſentence, one while properly, and another while fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guratiuely: as in this place for example. <hi>Euery one that drinketh of this water shall</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan.</hi> 4. 13.</note> 
                        <hi>thirſt againe, but he that shall drinke of the water that I will giue him, shall not thirſt for euer.</hi> Where to drinke of water, and to thirſt,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:1409:23"/> in the former part of the ſentence, is taken corporally, and in the latter part ſpiritually. And againe in the very ſame Chapter. <hi>Do not you ſay, that yet there are</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ibid. v.</hi> 35.</note> 
                        <hi>foure monthes, and harueſt cometh? Behould, I ſay to you, lift vp your eyes, and ſee the countries that they are white already to harueſt.</hi> For heare in the firſt place, the word har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueſt is taken in it proper ſignification, but in the latter figuratiuely.</p>
                     <p>And againe in the ſame Apoſtle.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan.</hi> 9. 39<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> For iudgment came I into this word: that they that ſee not may ſee: and they that ſee may become blind: where the former part is taken for corporall ſight, and the latter for ſpirituall.</p>
                     <p>And in <hi>S. Paul: Him who knew no ſinne,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 5. 21.</note> 
                        <hi>for vs, he hath made ſinne.</hi> Where ſinne in one place is taken properly for ſinne, but in the other place figuratiuely for a ſacrifice offered for ſinne: for the ſenſe<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Vide. Orig 3. com. in. Epiſt. ad Rom. &amp; Augu. lib. 2. de conſen. Euangeliſt. cap.</hi> 30.</note> of that place is, that it was Gods will that Chriſt who neuer had ſinned, ſhould be a ſacrifice for the ſinne of mankind.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, not only figures are found in the words, as I haue already ſhewed, but alſo in the very things themſelues.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1409:24"/> For one thing oftentymes is a figure &amp; type of another ſignified by it: euen as the Paſchall Lambe was a figure of Chriſt, the red Sea of Baptiſme, <hi>Manna</hi> of the Euchariſt, <hi>Mont Sio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                        </hi> of the Church, and ſo of others. From hence doth pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed a triple obſcurity.</p>
                     <p>Firſt it doth not ſtraight appeare of which thing another thing is a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure, for example ſake: <hi>Agar Abraham</hi> his mayd to haue beene a figure of the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue, and <hi>Sara Abrahams</hi> wife to<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Galat.</hi> 4. 14.</note> haue beene a figure of the Church, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe the Apoſtle by the inſtinct of the holy Ghoſt had explicated them ſo. Likewiſe how ſhould it haue beene<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ierem.</hi> 1. 11.</note> knowne, that the waking rod ſignified the ſpeedy execution of Gods diuine ſentence againſt the Iewes &amp; Gentils. And that the burning pot was a figure<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ierem. 13. Ierem.</hi> 16. 2.</note> of <hi>Nabuchodonoſor.</hi> And that <hi>Ieremy</hi> who was forbidden to marry a wife, was a figure of the ſpoyles hanging ouer Iewry. And that by the chalice of the fury of our Lord, the power and fury of<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iere.</hi> 15. 15.</note> the King of <hi>Babilon</hi> was ſignified: and by arotten girdle the ruine of the people<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iere. 13. v.</hi> 1.</note> in Captiuity. And by the Flagon to be
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:1409:24"/> filled with wyne, the inhabitants of <hi>Hieruſalem</hi> to be made drunke with the<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iere,</hi> 13. 12.</note> wyne of the fury of our Lord. And by the two baskets of the beſt and worſt figgs two kynd of men, of whom ſome were happy who paſt ouer with the King, ſome miſerable and vnhappy who remayned behind in <hi>Hieruſalem.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iere. 24. v. 2. Iere.</hi> 18. 6.</note> And by the clay in the potters hand, the people of the Iewes in the hand of God. And by the chaynes and fetters of <hi>Ieremy</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iere.</hi> 27. 2.</note> the captiuity of diuers nations. And by the breaking of the earthen pot, the cruſhing of the people and the Citty of <hi>Ieruſalem.</hi> And by the foure beaſts, four Kingdomes, and Empires. And by the<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iere. 19. 10<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Dan. 7. v. 3. Dan.</hi> 8. 20.</note> Ramme the king of the <hi>Medians</hi> &amp; <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſians.</hi> And by the Goate the king of the <hi>Grecians.</hi> Theſe I ſay, and many ſuch would neuer haue beene ſo vnderſtood vnleſſe they had beene declared parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culerly by God, and after this declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion alſo without an interpreter they can be ſcarce vnderſtood.</p>
                     <p>The other obſcurity doth ariſe v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon this, that one thing ſomtymes is a figure of diuers things which are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary and repugnant one to another.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:1409:25"/>
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:1409:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                        <pb n="36" facs="tcp:1409:26"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="37" facs="tcp:1409:26"/>
                        <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                           <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:1409:27"/> As <hi>Ionas</hi> was the figure of Chriſt: For as <hi>Ionas</hi> was in the belly of the Whale three daies and three nights, ſo ſhall the ſonne of man be in the hart of the earth three dayes and three nights. The ſame <hi>Ionas</hi> was the figure of the people of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> who were contrary to Chriſt: For as <hi>Ion<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </hi> did greiue at the Conuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ion. 4. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. Auguſt. Epiſt. 49. quaeſt.</hi> 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> of the <hi>Nimuits,</hi> euen ſo the Iewes in the Conuerſion of the Gentills. That which is ſayd of <hi>Ionas,</hi> may be ſayd alſo of the deluge, of the Rock, and ſuch like. For the Deluge was both the figure of<note place="margin">Aug ep. 99. ad Euo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dium.</note> the Baptiſme of the faythfull, and to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geather the type of the puniſhment of the vnfaythfull. And the Rock which<note place="margin">1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 8.</note> is Chriſt, was the ſtone of ſcandall and offence to them that periſh, and to<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom. 9. v.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>2.</note> them that beleeue the Corner-ſtone.</p>
                     <p>The laſt obſcurity ariſeth vpon this, that ſomtimes one certayne thing which is the figure of another doth re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent the ſame in one reſpect, and is altogether vnlike vnto it in another. As for example the fornicating woman whom the Prophet <hi>Oſeas</hi> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded to marry, was a figure of the Sinagogue, which ſhe repreſented in
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:1409:27"/> this, to wit, that as ſhe had committed carnall fornication, ſo the Sinagogue had committed ſpirituall, which did conſiſt in the worſhiping of Idolls. But in this it did diſagree, that ſhe after her marriage to <hi>Oſeas</hi> did neuer returne to her former carnall fornication, as many probably do affirme. But the Sinagogue after ſhe was reconciled to God fell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine into Idolatry.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly in the Scripture are to be found many apparent contradictions which cannot but breed great difficulty in the mynd of the reader: of many I will relate ſome.</p>
                     <p>1. <hi>Moyſes</hi> ſayth, that God created<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> heauen and earth in ſix dayes and reſted the ſeauenth; but in the eighteene of<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccleſ. cap.</hi> 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> 
                        <hi>Eccleſiast.</hi> it is ſayd, <hi>who liueth for euer did create altogeather.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>2. <hi>Moyſes</hi> tells vs, that the children<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen. 15. 3. Acts 7. Galat.</hi> 3 17.</note> of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were in <hi>Aegypt</hi> foure hundred yeares. But the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>that they were there foure hundred thirty yeares.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>3. <hi>Iacob</hi> the Patriarch ſayth: I haue<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 32. 30.</note> ſeene God face to face, and my ſoule was ſaued. But we haue the contrary <hi>Exod.</hi> 33. 20. for God ſayth, <hi>man shall
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:1409:28"/> not ſee me and liue.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>4. In <hi>Exod. 20. v.</hi> 5. it is ſayd, I am thy Lord God viſiting the iniquity of the Fathers vpon the children vnto the third and fourth generation of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary is found in <hi>Ezechiel: The ſonne shall not carry the iniquity of his Father.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>5. Honour thy Father, and thy<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Exod. 20. 12. Luc. 14. v.</hi> 26.</note> Mother that thou maiſt liue long vpon the earth: but contrary to this Chriſt ſayth, <hi>who doth not hate his Father, and his Mother, cannot be my Diſciple.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>6. Thou ſhalt feare thy Lord God<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut. 6. 3. Math.</hi> 5. 34.</note> and ſweare by his name. Which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that: <hi>But I ſay to you, do not ſweare at all.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>7. It repenteth me that I haue made<note place="margin">1. <hi>Reg. 15. 11. Rom.</hi> 11. 29.</note> 
                        <hi>Saul</hi> King: contrary to that, without repentance are the gifts and vocation of God.</p>
                     <p>8. In the Arke there was nothing<note place="margin">3. <hi>Reg.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 9.</note> els but two tables of ſtone which <hi>Moyſes</hi> put in it in Horeb; contrary to that of<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Hebr.</hi> 9. 4.</note> 
                        <hi>S Paul:</hi> In the Arke there was a goulden pot hauing <hi>Manna,</hi> and the rod of <hi>Aaron</hi> that had bloſſomed, and the tables of the Teſtament.</p>
                     <p>9. The impious ſhall not riſe in<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. 5.</note>
                        <pb n="41" facs="tcp:1409:28"/> iudgment; contrary to that: we ſhall<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 15. v.</hi> 51.</note> all indeed riſe againe, but we ſhall not all be changed.</p>
                     <p>10. God hath ſpoken once; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal. 6. 12. Hebr.</hi> 1. 1.</note> to that: diuerſly and many wayes in tymes paſt God ſpake to the Fathers in the Prophets, laſt of all in theſe daies hath ſpoken to vs in his ſonne.</p>
                     <p>11. Euery man is a liar: contrary<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal. 115. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. Apoc. 14. 5. Prou.</hi> 6. 6.</note> to that, and in their mouth was found no ly. Go to the emot, o ſluggard and learne wiſdome, the which doth pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare her meat in ſommer, and gather in the harueſt that ſhe may eate, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math. 6. v.</hi> 34.</note> to that: <hi>Be not carefull therefore for the morrow.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>12. Tranſgreſſe not the ancient<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro. 22. 28. Ezec.</hi> 20. 18.</note> bounds which thy Fathers haue put; contrary to that, <hi>In the precepts of your Fathers walke not, neyther keep you their iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>13. Anſwere not a foole according<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pro. 26. 4. Ibid. Sap.</hi> 1. 13.</note> to his folly leaſt thou be made like to him; contrary to that, <hi>Anſwere a foole according to his folly, leaſt he eſteeme himſelfe to be wiſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>14. God hath not made death; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 11. 14.</note> to that: <hi>Good things, and euill life, and
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:1409:29"/> death, pouerty, and honeſty, are of God.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Sap.</hi> 11. 25.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>15. Thou loueſt all things that are, &amp; hateſt nothing of thoſe which thou haſt made; contrary to that, <hi>Iacob I loued,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom. 9. 13. Eccl. 10. 15. 1. Tim.</hi> 6.</note> 
                        <hi>but Eſau I hated.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>16. The beginning of all ſinne is prvde: contrary to that, <hi>the roote of all euill is couetouſneſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>17. Do good to the humble &amp; giue<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccl. 12. 6. Luc.</hi> 6. 30.</note> not to the impious: prohibite to giue him bread; contrary to that, <hi>giue to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery one that asketh thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>18. They that eate me ſhall yet<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eccl. 24. 28. Ioan.</hi> 4. 13.</note> hunger, and they that drinke me ſhall yet thirſt; contrary to that, <hi>he who shall drinke of the water which I will giue him, shall not thirſt for euer.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>19. As yet fourty dayes, and <hi>Niniue</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan. 3 4. Ioan.</hi> 4. 11.</note> ſhalbe ſubuerted, contrary to that, <hi>shall not I ſpare Niniue the great Citty?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>20. <hi>Gratis</hi> you haue receiued, <hi>Gratis</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat. 10. 8. Luc.</hi> 10. 7.</note> giue you: contrary to that, the <hi>work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man is worthy of his wages.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>21. Take nothing in the way, ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther skrip, ſhooes, nor rod; contrary to<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math. 10. 10. Marc.</hi> 6. 8.</note> that, <hi>and he hath commaunded them that they should take nothing in the way, but a rod only.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:1409:29"/>
                     <p>22. After 6. daies Ieſus tooke <hi>Peter,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat. 17. 1. Luc.</hi> 9. 28.</note> 
                        <hi>Iames,</hi> and <hi>Iohn;</hi> contrary to that: <hi>It came to paſſe after theſe words, almoſt eight dayes, and he tooke Peter &amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>23. But if thy brother ſhall offend<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 15.</note> againſt thee, go and rebuke him bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>weene thee and him alone; contrary to<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim</hi> 5. 20.</note> that: <hi>Them that ſinne rebuke before all, that the reſt alſo may haue feare.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>24. None is good but one God;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mar. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>0. 19. Luc.</hi> 6. 45.</note> contrary to that: <hi>The goodman of the good treaſure of his hart bringeth forth good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>25. Go preach the Ghoſpell to e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mar. 16. 15. Math.</hi> 10. 5.</note> creature; contrary to that: <hi>Into the way of the Gentiles do not go, and into citties of the Samaritans enter yee not:</hi> But, <hi>go to the sheepe that are perished of the houſe of Iſraell.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>26. You are they that haue remai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc. 22. 28. Math.</hi> 26. 31.</note> with me in my temptations, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that, <hi>you shall all ſuffer ſcandall in me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>27. If I giue teſtimony of my ſelfe<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan.</hi> 5. 31.</note> my teſtimony is not true; contrary to<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan.</hi> 8. 14.</note> this; <hi>Although I giue testimony of my ſelfe, my teſtimony is true.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>28. I do not receaue teſtimony of<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan. 5. 34. Ioan.</hi> 15. 27.</note> man; contrary to this: <hi>And you shall giue teſtimony of me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="44" facs="tcp:1409:30"/>
                     <p>29. He that eateth my fleſh and<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan. 6. 55. Ibidem. v.</hi> 63.</note> drinketh my bloud hath life euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting; contrary to that, <hi>It is the ſpirit that quickneththe, flesh profitteth nothing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>30. All things whatſoeuer I haue<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan. 15. 15. Ioan.</hi> 16. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> heard of my Father, I haue notified vnto you; contrary to this; <hi>I haue yet many things to tell you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>31. <hi>Mary Magdalen</hi> came earely to<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan. 20. 1. Mar.</hi> 16. 2.</note> the monument when it was yet darke; contrary to that: ſhe came to the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nument the ſunne being now riſen.</p>
                     <p>32. Circumciſion indeed profiteth<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 25.</note> if thou obſerue the Law; contrary to that: <hi>Behould I Paul tell you, that if you be cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſed,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Galat.</hi> 5. 2.</note> 
                        <hi>Christ will profit you nothing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>33. <hi>VVe account a man to be iuſtified by</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom. 3. 28. Iames 2. 20. 24. Rom. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. v. 19. Act. 7. v. 51. Rom. 11. v. 34<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> 1. Cor. 2. v. 16. 1. Cor. 13. v.</hi> 3.</note> 
                        <hi>faith without works:</hi> Contrary to that of <hi>S. Iames: Fayth if it haue not workes is dead in it ſelfe.</hi> And againe: <hi>you ſee that man is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by workes, and not by fayth alone.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>34. <hi>For who reſiſteth his will;</hi> contrary to that; <hi>you alwaies haue reſiſted the holy Ghoſt as alſo your Fathers.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>35. <hi>VVho hath knowne the mind of our Lord;</hi> contrary to that; <hi>But we haue the ſenſe of Christ.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>36. <hi>If I shall diſtribute all my goods to be
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:1409:30"/> meate for the poore, and haue not charity, it doth</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc. 11. v.</hi> 41.</note> 
                        <hi>profit me nothing;</hi> contrary to that: <hi>giue al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes and all things are cleane to you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>37. <hi>And as in Adam all dy, ſo alſo in Chriſt</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. 13. v. 32. Ioan. 5. v. 21. Galat. 1. v. 10. 1 Cor. 10. v.</hi> 33.</note> 
                        <hi>all shalbe made aliue;</hi> contrary to that: <hi>The Sonne quickneth whom he will.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>38. <hi>Do I ſeeke to pleaſe men? If I yet did pleaſe men, I should not be the ſeruant of Christ;</hi> contrary to that, <hi>be without offence, euen as I in all things do pleaſe all men.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>39. Beare ye one anothers burden;<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Galat. 6. 2. Ibid. v.</hi> 5.</note> contrary to this: <hi>Euery one shall beare his owne burden.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>40. God inhabiteth light not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſible; contrary to that: <hi>Come to him,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim. 6. 16. Pſal. 33. 6. 1. Iohn. 1. 8. 1. Ioan.</hi> 3. 9.</note> 
                        <hi>and you may be illuminated.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>41. If we ſhall ſay that we haue no ſinne we ſeduce our ſelues; contrary to that: <hi>Euery one that is borne of God, commiteth not ſinne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe and ſuch like <hi>apparent</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions, which are found in many places of the Scripture, oftentimes do trouble the reader, and cauſe exceſſiue paines and labour euen to the moſt lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of all. The auncient Fathers do giue teſtimony of this, who ſpent much tyme in the according of theſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:1409:31"/> and ſuch like contradictions, as <hi>S. Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> for example wrote certaine bookes of the agreement amongſt the Euange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſts: and diuers others alſo who tooke great paines in interpreting the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, whoſe labours if we had not beene partaker of, we ſhould haue yet beene ignorant and blind in many matters of great importance. And thus far about the third cauſe of obſcurity in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                     <p>The fourth ariſeth vpon this, that often tymes the words of Scripture make a doubtfull ſenſe, by reaſon of the want of ſome diſtinction. For ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes where a diſtinction is needfull there is none at all. Which moſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly happeneth in theſe caſes. 1. When it maketh mention of God. 2. When of Chriſt. 3. When it inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth the coming of Chriſt. 4. When it ſpeaketh of the Church. For there be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longeth vnto God, eyther Vnity of eſſence, or Trinity of perſons. To Chriſt eyther the humane nature or diuine. Moreouer Chriſts comming is two<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fould, the one in his nat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>uity, the other in the day of Iudgme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Alſo the Church
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:1409:31"/> is eyther militant vpon earth, or tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphant in heauen<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Therefore when the Scripture maketh mention eyther of God, or of Chriſt, or of the Church, it is doubtfull and obſcure, in what ſenſe there they are to be taken: as if it ſpeake of God, whether it meane there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by as he is one in eſſence, or as he is three in perſon: if of Chriſt, whether it be vnderſtood as he is God, or as he is man: or when mention is made of his coming, whether it be of his firſt or of his laſt: or when the Church is named whether the militant or triumphant thereby is ſignified it is hard to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. But to explaine it the better I will giue an example of euery one.</p>
                     <p>The Scripture maketh mention of<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mar. 6. v.</hi> 9.</note> God, in ſaying: <hi>Our Father which art in heauen.</hi> Now it is doubtfull whether it be ſpoken of God according to the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of his eſſence, or according to the diſtinctio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of his perſons, or, as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uines do propound it, whether the name of Father be taken there eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tially as it is common to three perſons, or perſonally as applied to the firſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon only? There are authors of both
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:1409:32"/> parts: yet it is more likely to be taken in that place eſſentially as it is to be ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered out of theſe words of Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan.</hi> 2. 17.</note> 
                        <hi>I aſcend to my Father and your Father.</hi> Where the word Father is taken both wayes. For the Father of Chriſt according to his eternall generation, is the firſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine perſon, as he is diſtinguiſhed from the ſonne, and the holy Ghoſt. But our Father according to our creation, gouerning and adoption, is the whole Trinity, as he is one God. Therefore when he ſayth: I aſcend to my Father, he ſpeaketh only of the firſt perſon, but when he addeth, and your Father, he ſpeaketh of three perſons as they are one in eſſence and nature.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>S. Paul</hi> maketh mention of Chriſt, <hi>VVho is the Image of the inuiſible God, the first</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Coloſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                           </hi> 1. 15.</note> 
                        <hi>borne of all creatures, becauſe in him were cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated all things, and he is the head of the body the Church, firſt borne of the dead.</hi> Heere alſo it is doubtfull, whether this be to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of Chriſt in reſpect of his di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uinity or humanity. Many thinke that ſome part of the ſenteuce is to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood one way, ſome part another; with whom I agree. For Chriſt according
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:1409:32"/> to his diuinity is the Image of God the Father, and alſo by him and in him all things are made: but according to his humanity he is the head of the Church and firſt borne of the dead. And in both ſenſes he may be called the firſt borne of euery creature, according to the ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dry expoſitions of the interpreters, as may be ſeene in their comments vpon that ſame place.</p>
                     <p>There is alſo a certaine ſpeach of the coming of Chriſt. <hi>And when againe</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> 
                        <hi>he bringeth in the firſt begotten into the world</hi> he ſayth: <hi>And let all the Angells of God adore him.</hi> Wherein conſiſts a queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther this was ſpoken of his firſt coming at his natiuity, or of his laſt coming in the day of iudgment. If were ſpect that word, <hi>againe,</hi> it ſeemeth rather to be of his later comming. But taking all the circumſtances together, it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare to be of his former<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> So the inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preters of this place. Of the Church alſo the Apoſtle writeth: <hi>But that Ilieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem which is aboue, is free, which is our mother.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>6.</note> 
                        <hi>For it is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Reioyce thou barren that beareſt not, breake forth and cry that trauaileſt not, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe many are the children of the deſolate,
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:1409:33"/> more then of her that hath a husband.</hi> Heere therefore is a difficulty to know whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it be meant, of the Church mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant or triumphant? Which difficulty is in another place of <hi>S. Paul. But you are</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Heb.</hi> 12, 22.</note> 
                        <hi>come to mount Sion, and the Citty of the liuing God heauenly Hieruſalem, and the Church of the first borne.</hi> And in the ſame Apoſtle,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 25.</note> 
                        <hi>Chriſt loued the Church and deliuered himſelfe for it, that he might ſanctify it, cleanſing it by the lauer of water in the word of life, that he might preſent to himſelfe a glorious Church, not hauing ſpot or wrinkle.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To this kynd of obſcurity, may alſo be reduced, that ſome things which are ſpoken of Chriſt in Scripture, are to be vnderſtood of the head of the Church, which is Chriſt, ſomtymes of both as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> noteth.</p>
                     <p>For the head of the Church Chriſt is taken in that place of the Apoſtle:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>lib. 3. de doctrina Chri. c. 31. Math.</hi> 28. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>0.</note> 
                        <hi>Behould I am with yow all dayes, euen to the conſummation of the world.</hi> Where Chriſt as the head of the Church, promiſeth to the body and members thereof his perpetuall aſſiſtance, protection, and gouerment.</p>
                     <p>For of the body and members of
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:1409:33"/> the Church is that place of the acts to be vnderſtood. <hi>Saul, Saul why dost thou per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Act.</hi> 9. 4.</note> 
                        <hi>me?</hi> For <hi>Saul</hi> did not perſecute the perſon of Chriſt (ſeing that he was in heauen where he could not be perſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) but his Apoſtles who were the members of his Church. Alſo that of <hi>Zachary; After glory he ſent me to the nations.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Zach.</hi> 
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 8.</note> Where Chriſt ſpeaketh in perſon of the Apoſtles. As though he had ſayd, my heauenly Father will ſend me (to wit my Apoſtles) to the conuerſion of the Gentills. But when will he ſend me? after glory (that is) after I haue ſhewed my glory and diuinity in my Reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection and Aſcenſion. After the ſame manner alſo <hi>S. Auſtine</hi> in the expoſition of the 147. Pſalme, doth interpret that place of <hi>S. Matth. Then if any man shall ſay</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math.</hi> 24. 23.</note> 
                        <hi>vnto you, loe here is Chriſt or there, do not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue him.</hi> For he thinketh that there by Chriſt is ſignified his Church whoſe words are theſe. <hi>There shall riſe falſe Chriſts, and falſe Prophets, and shall ſay, loe here and loe there</hi> but they ſhall not ſpeake of the head himſelfe, behould here &amp; behould there (for it is certaine that Chriſt is in heauen) but of the Church. And out
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:1409:34"/> of this place he confuteth the Donatiſts who ſayd: Behould here in Affrick is the Church, and in no other place be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides.</p>
                     <p>And that of the Prophet <hi>Iſay</hi> of<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſay</hi> 61. 10.</note> both. <hi>He hath clothed me with the garment of ſaluation, and with the garment of iuſtice: he hath compaſſed me as a bridegroome decked with a Crowne, and as a bride adorned with her Iewels.</hi> Where Chriſt is called the bride and the bridegroome, that is, the head and the body: and that of the Pſalme,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.</note> 
                        <hi>The kings of the earth haue ſtood vp and the Princes haue gathered together againſt our Lord and againſt his Chriſt.</hi> Which was fullfilled in the head, and daily is fullfilled in the members.</p>
                     <p>The firſt cauſe of the obſcurity of ſcripture ariſeth from this, that often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes, when we thinke leaſt, paſſage is made from the litterall ſenſe to the myſticall, from carnall things to ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, from temporall to eternall, from the Kings of <hi>Iſraell,</hi> to Chriſt the king himſelfe, and contrariwiſe. This eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially is performed in the Pſalmes and the Prophets, as is to be ſeene in the 7. Chapter of <hi>Iſay,</hi> where from
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:1409:34"/> the Hiſtory of two kings (of the which one was <hi>Raſin</hi> King of <hi>Syria,</hi> and the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Phacee</hi> King of <hi>Iſrael</hi>) paſſage is made preſently to the B. Virgin: Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hould (ſayth he) a virgin ſhall conce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aue, and ſhall bring forth a ſonne, and his name ſhalbe called <hi>Emanuel.</hi> And in the 14. Chapter, where the Prophet paſſeth from the king of Babilon vnto Lucifer: and in the 71. Pſalme paſſage is made from Salomon vnto Chriſt; All the kings of earth ſhall adore him:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Vide D. Hieron. l. 5. in pſal. cap.</hi> 16.</note> and in the ſixt Chapter of <hi>S. Iohn,</hi> the Euangeliſt paſſeth from barly loaues to the Euchariſtical or Sacramental bread. And ſo often tymes in other places.</p>
                     <p>The ſixt obſcurity ariſeth from this, that in the Hiſtories of Scripture things are not ſet downe in that order in which they were done. In like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner that the computation of yeares doth not appeare plaine and manifeſt. Laſtly that certaine bookes often tymes are cited, which if they were extant, they would help the reader very much, but ſeeing they are not to be found, they leaue him doubtfull &amp; in ſuſpence, as are theſe which follow.</p>
                     <list>
                        <pb n="54" facs="tcp:1409:35"/>
                        <item>1. The booke of the warres of our<note place="margin">Numer. 21. v. 14. Ioſue 10. v. 13. 3. Reg. 11. v. 41. 3. Reg. 14. &amp;c.</note> Lord.</item>
                        <item>2. The booke of the Iuſt.</item>
                        <item>3. The booke of the words, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the daies of Salomon.</item>
                        <item>4. The booke of the ſpeaches con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the dayes of the kings of <hi>Iuda,</hi> and the kings of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>5. The booke of <hi>Samuel</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet<note place="margin">1. <hi>Paral. 29. v. 29. Ibidem.</hi>
                           </note> concerning the acts of <hi>Dauid.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>6. The booke of <hi>Nathan</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet concerning the ſame things.</item>
                        <item>7. The volume of <hi>Gad</hi> the Prophet.<note place="margin">Ibid. 2. Paral. 9. v. 19. Ibid. Ibid.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>8. The booke of <hi>Nathan</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet concerning the acts of <hi>Salomon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>9. The booke of <hi>Achias</hi> the <hi>Silonite</hi> of the ſame.</item>
                        <item>10. The viſion of <hi>Addo</hi> the Prophet<note place="margin">2. <hi>Paral. 20. v.</hi> 
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>4.</note> againſt <hi>Ieroboam</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Nabat.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>11. The hiſtory of the kings of <hi>Iſrael</hi> written by <hi>Iehu</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Hanan.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. <hi>Paral. 26. v.</hi> 22.</note>
                        </item>
                        <item>12. The hiſtory of king <hi>Ozias,</hi> written by <hi>Iſay</hi> the ſonne of <hi>Amos.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>13. The ſermons of <hi>Oſe,</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<note place="margin">2. <hi>Paral 33. v. 19. 2. Paral. 35. v. 25 Iere. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                    <desc>•</desc>
                                 </gap>6. v.</hi> 6.</note> the deedes of <hi>Manaſſes.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>14. The lamentation of <hi>Ieremy</hi> in the funerall of king <hi>Ioſias.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>15. The volume of <hi>Ieremy</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:1409:35"/> the ruine of the Citty, and the captiuity of the people.</item>
                        <item>16. The booke of <hi>Ieremy</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Iere. 51. v. 61. 1. Machab. 16. v. 24. 2. Macha.</hi> 2. 1.</note> the deſtruction of <hi>Babilon.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>17. The booke of the tyme of the preiſthood of <hi>Iohn Hircanus.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>18. Deſcriptions of <hi>Ieremy</hi> the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet.</item>
                        <item>19. The booke of <hi>Henoch.</hi>
                           <note place="margin">Epiſt. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Apoſtoli.</note>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                     <p>Beſides theſe cauſes, there are many others the which I will touch in pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſing. For firſt ſomtymes there are many ſentences couched together betweene the which, eyther there is no connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, or at leaſt the connexion doth not appeare. 2. Hebrew words occur the which of few are vnderſtood. 3 Often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes the anſwere which is made ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth not to be ſo fit, &amp; to the purpoſe of the queſtion propounded. 4. Very often words are doubtfull, ſo that it cannot be diſcerned in what ſenſe they are to be taken, as in this place of the firſt to the Corinthians. <hi>For other foundation no</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>. v</hi> 11.</note> 
                        <hi>man can lay, beſides that which is layd which is Christ Ieſus. And if any man build vpon this foundation gould, ſiluer, precious stones wood, hay ſtubble, the worke of euery one shalbe manifeſt:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:1409:36"/> for the day of our Lord will declare, becauſe it shalbe reuealed in fier: and the worke of euery one of what kind it is, the fier shall try. If any mans worke abide which he built thereupon: he shall receaue reward, if any mans worke he shall ſuffer detryment, but himſelfe shalbe ſaued, yet ſo as by fier.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This place without doubt is moſt hard. 1. Becauſe it is hard to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand what is meant, by gould, ſiluer, hay, and ſtubble. 2. What is meant by the day of our Lord. 3. What by fier. 4. What it is to burne, and to ſuffer detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Laſtly what it is to be ſaued ſo as by fier. Whereupon <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Aug. in l. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                                 <desc>••</desc>
                              </gap>i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>e &amp; oper. c.</hi> 15</note> plainly, that this is one of theſe places of which <hi>S. Peter</hi> ſpake in his laſt epiſtle, when he ſayd, <hi>there are ſome things in the epiſtles of S. Paul hard to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Petr. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>oſt. epiſt</hi> 3. 16.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>That other place of <hi>S. Paul</hi> is as hard. <hi>VVhat shall they do that are baptized</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> 
                        <hi>for the dead, if the dead riſe not againe at all? why alſo are they baptized for them?</hi> for it is not eaſy to explicate what to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed ſignifieth in this place; and what to be baptized for the dead. As concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning the which, ſix diuers opinions are
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:1409:36"/> extant in <hi>Bellarmine.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Bel. lib. 1. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Purg. c.</hi> 4.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Likewiſe in the ſame Apoſtle this ſentence is found. <hi>It is impoſſible for them that were once illuminated, haue taſted alſo of the heauenly guift, and were made partakers of the holy Ghost: haue moreouer taſted the good word of God, and the powers of the world to come, and are fallen to be renewed againe to pennance, crucifying againe to themſelues the ſonne of God.</hi> Which wordes are moſt obſcure, and by the ill vnderſtanding of them, the hereſy of the Nouatians aroſe in <hi>S. Cyprians</hi> tyme, who ſayd, that ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther penance, nor pardon was to be giuen to them that fell; and therefore they called themſelues <hi>Catharos,</hi> that is pure and cleane. And this is ſufficient about the cauſes whereby the Scripture according to the true and lawfull ſenſe therof is very hard and obſcure. There remayneth yet another queſtion, which ſhalbe briefly examined.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="58" facs="tcp:1409:37"/>
                     <head>Wherefore is it Gods will, that the Scripture ſhould be obſcure?</head>
                     <p>THIS truly is a great queſtion and worthy to be ſought out, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scripture being by reaſon of the things themſelues, and the miſteries therein conteined very obſcure, is made yet more obſcure by reaſon of the man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of treating thereof, and this accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the will and diſpoſition of God. And wherefore rather by his will and diſpoſition are not thoſe myſteries which ſeeme obſcure by themſelues, ſo clearely propounded, that there may be no difficulty to any in the vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of them? Truely there be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers reaſons of this, of the which I will here ſet downe ſome few.</p>
                     <p>The firſt reaſon is. Becauſe God as he is willing that an order be kept in al other things, euen ſo alſo in his Church to wit, that there ſhould be ſome who might teach, and ſome who might be taught, which order could not be kept, if the Scripture were ſo plaine that it might eaſily be vnderſtood of all, to the
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:1409:37"/> which that place of <hi>S. Paul</hi> doth belong. <hi>He gaue ſome Apoſtles, and ſome Prophets, and</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Eph</hi> 4. 11.</note> 
                        <hi>other ſome Euangeliſts, and other ſom paſtours and Doctours, to the conſumation of the Saints vnto the worke of the ministery, vnto the edifying of the body of Chriſt, that is of the Church.</hi> And alſo that to the Corinthians: <hi>Are all A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles? are all, Prophets? are all doctours? do</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 29.</note> 
                        <hi>all interprete?</hi> as though he had ſayd in no wiſe. For it is the office of ſome to teach and interpret, of others to learne and giue eare, which in the ſame place is declared with a noble example taken from mans body. For euen as in a mans body there be many members, yet not all of them are exerciſed about the ſame office: euen ſo in the Church which is Chriſts body there bee many faythfull, yet all are not partakers of the ſame grace proceeding from God. <hi>For to one</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 8. &amp; 9.</note> 
                        <hi>is giuen the worke of wiſdome, to another the working of miracles, to another the diſcerning of ſpirits, to another the interpretation of lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guages.</hi> And as the ſame Apoſtle ſpeaketh in another place. <hi>To euery one as God hath</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 5.</note> 
                        <hi>diuided the meaſure of his fayth,</hi> where he addeth in the ſame place: <hi>I ſay to all that</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 3.</note> 
                        <hi>are among you not to be more wiſe then behoueth
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:1409:38"/> to be wiſe.</hi> Which is as much to ſay: euen as the eyes haue not the office of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, nor the eares of ſeing, nor the armes of walking, nor the feete of ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, becauſe it is not graunted them ſo by nature: euen ſo in the Church, not all ought to vſe the office of tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching, not all of interpreting the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, not all of working miracles (for that were to be more wiſe then be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth to be wiſe) but euery one doth that which he ought to do euen as it is giuen him from God, in diuiſion of graces.</p>
                     <p>But our aduerſaries do erre excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly againſt this diuine ordination, who permit the liberty of reading and interpreting of Scripture to all; as to all meere lay men, yea to poore and ſilly women. For ſeing that they be not called of God to the office, they do ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare moſt vnfit to thruſt themſelues into it. For now it is come to that paſſe, that there is not one, whether he be Tapſter, Tayler, or Tinker (Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theran or Caluiniſt) who doth not thinke himſelfe skillfull inough in vnderſtanding and interpreting the
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:1409:38"/> Scripture, only by his owne labour, without the helpe and inſtruction of any other. But let them heare what the Apoſtle ſayth, <hi>the eye cannot ſay to the</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 21.</note> 
                        <hi>hand, I neede not thy help:</hi> or againe, <hi>the head to the feete, you are not neceſſary for me.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Let them heare that of the firſt to<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim. 2. 11. 1. Cor. 14. v.</hi> 34.</note> Timothy. <hi>Let the women learne in ſilence withall ſubiection: But to teach I permit not the woman, nor to haue dominion ouer the man, but to be in ſilence.</hi> And to the Corinthians. <hi>Let women hold their peace in the Church, for it is not permitted them to ſpeake, but to be ſubiect. But if they liſt to learne any thing let them aske their owne husbands at home.</hi> But to what end al this? Truly to this, that the order ſet downe of God in his Church ought to be obſerued. <hi>Are all Doctours? do all inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prete? No, For there are diuiſions of graces:</hi> from hence followeth that thoſe ſilly women who pratle much out of the Scriptures, and bluſh not to blab out their owne priuate opinions concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning controuerſies of fayth, do moſt fooliſhly arrogate vnto themſelues that which neither they haue on or belongs vnto them. But in this they imitate their Mother <hi>Eua,</hi> who could not hold
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:1409:39"/> her peace in paradiſe, but her husband being ſilent ſhe bega<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to diſpute with the ſerpent, and preſently was ouercome by him and deceaued, as her husband alſo by her, and many ſuch Eues are found in this age which do the ſame.</p>
                     <p>The ſecond reaſon, yf the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture were eaſy, it would be vnderſtood not only of the faithfull who are in the Church, but alſo of thoſe who are Infidells &amp; no members of the Church: and ſo by little and little the Maieſty &amp; authority of it would be ouerthrowne. To this purpoſe is that which is ſayd in <hi>S. Math. Giue not that which is holy to dogs,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math.</hi> 7. 6.</note> 
                        <hi>neyther caſt yee your pearles before ſwyne leaſt perhaps they tread them which their feete.</hi> As<note place="margin">D. Thomas 1. p. q. 1. art. 9. ad 2. &amp; S. Aug. (aut quiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quis aut hoc ille eſt) hom. 7 in Apocalip.</note> It is vnderſtood by <hi>S. Auguſtine,</hi> and <hi>S. Thomas.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If the Scripture were plaine and eaſy, doubtleſſe it would be leſſe eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med both of the infidells &amp; Chriſtians then is fitting. Moreouer to many it would be an occaſion of pride and aro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gancy. For if they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>hould perceaue that theſe things which treate of profound myſteries were plaine and apparent, they would brag of themſelues exce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſiuely,
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:1409:39"/> &amp; imagin nothing to be ſo hard which they could not by their owne wit and learning conceaue and vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand. But now contrariwiſe they ſee the obſcurity of the Scripture to be ſo great, that by no meanes they are able to ouercome it, and therefore finding themſelues ignorant and wanting the inſtruction of others, they fly ſeriouſly to God, to the end that he may open their eyes and illuminate their vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that his diuine miſteries may be layd open vnto them. As <hi>Dauid</hi> did who ſayd: <hi>Open my eyes and I will conſider</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pſal. 118. verſ.</hi> 18. 34.</note> 
                        <hi>the wonders of thy law.</hi> And a little after. <hi>Giue me vnderſtanding and I will ſearch the law.</hi> And againe in the ſame Pſalme. <hi>Illumimate thy face vpon thy ſeruant and teach me thy iuſtifications.</hi> And very well: for the ſenſe of the Scripture can proceed from none but from the Author of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: But the author of the Scripture is the holy Ghoſt, and therefore it is cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the word of God: the ſenſe therefore of the ſcripture can come from none but from the holy Ghoſt, to which that place of <hi>S. Peter</hi> doth belong, <hi>no prophecy</hi>
                        <note place="margin">2. <hi>Petr.</hi> 1. 20.</note> 
                        <hi>of Scripture is made by priuate interpretation.</hi>
                        <pb n="64" facs="tcp:1409:40"/> The cauſe headdeth: <hi>For not by mans will was prophecy brought at any time, but the holy men of God ſpake, inſpired with the holy Ghoſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And thus it cometh to paſſe, that proud and arogant men who are wiſe in their owne iudgments, and attribut much to their owne wits, do neuer ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine the true ſenſe, becauſe <hi>God reſiſteth the proud, and giueth grace to the humble.</hi> And<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Math.</hi> 11. 25.</note> this is it that Chriſt ſpake of in the Ghoſpell: I confeſſe to the O Father, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thou haſt hid theſe things from the wiſe and the prudent, and haſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uealed them to little ones. And alſo the Apoſtle, ſaying themſelues wiſe, they become fooliſh.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <head>It followes neceſſarily out of the obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Scripture, that many Controuerſies ariſe amongst Chriſtians.</head>
                     <p>THIS is another principle of thoſe which I ſet downe before. And truly it needeth no other confirmation then daily experience. For it is gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rally well known that in all ages euen
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:1409:40"/> from the Apoſtles tyme vnto this our preſent age, that there hath ſprung out alwaies new controuerſies about the true and lawfull ſenſe of Scripture. But now letting paſſe all thoſe which haue beene ſet abroach in the tyme of <hi>Arius, Macedonius, Donatus,</hi> and other auncient heretikes; Infinite they are that occur in this preſent tyme, of which I will ſet downe ſome: as for example, there is a controuerſy.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. In what ſenſe thoſe words of Chriſt are to be vnderſtood: <hi>This is my body.</hi> The Lutherans vnderſtand it ſo, this bread is my body. The Caluiniſts, this bread ſignifieth my body. The Catholikes agree with neither of them.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. How that of <hi>S. Iohn</hi> is to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood:<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Vnleſſe a man be borne againe of the water and the ſpirit, he cannot enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> The Catholikes and the Lutherans do vnderſtand thereby the neceſſity of baptiſme with water; and alſo out of it do gather that infants without baptiſme can in no wiſe be ſaued. The Caluiniſts deny all this.</p>
                     <p>3. What Chriſts meaning was
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:1409:41"/> when he ſpake theſe words to the young man of whom mention is made in <hi>S. Matthew:</hi> If thou will enter into life, keepe the comaundments. Caluin interpreteth it to be ſpoken in ieſt; the Catholikes hould it to haue beene ſayd in earneſt.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. Whether out of theſe words: <hi>Ieſus came the doores being shut, and stood in the</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan.</hi> 20. 26.</note> 
                        <hi>midſt of them,</hi> may be gathered that Chriſt pierced the doores ſhut. The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes affirme it. Others deny it And ſurely, <hi>Oecolampadius</hi> he thinketh, that whileſt the doores were ſhut, Chriſt crept in at the window: others imagin I know not what chinkes by the which they ſay he entred in.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Whether Chriſt ſpake of the Sacrament of the Euchariſt when he ſayd: <hi>Vnleſſe you eate the flesh of the ſonne of</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Ioan.</hi> 6. 53.</note> 
                        <hi>man, and drinke his bloud, you shall not haue life in you.</hi> The Catholikes affirme it: the Lutherans deny it.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Whether Chriſt bindeth all lay men to receaue the Chalice, when he ſaith: Drinke yea all of this. <hi>Caluin</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal. lib. 4. Inſtit. c.</hi> 17. §. 47. §. 48.</note> holdeth he doth. <hi>There is a decree</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>from the eternall God, that all drinke.</hi>
                        <pb n="67" facs="tcp:1409:41"/> And a little after. <hi>They are wordes of him commaunding: Drinke yee all of this Chalice.</hi> But the Catholikes teach, that theſe words only belonged to the Apoſtles, as <hi>S. Marck</hi> declareth, when he ſayth,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Mark.</hi> 14. 24.</note> 
                        <hi>and they all dranke of it.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="7">7. Whether ſinne he taken proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 6. 12.</note> of the Apoſtle: <hi>Let not ſinne therefore raigne in your mortall body.</hi> The Lutherans and the Caluiniſts hould that it is: and from thence they gather that concupi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcenſe (of the which the Apoſtle there ſpeaketh) is originall ſinne: but the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes teach, that the word ſinne is there improperly taken, to wit for the cauſe of ſinne; becauſe concupiſcenſe though it be not properly a ſinne, yet it doth prouoke to ſinne.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. Whether out of that place of <hi>S. Paul: we account a man to be iuſtified by</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Rom.</hi> 3 28.</note> 
                        <hi>fayth without the workes of the law;</hi> may be gathered that only fayth iuſtifieth. The Lutherans affirme it. The Catholikes deny it.</p>
                     <p n="9">9. Whether that place of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: But he ſhalbe ſaued, yet ſo as by fier; be vnderſtood of Purgatory fier? The Catholikes do affirme it with <hi>S.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:1409:42"/> Aug.</hi> vpon the 37. Pſalme, and other more ancient Fathers. The Lutherans and the Caluiniſts deny it.</p>
                     <p n="10">10. Whether it may be gathered out of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> that the Apoſtles had wiues, where he ſayth: <hi>Haue we not</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9. 5.</note> 
                        <hi>power to lead about a woman a ſister, as alſo the reſt of the Apoſtles?</hi> The Lutherans affirme it out of Luthers Gloſſe which is this, <hi>of leading about a woman wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e.</hi> But truly the Catholikes will not admit this gloſſe.</p>
                     <p n="11">11. Of what fayth Chriſt ſpeaketh when he ſayth: belieue only, and ſhe<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc.</hi> 8. 50.</note> ſhalbe ſafe. The Lutherans interpret it to be iuſtifying fayth, whoſe effect is the remiſſion of ſinne. But the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes vnderſtand it of that fayth which <hi>Iarus</hi> Prince of the Sinagogue did beleeue that his daughter then dead could be raiſed againe by Chriſt.</p>
                     <p n="12">12. And what the ſenſe of that place is: <hi>Do good or euill if you can:</hi> Out of<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Iſay.</hi> 41. 23.</note> which Luther proueth that men haue not free will; becauſe they cannot do good and ill as they liſt. The Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes laugh at this their argument, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe thoſe words are not ſpoken to men, but to the Idols of the Gentills,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:1409:42"/> which although they be worſhiped of the Gentills as Gods, yet they be not Gods, becauſe they can neyther profit their worſhippers, nor hurt their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temners.</p>
                     <p n="13">13. Whether out of that which is written of <hi>S. Iohn Baptiſt: The infant in</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Luc.</hi> 1. 44.</note> 
                        <hi>my wombe did leape for ioy,</hi> may be gathered that all infants when they are baptized haue actuall fayth? The Lutherans ſay yea, the Catholikes no.</p>
                     <p n="14">14. Whether God commaunded all to be maried, when he ſayd, <hi>Increaſe</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 28<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>and multiply.</hi> The Lutherans hould that in thoſe words are implied a precept to marry. But the Catholikes take it as<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. 1.</note> a bleſſing, giuen to mariage already contracted, as appeareth in the text it ſelfe.</p>
                     <p n="15">15. Whether this place of <hi>S. Paul:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 5.</note> 
                        <hi>There is one mediatour of God and men, man Christ Ieſus,</hi> doth exclude the inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and interceſſion of Saints, as the aduerſaries affirme. Or do not as we Catholikes maintaine, and proue, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it doth not exclude the inuoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Saints vpon earth: otherwiſe the Apoſtle world not haue ſayd, <hi>Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:1409:43"/> pray for vs.</hi>
                        <note place="margin">1. <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. 25.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p n="16">16. Who are theſe two witneſſes of whom is made mention in the 11. of the Apocalips: <hi>And I will giue to my two wittneſſes, and they shall propheſy a thouſand two hundred ſixty daies, clothed with ſack-clothes.</hi> Some of our aduerſaries ſay, that Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Caluin are meant thereby. Others the old and the new teſtament: but the Catholikes ſay <hi>Henoch,</hi> and <hi>Helias,</hi> or <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and <hi>Helias.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="17">17. What that ſignifieth which is written of Antichriſt in the Apocalips. <hi>And he did great ſignes, ſo that he alſo made fier to come downe from heauen.</hi> Our adue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries do vnderſtand by fier deſcending<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Pow. lib. 1. de. Ant. cap. 26. Bald. in diſpu. de Anti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>h. cap.</hi> 6.</note> from heauen, the Pope his excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munication, as <hi>Powell</hi> the Caluiniſt, and <hi>Balduinus</hi> the Lutheran do hould, and hereby they proue that the Pope is Antichriſt. The Catholikes contemne theſe follies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="section">
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:1409:43"/>
                     <head>The Scripture cannot be the Iudge of theſe, and the like Controuerſies.</head>
                     <p>IT is certaine that in theſe and ſuch like Controuerſies which are about the ſenſe of the Scripture, ſome certaine iudge is needfull, who may decide the ſame, and plainly pronounce that this is true, and not the other. But now I will proue with two arguments that the Scripture it ſelfe cannot be this iudge.</p>
                     <p>The firſt is drawne out of that which I ſayd before in this manner: The Iudge ſo ought to pronounce ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence that both parties at variance may well vnderſtand it, otherwiſe he ſhould pronounce it to no purpoſe; But the Scripture when the ſenſe thereof is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure, and doubtfull (which falleth out often as I haue ſhewed aboue) cannot ſo plainly pronounce ſentence, that it may be vnderſtood of both parties at variance. For if it ſhould clearly pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſentence in any ſuch caſe, the ſenſe of the Scripture ſhould not be obſcure, but plaine and manifeſt, which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:1409:44"/> to our ſuppoſition. Therefore in ſuch a caſe the Scripture cannot be iudge.</p>
                     <p>Perchance you will ſay, that al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though the ſenſe of the Scripture in one place be obſcure, yet notwithſtanding in ſome other place it is very playne, and therefore the Scripture by that place which is cleare, may pronounce ſentence of that place which is ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcure.</p>
                     <p>I anſwere. The heretikes harpe on this ſtring but in vaine. For firſt, if it be ſo, wherefore by that meanes do they not end all controuerſies betwene them? wherefore I ſay, do not the Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therans and the Caluiniſts, ſeing they ſo long contend about ſome obſcure place, run preſently to another which is plaine? or if they do ſo, why make they not an end of all their ſtrife? Here they are at a non-plus, and know not what to ſay.</p>
                     <p>Furthermore that the words of the Scripture are playne, is one thing, but that the ſenſe is plaine is another. For the plaineſſe of the words depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth vpon the knowledg of grammer.
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:1409:44"/> but the ſenſe vpon the intention and counſell of the holy Ghoſt. And doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleſſe oftentymes it may happen that one may be perfect in the knowledg of his grammer, and yet very ignorant of the meaning of the holy Ghoſt. So that it may fall out very well, that the words of the Scripture may be plaine, yet the ſenſe of the words as they be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded of the holy Ghoſt may be obſcure. To ſhew this to the eye I will declare it with this example. The words of Chriſt in the ſcripture be theſe: <hi>This is my body: This is my bloud.</hi> Which words if they be taken according to their proper ſignification, are ſo manifeſt and plaine that they may be well vnderſtood of all men, whether they be Chriſtians, Iewes, Turkes, or Ethnicks. But about the ſenſe of them intended by the holy Ghoſt almoſt infinite controuerſies are amongſt Chriſtians. The like is to be found in thoſe words of <hi>S. Iohn. Mary Magdalen co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth earely to the monument when it was yet darke.</hi> And in thoſe of <hi>S. Mark. She came to the monument the ſunne being riſen.</hi> Then the which wordes nothing could be ſpoken more plainly, yet be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:1409:45"/> the firſt do ſeeme to be contrary to the ſecond, it may be doubted, and that with great reaſon, what the proper ſenſe of them is, and how they may a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree one with another.</p>
                     <p>Moreouer I ſay that oftentymes it happeneth that the one party thinketh that place cleare and manifeſt which the other houldeth to be obſcure and intricate. Now then what is to be done in ſuch a caſe? or what iudge is to be admitted? doubtleſſe the ſcripture can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be the iudge, ſeing the controuerſy is about the ſenſe of it, when ſome thinke it plaine, others obſcure, and of ſome it is conſtrued in this ſenſe, of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers in another. What counſell ſhall we take therefore? muſt not then ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther iudge be ſought out. For example. There is contention betwixt vs and the Caluiniſts, as concerning the true deſcending of Chriſt into hell which they deny, we mantaine, and do for our beleife bring a double teſtimony. The one is out of the Creed: <hi>He deſcended into hell,</hi> the other out of the acts: Thou wilt not leaue my ſoule in hell. We ſay that both of theſe be cleare and euident;
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:1409:45"/> The Caluiniſts deny both, and with their obſcure interpretation they make both places moſt obſcure. For they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpret the firſt in this ſenſe: <hi>He deſcended into hell,</hi> that is (ſay they) he ſuffered vpon the Croſſe moſt cruell and hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible torments of a damned &amp; forlorne man, that preſſed with anguiſh he was forced to cry out, My God, why haſt thou forſaken me? So Caluin. But<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Cal. lib. 2. inſt. c. 16. §. 10. 11. &amp;. catechiſm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> Hidelberg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap> quaeſt.</hi> 44.</note> they take the latter in this ſenſe: <hi>Thou shalt not leaue my Carcaſe in the graue.</hi> What is to be done here? To what iudge ſhal we appeale? If we aske counſell of the Scripture, it will ſay the ſame that it ſayd before. It will not ad ſo much as any one iote to that ſet downe. Now of that which is ſayd before is the contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſy, which can neuer be ended by that which is ſayd before. If then after the Controuerſie begun, the Scripture ſay no new thing at all, but remaine ſtill in the ſame ancient tearmes, truly by it the contention cannot be decided, but of neceſſity we muſt eyther go to ſome other Iudge, or one of the parties contending muſt yield voluntarily, or els they are forced ſtill to continue in
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:1409:46"/> their endleſſe ſtrife and contention.</p>
                     <p>The other argument is this. There are many teſtimonies of the Scripture which can by no meanes be interpre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted according to the true ſenſe, but by the authority and tradition of the Church: Therefore if a Controuerſy ſhould ariſe about theſe teſtimonies, the Scripture only cannot be iudge, but we ought to fly to the tradition &amp; authority of the Church: as for exa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ple Chriſt ſayth, <hi>Teach ye all nations, baptizing them in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne and of the holy Ghoſt.</hi> The true and lawfull ſenſe is, that in baptiſme we are to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounce theſe wordes. <hi>I baptize thee in the name of the Father, and of the Sonne, and of the holy Ghost.</hi> And that baptiſme without ſuch a verball and expreſſe pronuntia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of thoſe words is no true baptiſme. We and our aduerſaries agree in this. But if one ſhould deny this to be the ſenſe, and ſhould ſay, that theſe words were not needfull: In the name of the Father, and the Sonne, and the holy Ghoſt, but that an inward will and intention of baptizing him, in the name of the holy Trinity were ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient;
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:1409:46"/> how ſhould he be confuted? only out of the words of the Scripture? No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe, ſeing the wordes be theſe baptizing them in the name of the Father &amp;c. where there is not any vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call inuocation of the bleſſed Trinity inſinuated, to be of neceſſity? From whence haue we then that it ought to be verily from the practiſe and tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Church? If thou doſt reiect this, thou ſhalt not haue helpe againſt the aduerſary, who ſhall deny the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouncing of theſe words to be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary.</p>
                     <p>Another example is this. Chriſt ſayth, <hi>Vnleſſe a man be borne againe of water and ſpirit he cannot enter into the kingdome of God.</hi> This place according to the true and lawfull ſenſe is vnderſtood of the neceſſity of baptiſme with water, as the Lutheranes themſelues do confeſſe, yet the Caluiniſts notwithſtanding deny it. How therefore can they be confuted of the Lutherans? Truly not out of the Word alleadged. For al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though water be named there, yet it is not ſo expreſly named, as though it ought to be vnderſtood of true and na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:1409:47"/> water. For in another place it is called fier as in <hi>S. Luke:</hi> He ſhall bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tize<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Lue. 3. v.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>.</note> you in ſpirit and fier, and yet it is not vnderſtood of true fire. Therefore how can it appeare that in the former place true water is to be vnderſtood? or how will the Lutherans proue it a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Caluiniſts? Not by any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther meanes, then by the practiſe, order, and tradition of the Church.</p>
                     <p>Another. Chriſt in his laſt ſupper did not only inſtitute the bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament, but alſo he adioyned the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhing of feete, and in the inſtitution of the bleſſed Sacrament he ſayd, <hi>Eate and drinke:</hi> but in the waſhing of eete, <hi>and you ought one to wash the feete of another.</hi> Here the Aduerſaries ſay, that in the firſt words there is a precept, but not in the laſt. And ſo the faythfull by Gods com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment are obliged to receaue the bleſſed Sacrament in both kindes, but not ſo to the waſhing of feete. Now I aske, how they are certaine of this? or by what pretence do they thinke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues bound to the receauing of both kyndes, and yet free from the waſhing of feet? Certainly they cannot pretend
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:1409:47"/> the words of Scripture: For they ſeeme rather to ſhew the contrary. For theſe words, <hi>Eate and drinke,</hi> ſeeme to ſignify no more of themſelues, then if a houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper ſhould ſay to his gueſts, eate and drinke, and be merry. And if the houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper ſhould ſay ſo, it would not be thought that be meant thereby to bynd them by a precept. Therefore ſeing Chriſt ſpake in the ſame manner, how is it certaine that he intended by that manner of ſpeaking to oblige all the faythfull to the receauing of both kinds? But theſe wordes; You ought to waſh the feete of one another, ſeeme to ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy a precept no leſſe, then if the mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhould ſay to the ſeruant: Thou muſt couer the table. How therefore know they that by theſe words they are not obliged to waſh the feete of one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, ſeing the words themſelues do ſhew plainly an obligation? Only by the practiſe, and Tradition of the Church. For the Church neuer hath vſed this waſhing as neceſſary, which notwithſtanding ſhe would haue done if ſhee had thought that ſhe had beene obliged to it, and that by Chriſts com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundment.</p>
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:1409:48"/>
                     <p>I omit many like examples which are eaſy to be found. And out of theſe I conclude thus: The Scripture may be conſidered two waies. 1. According to the bare and outward letter. 2. Accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the inward ſenſe which is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended of the holy Ghoſt. But neyther of theſe two waies can it be iudge of Controuerſies. Not the former way as we haue proued in the firſt part of this ſecond argument. Neither as it is taken in the ſecond way, becauſe the ſenſe of the Scripture often tymes is ſo obſcure and doubtfull, that there is need of ſome other iudge who may define this to be the true meaning, which is intended of the holy Ghoſt, and not any other con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. And this is ſufficient about the ſecond Argument drawne from the Scripture.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="argument">
                  <pb n="81" facs="tcp:1409:48"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE III. ARGVMENT.</hi> Which is drawne out of the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies them ſelues.</head>
                  <p>THIS argument, thus I propound. There are many Controuerſyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fayth and Religion, of the which in the Scripture there is no mention made at all, or at leaſt not ſo much as is ſufficient, ſo that the Scripture may giue ſentence of them: therefore in de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciding of them, ſome other iudge is to be ſought. Such Controuerſyes be theſe.</p>
                  <p>The firſt, whether the Bookes of <hi>Toby, Iudith, VViſedome, Eccleſiaſticus,</hi> &amp; the <hi>Machabees</hi> be Canonicall land diuine? The Lutherans, and the Caluiniſts ſay no. But the Catholikes ſay the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary. Now who muſt be iudge to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide this contention? The Scripture cannot be. Neither the Lutherans nor the Caluiniſts (which is well to be no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) do appeale to the Scripture, but to the Canon and tradition of the Iewes. They ſay therefore that thoſe Bookes
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:1409:49"/> cannot be found in the Canon of the Iewes, which is extant in S. <hi>Hierome,</hi> and therefore they are not to be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Canonicall and Diuine. Hence they confeſſe, that in this caſe there ought to be ſome other iudge beſides the Scripture. And who is that? The tradition of the Iewes ſay they. But is not this ſtrang, to ſee our Aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries make more reckoning of Iewes, then of Chriſtians? For although they be deſirous to be accounted Chriſtians they are deadly enemyes to the traditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of Chriſt, and his Apoſtles, and yet notwithſtanding make great accompt of the Iewes traditions. Wherefore ſay they not rather with S. <hi>Auguſtine: Not</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Auguſt. l. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>8. de ciuit. Dei c.</hi> 36.</note> 
                     <hi>the Iewes, but the Church holdeth the Bookes of the Machabees for Canonicall?</hi> or with Iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorus: <hi>The Iewes do not receaue the bookes of Toby, Iudith, and the Machabees, but the Church doth number them among the Canonicall Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ifidor. in l. Pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m. de lib. vet. &amp; no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Teſt.</note> And in the ſame place: <hi>The Booke of VViſedome, and Eccleſiaſticus are knowne to haue the like authority that other Canonicall Bookes haue?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond is, how many Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craments there be of the new Law?
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:1409:49"/> Our aduerſaries ſay but two, Baptiſme, and the Lords ſupper: The Catholiks beleeue ſeauen. But what ſayth the Scripture? Nothing as concerning a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny certaine number, and therefore it cannot be the Iudge in this Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſy. From whence therefore receaue the Catholikes the number of ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, if not out of Scripture? From the tradition and conſent of the Church. From whence the aduerſaryes the nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of 2.? Let them looke from whence. Truly they haue it not from the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture: but if they thinke they haue, let them performe theſe three things. Firſt let them ſhew out of Scripture, that the name of a Sacrament is attributed to Baptiſme, and to the Euchariſt, and not as well to <hi>Confirmation, Order, Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, Matrimony,</hi> and <hi>Extreme Vnction.</hi> Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly out of Scripture let them define a Sacrament. Thirdly let them ſhew, that the definition agreeth fitly with Baptiſme, and the Euchariſt, and not as well to the reſt. If they can do this they do ſomething: but that they nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wil, nor euer can do this I am moſt certaine.</p>
                  <pb n="84" facs="tcp:1409:50"/>
                  <p>For firſt where will they find in Scripture, that the name of a Sacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t is attributed to Baptiſme, and the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt. Truly in no place. But I will find where it is applyed to Matrimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny. For ſo writeth the Apoſtle. <hi>For this cauſe shall man leaue his Father and Mother, &amp;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 5. 31.</note> 
                     <hi>shall cleaue to his wife and they shallbe two in one flesh. This is a great Sacrament: But</hi> I <hi>ſpeak in Chriſt, &amp; in the Church.</hi> As though he had ſayd, That a man ſhall leaue his parents and cleaue to his wife. This is a great Sacrament, becauſe it is a ſigne of the vnio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of Chriſt with his Church that is, the mariage of Chriſt, and his Church.</p>
                  <p>Secondly where will they find<note place="margin">Luth. in l. de captiu Bab <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. vlt Melan. in ep. Conf. Auguſt. art. 13. Mel. in lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cis<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ommu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>us tit. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> numero Sacramen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>torum.</note> in the Scripture the definition of a Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament? <hi>Luther</hi> indeed doth thus define it: <hi>A Sacrament is a promiſe annexed to an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall ſigne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Melancthon</hi> thus: A Sacrament is a rite which hath the commandment of God, to which is adioyned a promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe of grace, that is to ſay, of free recon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciliation, or remiſſion of ſinnes, as he explicateth himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Caluin</hi> in this manner: A Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:1409:50"/> is an outward ſigne by the which<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Calu. l. 4. Inſtit cap.</hi> 14. §. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> our Lord doth ſeale to our conſciences the promiſe of his good will to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prop the weaknes of our fayth. But verily none of all theſe definitions are in the Scripture. Nay one of them doth not agree with another. For <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther</hi> in his definition ſayth, that the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is of the eſſence of a Sacrament. <hi>Melancthon</hi> houldeth, that it is annexed to the Sacrament. But <hi>Caluin</hi> inſinua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth in his, that the promiſe is not anne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xed to the Sacrament, but rather that the Sacrament is annexed and added to the promiſe; and not that the promiſe is of the effect of Gods good will to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards vs. Therefore according to <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancthon</hi> thus the promiſe were to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed if any ſhall receaue the ſacrame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of Baptiſme, or of the Euchariſt; Him I promiſe the remiſſion of his ſinnes. But according to <hi>Caluin</hi> in this ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ner; God hath promiſed to you remiſſion of ſins and life euerlaſting, and this promiſe he declares and ſeales by the Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, whatſoeuer is to be thought of theſe definitions, which
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:1409:51"/> our Aduerſaryes haue newly inuented, how will they ſhew out of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that they agree to Baptiſme, and the Euchariſt? I for my part ſee not. But let vs try. One definition is this<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A Sacrament is a rite which hath a Commandment of God, to which is annexed a promiſe of remiſſion of ſins. Let our aduerſaryes proue out of ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, that this definition is agreeable to the Euchariſt. Let them proue I ſay this out of Scripture, that the Eucha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſt hath a promiſe of remiſſion of ſinns annexed vnto it. Or, that which is all one, That God in the Scripture doth promiſe vs remiſſion of our ſinns if we receaue this Sacrament. They can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer proue it. For this Sacrament is not ordayned of God to remit a man his ſinnes, or to make of a wicked man, or a ſinner a iuſt &amp; holy man, but rather it is inſtituted to the end, that it may nouriſh, confirme, and increaſe that iuſtice, grace and ſanctity, which was in him before he receaued this Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Nay rather it is ſo farre off from remitting of ſinnes, as it is pernicious to a ſinner if he come to it, knowing
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:1409:51"/> himſelfe guilty of deadly ſinne. Hence it is of the Apoſtle to the Corinthians. <hi>But let a man proue himſelfe, and ſo let him eat of that bread, and drinke of that chalice, for he that eateth and drinketh vnworthily, eateth &amp; drinketh iudgment to himſelfe.</hi> And Chriſt in his laſt ſupper would not giue the Euchariſt to his Apoſtles before he had waſhed their feet, to the end that he might giue vs to vnderſtand that none vnles they be waſhed pure, and free from all mortall ſinne are to be admit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the holy table of our Lord. And the reaſon is plaine out of the nature of this Sacrament. For what is the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chariſt, but a kind of ſpirituall meate, and drinke by the which our ſoule is refreſhed and made ſtrong? <hi>For my flesh,</hi> ſayth Chriſt, <hi>is truly meate, and my bloud is truly drinke.</hi> And therefore as corporall meate and drinke doth not profit the body, vnles it be aliue: euen ſo neither the Euchariſt doth helpe the ſoule, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>les it be voyd of ſin, which is the death of the ſoule.</p>
                  <p>The third Controuerſy is, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther exorciſmes, and other ceremonyes vſed in the Catholike Church may be
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:1409:52"/> admitted in Baptiſme? That Lutherans admit them, the Caluiniſts reiect the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Yet neither of them both can confirme their opinion out Scripture. Not the Lutherans, becauſe the Scripture in no place maketh mention, that ſuch cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monyes ought to be vſed: but only we receaue them from the tradition of the Church. Of the which thus S. <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine</hi> writeth. <hi>By the moſt ancient tradition of the Church</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>children are exerciſed</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug l. 2. de nupt. &amp; concup. cap.</hi> 29.</note> 
                     <hi>and breathed vpon, that they may be tranſlated to the kingdome of Chriſt, from the power of darknes.</hi> Not the Caluiniſts, without it be in this manner. No ceremonyes are to be vſed in the Church, but thoſe of the which there is expreſſe command in the Scripture: But there is no com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the ceremonyes, which the Catholikes vſe in Baptiſme: Therfore ſuch Ceremonyes are not to be vſed. But the M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ior is both falſe and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to the Caluiniſts themſelues. For the Caluiniſts do vſe many ceremonies in Baptiſme, of the which there is no command in the whole Suripture, ſuch are theſe. 1. That the infant muſt be baptized before al the people, and that
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:1409:52"/> it ſhould be on a Sunday, or ſome other day when the people is wont to come togeather. 2. That they who bring the infant to be baptized ſhould be aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked whether they will promiſe to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct the child in fayth and manners, after he ſhall grow to perfect age. 3. That a name ſhould be impoſed vpon the infant, who is baptized 4. That the forme of Baptiſme ſhould be pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounced in their country language. 5. That the Creed, our Lords prayer &amp; others alſo ſhould be recyted. Which ceremonyes <hi>Caluin</hi> preſcribeth in a litle booke treating of the forme of mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtring the Sacraments. But where I pray you, is commanded in Scripture Baptiſme ought to be miniſtred? Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly in no place. Hence therfore fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loweth, that either they muſt reiect all thoſe their ceremonyes, or els graunt, that all thoſe which we vſe are not therefore to be condemned, becauſe they are not expreſly commanded in Scripture.</p>
                  <p>The fourth Controuerſy. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther thoſe who are baptized of here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tikes, are to be baptized againe? <hi>S. Cr<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian</hi>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:1409:53"/> in tymes paſt who was Biſhop of Carthage did affirme it with ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. But <hi>S. Augustine</hi> did deny it, and followed that doctrine which was more true, the which he did defend by no other meanes then by the Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call tradition, &amp; practiſe of the Church. For ſo he writes againſt the Donatiſts. <hi>VVhich cuſtome</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>to wit that bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſme may not be iterated, I beleeue to haue pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug. l. 2. cont. Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nat. c.</hi> 7.</note> 
                     <hi>out of the Apoſtolicall tradition.</hi> And againe. <hi>That cuſtome which was oppoſed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Cyprian,</hi> is to be beleeued to haue receiued it beginning from the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtolicall tradition, to the which <hi>Cyprian</hi> did not yeald, becauſe it ſeemed to him vtterly deſtitute of any authority from the Scripture.</p>
                  <p>There are many other ſuch like controuerſies which cannot be decided out of Scripture alone, but they muſt of neceſſity haue ſome other Iudge which heer I will briefly poynt to. 1. Whether Baptiſme may be giuen by one dipping. 2. Whether Chriſtians may worſhip Sunday in place of the Sabboath. 3. Whether our Lady re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained a Virgin after her Childbirth.
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:1409:53"/> 4. Whether <hi>S. Peter</hi> the Apoſtle was Biſhop of the Romaine Church. 5. Whether the Creed be Canonicall and Apoſtolicall. 6. Whether in the old Teſtament there was ſome outward remedy for women againſt originall ſinne.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="argument">
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE IIII. ARGVMENT.</hi> Which is taken out of the vſe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the old Testament, where not the Scripture, but the Biſhop was acknowleged for the Iudge.</head>
                  <p>IT is certaine, that in the old Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment all legall controuerſies which were of great moment were to be en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and decided by the High Prieſt, as by the ſupreme Iudge vpon earth, and not by the Scripture only. Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this is <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in theſe wordes. <hi>The high Prieſt doth offer vp ſacrifice to God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all other Prieſts, he keepeth the lawes, he is iudge of controuerſyes, he punisheth offenders, whoſeuer is diſobedient to him is punished as im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious againſt God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:1409:54"/>
                  <p>And this is plainly deduced out of that place of <hi>Deuteronomy. If thou perceaue</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 8.</note> 
                     <hi>that the iudgment with thee be hard and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full betweene bloud and bloud, cauſe and cauſe, leproſy and not leproſy, and thou ſee that the words of the Iudges within thy gates do vary: ariſe and go vp to the place which thy Lord thy God shall chooſe, and thou shalt come to the Prieſts of the Leuiticall ſtocke, and to the Iudge that shallbe at that tyme, and thou shalt aske of them, who shall shew thee the truth of the iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, neither shalt thou decline to the right hand, nor to the left hand: but he that shallbe proud refuſing to obey the Commandment of the Priest which at that tyme miniſtereth to our Lord thy God, and the decree of the Iudge, that man shall dye.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>About this paſſage we muſt note, firſt that amongſt the Iewes there were diuers Controuerſyes: in this two eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially are recorded. The one concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oud. The other concerning le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſy: but in other places we find foure as in the ſecond of Paral p. in theſe words. <hi>VVhereſoeuer there is queſtion of the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Paral. 19. v.</hi> 10.</note> 
                     <hi>Law, of the Commandment, of Ceremonyes, of iuſtification.</hi> Where <hi>Lyranus</hi> tells vs, that ſome did ariſe out of the Law of the
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:1409:54"/> Decalogue, ſome out of the morall Commandments, which are not in the Law of the Decalogue: ſome out of the Ceremonial Precepts belonging to the worſhip of God. Some laſtly out of thoſe which were iudiciall, and very conuenient for the preſeruing of out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward peace and iuſtice.</p>
                  <p>Againe we muſt note, that in e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery Citty there were placed inferiour iudges, who according to their office were bound to decide ſuch Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyes, as is ſet downe in the 16. of <hi>Deu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teronomy.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 16. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>Iudges and Maiſters shalt thou ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>point in all thy gates which our Lord thy God shal giue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thee in euery of thy Tribs, that they may iudge the people with iust iudgement, and not decline to either part.</hi> And againe, <hi>he appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted iudges of the Land in all the fenced Cittyes</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Paral.</hi> 19. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>of Iuda in euery place.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Moreouer we muſt obſerue, that when inferiour Iudges could not agree amongſt themſelues, nor decide thoſe conferences, which were preſented to them for ſome peculiar difficulty, then they were forced to repaire to <hi>Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     </hi> to thoſe who were ſuperiour iudges, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer whome the high Prieſt was Preſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:1409:55"/> or ſupreme iudge, to whoſe ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence all were bound to obey vnder paine of death. This is plaine out of the words, which are ſet downe before <hi>Duet.</hi> 17. 8.</p>
                  <p>From hence we gather that there was a double Tabernacle ſeat or Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell amongſt the Iewes; the one was greater, the other leſſe. Between them there was great difference. Firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the greater was only at <hi>Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> the leſſer in euery Citty 2. In the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter were decided matters of greater mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, in the leſſer thoſe which were eaſy. 3. In greater the high Prieſt was Preſident, not ſo in the leſſer. 4. It was lawfull to appeale from the leſſe to the greater, not ſo from the greater to the leſſer. 5. In the greater there was 70. perſons beſides the high Prieſt, in the leſſer 23. 6. The greater was cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mark. 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>5. Luc. 9. 22. Act.</hi> 4. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>Sanedrin,</hi> or <hi>Synedrion</hi> or the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of the Elders, the leſſer not ſo. Of the greater is often made mention in the Ghoſpell.</p>
                  <p>Both theſe Councells had their beginning vnder <hi>Moyſes.</hi> The leſſer was ordayned according to the Counſell of
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:1409:55"/> 
                     <hi>Iethro,</hi> but the greater according to the Commandment of God. The occaſion of ordeyning the leſſer is deſcribed in <hi>Exodus,</hi> in theſe wordes: <hi>And the next day</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Exod.</hi> 18. 13.</note> Moyſes <hi>ſate to iudge the people, who stood by Moyſes from morning vntill night, which thing when his Allyed had ſeene, to wit all things that he did in the people, he ſayth; VVhat is this thou doſt in the people? VVhy ſitteſt thou alone, and all the people attendeth from morning vntill night? To whome Moyſes anſwered: The people cometh to me ſeeking the ſentence of God, and when any Controuerſy chanceth among them, they come vnto me to iudge betweene them, and to shew the Precepts of God, and his lawes. But he ſayd, Thou doſt not well, thou art tyred with foolish labour, both thou, and this people that is with thee, the buſines is aboue thy strengh, thou alone canſt not ſuſteine it. But heare my words and counſells, &amp; God shallbe with thee. Be thou to the people in theſe thinges that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine to God, to report their wordes vnto him, and to shew to the people the ceremonyes, and rite of worshipping, and the way wherein they ought to walke, and the worke that they ought to do, and prouide out of all the people men that are wiſe, and do feare God, in whome there is truth, and that do hate auarice, and appoint of
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:1409:56"/> the Tribunes and Centurions, and Quinquage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narians, &amp; Decanes which may iudge the people at all tymes, and what great matter ſoeuer shall fall out. let them referre it to thee, and let them iudge the leſſe matters only.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Of the Inſtitution of the greater Councell, thus we read. <hi>And our Lord</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 11. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>ſayd to Moyſes; Gather me ſeauenty men of the ancients of Iſraell, whom thou knoweſt to be the ancients of the people<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and Maiſters, and thou shalt bring them to the dore of the Tabernacle of Couenant, and thalt make them to ſtand there with thee, that I may deſcend, and ſpeake to thee: and I will take off thy ſpirit and will deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer it to them that they may ſuſtaine with thee the burden of the people, and thou only be not</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. v.</hi> 24</note> 
                     <hi>burdened.</hi> And in another place. <hi>Moy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes therfore came and tould the people the words of our Lord aſſembling ſeauenty men of the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients of Iſrael, whom he cauſed to stand about the Tabernacle: and our Lord deſcended in a cloud<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and ſpake to him, taking away off the ſpirit that was in Moyſes &amp; giuing it to the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uenty men. And when the ſpirit had rested on them, they propheſied, neither ceaſed they any more.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But when the Councell was almoſt ouerthrowne, it was reſtored againe
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:1409:56"/> by <hi>Ioſaphat</hi> King of <hi>Iuda,</hi> as is related in theſe wordes. <hi>Ioſaphat therefore dwelt in Hieruſalem, and went forth to the people againe from Berſabee vnto mount Ephraim, and recou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciled them to our Lord the God of their Fathers. And he appointed Iudges of the Land in all the fenced Cittyes of Iuda in euery place: &amp; com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manding the Iudges he ſayd: Take heed what you do, for you exerciſe not the iudgment of man but of our Lord, and whatſoeuer you shall iudge, it shall redound to you.</hi> All theſe words are vnderſtood of the leſſer Councell. But now of the greater. <hi>In Hieruſalem alſo Io<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaphat appointed Leuits, &amp; Priests, and Princes</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. v.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>of familyes of Iſraell, that they should iudge the iudgment and cauſe of our Lord to the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereof. And he commanded them ſaying: Thus shall you do in the feare of our Lord faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, and with a perfect hart. Euery cauſe that shall come to you of your brethren, that dwell in their Cittyes, betweene kindred and kindred, whereſoeuer there is queſtion of the Law, of the Commandment, of Ceremonyes, of Iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, shew it them that they ſinne not againſt our Lord, and leaſt there come wrath vpon you, and your Brethren, ſo long therefore you shall not ſinne. And Amarias the Prieſt, and your Bishop shallbe chiefe in theſe thinges, which pertaine to
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:1409:57"/> God. Moreouer Zabidias the ſonne of Iſinahell who is the Prince in the houſe of Iuda, shalbe o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer thoſe workes which pertaine to the Kings office.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now therfore that I may repeat in a word, that which is ſayd. The matter was thus done by <hi>Moyſes</hi> in the deſert. Firſt <hi>Moyſes</hi> alone (who was an extraordinary high Prieſt) did iudge all Controuerſyes amongſt the people. Then a while after, that he might be releaſed a little from his burden, there were added to him Tribunes, &amp; Cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turions about the number of fifty, and alſo Decanes, who iudged of the leſſer cauſes, and paſſed ouer the greater only vnto him: laſtly to his greater comfort 70. Seniors were elected, who might alſo aſſiſt him in greater cauſes. After the death of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> when the children of Iſraell were come into the Land of Promiſe, there was a double Tribunall and iudgment conſtituted. The one at <hi>Hieruſale<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,</hi> to iudge of more hard cauſes, and the other in euery Citty was pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, for thoſe which were more eaſy. This laſt was giuen from the Councel of Decanes, and Tribunes, but the
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:1409:57"/> firſt from the Councell of the ſeauenty Seniors.</p>
                  <p>Hither may be adioyned, that it was done other wiſe in the deſert vnder <hi>Moyſes,</hi> then it was vnder the other high Prieſts in the Land of promiſe; for ther was a double difference, the one by reaſon of the high Prieſt, the other by reaſon of the Councell of the Seniors. For the high Prieſt after his entrance into the Land of promiſe did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cyde Controuerſyes, but only out of the written Law. But <hi>Moyſes</hi> did decyde many out of the liuely voice, and ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of God before the law was yet wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten. Among other were theſe three.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> Firſt what was to be done with them who for their Legall vncleanes, could<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 15. 32.</note> not celebrate the Paſch with the reſt? Secondly what puniſhment was to be layd vpon him, who was found gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Num.</hi> 27. 1.</note> wood vpon the Sabaoth? Thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dly whether the daughters of <hi>Salphaad</hi> could haue inheritance amongſt the kindred of their Father? Of all which there was nothing at all writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Law. Therefore <hi>Moyſes</hi> asked Counſell of God by a liuely voice, and
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:1409:58"/> receauing an anſwere did follow the will of God. And then firſt all theſe were tranſlated into the Law.</p>
                  <p>Of the part of the Councell of the Seninors, there was this difference. The ſeauenty Seniors, who were ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> receaued the ſpirit of propheſy euen at their election. But whether the reſt who ſucceeded them, by courſe of tyme did receaue the ſame it is vncertaine. But this is very credi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, that whenſoeuer they conſulted of hard matters, they were helped by the ſingular aſſiſtance of God. And that this aſſiſtance was graunted eſpecially to the Biſhop, who was chiefe of them, when he did performe the office of a Iudge in giuing of ſentence. As con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the which I wil ſay ſomthing heereafer.</p>
                  <div type="objection">
                     <head>AN OBIECTION.</head>
                     <p>IT may be you will ſay, that all this is to be vnderſtood of Legall Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſyes, in the which the High Prieſt was the ſupreme Iudge, as it is ſufficiently proued: but not of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſyes
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:1409:58"/> in matters of fayth, in the which the Scripture alone was to be the iudge. I anſwere. This truly is ſayd without any ground at all. For all Controuerſyes, whether they were of fayth, or of other matters were called Legall, for two cauſes. Firſt they did riſe out of the Law it ſelfe not well vn<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derſtood. Secondly, becauſe they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e to be decyded by the true interpre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="4 letters">
                           <desc>••••</desc>
                        </gap> of the Law. Moreouer all of them, without any exception did belong to the Biſhop, euen as to the ſupreme<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 17. 10.</note> Iudge, euen thoſe which were of faith and Religion. This is manifeſt out of theſe words cyted a little before: <hi>Ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rias your Bishop shall be chiefe in theſe thinges, which appertaine to God.</hi> But Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſyes of fayth and religion do belong eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially to God, therefore the Biſhop was chiefe in thoſe Controuerſyes. But what is it to be chiefe in Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſyes, but to play the part of a Iudge? Alſo out of the precedent wordes, <hi>VVhereſoeuer queſtion is made of the Law, of the Commandment of ceremonies, of iuſtificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> all theſe queſtio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s were brought to the Biſhop, and beſide theſe there were
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:1409:59"/> no other, therefore there were none ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>empted from the iuriſdiction of the Biſhop.</p>
                     <p>And it is confirmed by an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample. For among the Controuerſyes of Fayth, of which we now eſpecially treate, a principal one was concerning the <hi>Meſſias.</hi> But euen this Controuerſy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>as referred to the Councel of Prieſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>ether that the Meſſias was borne yet or no, in which the High Prieſt was the chiefe. Which to be ſo appeareth by the Ghoſpell: <hi>And Herod the King hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring this, was troubled, &amp; Hieruſalem with</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Matt.</hi> 2. 3.</note> 
                        <hi>him. And gathering togeather al the High Prieſts and Scribes of the people, he enquired of them, where Chriſt should be borne. But they ſayd to him. In Bethleem of Iuda; for ſo it is written by the Prophet: And thou Bethleem the Land of Iuda art not the leaſt among the Princes of Iuda, for out of thee shall come forth the Captaine that shall rule my people Iſraell.</hi> In which place, three things are to be noted. Firſt that King <hi>Herod</hi> was doubtfull of the place where the Meſſias was to be borne. Secondly that he referred the reſoluti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of this doubt to the Councell of Prieſts. Thirdly that the Prieſts accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:1409:59"/> to their office reſolued this doubt out of the Scripture, as the rule to the which they conformed themſelues.</p>
                     <p>Moreouer that the Scripture, neither was, nor could be by it ſelfe a iudge of theſe Controuerſyes may eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be proued. For the Scripture which then was extant, eſpecially in ſome of the firſt ages, was no other but the law of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> or a volume of the Couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; <hi>Deuteronomy.</hi> But of this volume, there are three things certaine. The Autogra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phum or firſt copy thereof, was writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by <hi>Moyſes,</hi> and placed of the Prieſts<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 31. 14.</note> in the Arke of the couena<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of our Lord and there kept, that it ſhould be an au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall inſtrument, of the which it might be manifeſt what the will and<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut. 17. 8. &amp; Ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaei. 2. 12. &amp; Malach.</hi> 2. 7.</note> diſpoſition of God was. Secondly that the interpretation thereof in doubtful caſes was committed vnto Prieſts, and eſpecially to the high Prieſt. Thirdly that this authenticall coppy was to be read of the Prieſts vnto all the people, in the Solemnity of the Tabernacles, but once in ſeauen yeares when it was the yeare of remiſſion.<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Deut.</hi> 31. 10.</note>
                     </p>
                     <p>Heerehence it followeth firſt,
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:1409:60"/> that the people had not the firſt &amp; au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thenticall coppy of the law of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> but only the Prieſts. If therefore out of the ſolemnity of the Tabernacles, in any tyme of the ſeauen yeare any legall Controuerſy had riſen, the people could not aske Councell of the authen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticall coppy, which then they had not, but were to go to the Prieſt, and aske the finall ſentence of him as of the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary Iudge. Secondly it followeth, that although the people had the cop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py, yet out of it they could not decyde any Controuerſy. For it was not the office of the people, but of the Prieſt, and eſpecially of the High Prieſt, to interprete the law of Moyſes, from the which thoſe Controuerſyes had their beginning.</p>
                     <p>But perchance you may aske, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the interpretation of the law and conſequently the deciding of legall controuerſies belonged rather vnto the high Prieſt then to others? Seing that well it might be that the other Prieſts were as skillfull, yea and more skillfull in the law then the high Prieſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe? I anſwere. If we reſpect humane
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:1409:60"/> induſtry it is certaine that others might haue beene as killfull in vnderſtanding and interpreting of the law, as the high Prieſt. But if we reſpect the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the holy Ghoſt, which is eſpecially to be regarded in this buſines, the ſame was communicated rather to the high Prieſt then to others, as we haue an example in <hi>Moyſes.</hi> For God grounted greater aſſiſtance to <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>oyſes</hi> then to 70. Seniors who all were mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters to him in his office. This is ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Num.</hi> 11. 7.</note> out of that our Lord ſayth to <hi>Moyſes:</hi> I will take from thy ſpirit and deliuer vnto them, that they may ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>port with thee the burden of the people. Where by the ſpirit we are to vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d a certaine guift of grace which is ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary in them, who will rightly go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerne others and end their controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. This therefore is the ſenſe. I will take from thy ſpirit, and deliuer vnto them, that is, I will giue to them a guift of grace, but yet inferiour to that guift which thou haſt. To thee who art the chiefe iudge it is behoueable that more be giuen, then to them who are ſubiect to thee.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="argument">
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:1409:61"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE V. ARGVMENT.</hi> Drawne from the custome, vſe, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the new Teſtament.</head>
                  <p>EVEN as in the old Teſtament (as I haue already ſhewed) the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture was not the iudge of Controuerſies but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>e high Prieſt and Councell of the Seniours: ſo alſo in the new it hath hitherto beene; yet I will briefly ſhew it, that it may appeare plainly. And firſt in the tyme of the Apoſtles there was a controuerſy aroſe about Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion, to wit, whether that the new Chriſtians, who did receaue the fayth of the Ghoſpell could not be ſaued, vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they were circumciſed and kept their legall ceremonies? which con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſy was eſpecially vnderſtood of the Gentills conuerted vnto fayth. But there was a double opinion about this. The one of ſome who of Iewes were made Chriſtians, who held that the Gentiles could not be ſaued by the fayth of Chriſt, vnleſſe they were circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed, and obſerued the ceremonies of
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:1409:61"/> the law. The other was of <hi>S. Paul,</hi> and <hi>Barnabas,</hi> who affirmed that there was no need of circumciſion, and the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruation of legall ceremonies.</p>
                  <p>But now how was this contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſy decided and ended? was it brought to the Scripture alone, euen as to the common iudge? Nothing leſſe. But rather by the common conſent of both parties, ſome were elected who might go to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> vnto the Apoſtles, that they in ſolemne Councell being informed in the whole matter, might pronounce there finall ſentence. Which was ſo done. For of the one ſide <hi>S. Paul</hi> and <hi>Barnabas</hi> were appoynted, and of the other ſome other men. Who going together to <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> went to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles and Seniours of the Citty. Theſe after there was a councell gathered and the holy Ghoſt called vpon, anſwered in theſe words. <hi>It ſeemeth good to the holy Ghoſt and to vs<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to lay no further burden vpon</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 15. 28.</note> 
                     <hi>you then theſe neceſſary things. That you abſteyne from the things immolated to Idolls, and bloud and that which is strangled<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and fornication.</hi> Which words were ſent in manner of an Epiſtle to the Chriſtians conuerted
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:1409:62"/> from Gentility whome they eſpecially concerned. And the ſenſe is this. We will not put vpon you the burden of circumciſion or other legall ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies which is troubleſome, but to ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaine from thoſe things, which were named before, and this will not be troubleſome to you.</p>
                  <p>Here two things are to be noted which are much to our purpoſe. The<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 1.</note> firſt is that this controuerſy of circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion and legall rites could ſufficiently<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 13. 2.</note> haue beene decided by <hi>S. Paul</hi> and <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabas,</hi> who both were Apoſtles, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets and Doctours: Who alſo were choſen eſpecially of the holy Ghoſt that they might preach the Ghoſpell to all<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Act.</hi> 14. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> nations: And alſo had preached it in many places and prouinces, yet neyther of them would take that office, to the end that they might teach by their ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, that ſuch controuerſies which concerne matters of fayth and religion ought to be brought to the ordinary Prelats of the Church, or to the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell conſiſting of them.</p>
                  <p>The other is that the Councell of the Apoſtles in the which that contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſy
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:1409:62"/> was determined, there was no teſtimony of ſcripture brought, which belonged directly to Circumciſion, though there be many for both parts, if it had beene fitting one of them only to haue ended the contention. For this place might haue beene brought for circumciſion: <hi>This is my Couenant which you shall obſerue betweene me and you, and thy</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 10.</note> 
                     <hi>ſeede after th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. All the male Kinde of you shalbe circumciſed, and you shall circumciſe the flesh of your prepuce, that it may be for a ſigne of the Couenant betweene me and you &amp;c. as well the home-bred, as the bought ſeruant of whom ſoeuer he is, not of your ſtock, and my coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant shalbe in your flesh for a perpetuall coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant.</hi> But if it be an externall couenant as here it is ſayd, it is of neceſſity to be alwaies kept, euen in the Euangelicall law: And not only of the Iewes but of others alſo who are not of the ſtocke of the Iewes. On the other ſide might be alleadged that of Deuteronomy. <hi>Our Lord thy God will circumciſe thy hart, and the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 6.</note> 
                     <hi>hart of thy ſeed.</hi> Where it is inſinuated, that Circumciſion of fleſh is not to remaine in the new Teſtament, but that the circumciſion of the hart is to
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:1409:63"/> ſucceed in the place thereof. As alſo that of Ieremy: <hi>Be circumciſed to our Lord, and take away the prepuce of your harts,</hi> as if he ſhould ſay, I do not require the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion of fleſh, but of the hart, which conſiſteth in the inward contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and greife for ſinnes. Theſe and ſuch like might be taken out of the Scripture for both parts. But it was not ſo done. For the Apoſtles being gathered together in Councell gaue ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence, by the direction and aſſiſtance of God, the which God had promiſed to them and their ſucceſſours for euer.</p>
                  <p>After the tyme of the Apoſtles there aroſe other new controueſies in diuers places and ages, which is certaine out of the Eccleſiaſticall hiſtories to haue beene decided eyther by the Romaine biſhops, or by ſome approued Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells. And thoſe who would not yeald to their ſentence, were accounted al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies and condemned for heretikes. I will bring forth ſome plaine examples euen of thoſe which do firſt occure.</p>
                  <p>The firſt controuerſy was: whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Paſch ought to be celebrated with the Iewes, on the fourteenth day
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:1409:63"/> of the firſt month, as many did hould<note place="margin">Vide Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeb. l. 5. hiſt. Eccleſ. cap. 23. &amp; ſequent.</note> in <hi>Aſia,</hi> who for that cauſe were called <hi>Quartadecimani,</hi> or only vpon Sunday as now it is. This truly after many Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells and aſſemblies of diuers Biſhops was decided and ended by <hi>Victor</hi> the Pope, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 198.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond was, whether the Church might abſolue the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from ſinnes,<note place="margin">Vide Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. circa eundem annum.</note> who were fallen after baptiſme. <hi>Noua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tian</hi> did deny it. But he was condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of errour in the Roman Councell by Pope <hi>Cornelius, Anno Chriſti</hi> 255.</p>
                  <p>The third was, whether in God there was three perſons really diſtinct. <hi>Sabellius</hi> denyed it, affirming that there was but one perſon which had three offices, of creation, redemption, and Sanctification. But he alſo was con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned<note place="margin">Iuxta Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron.</note> in the Councell of <hi>Alexandria,</hi> in the tyme of Pope <hi>Silueſter, Anno Chriſti</hi> 319<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fourth, whether Chriſt be a pure man, as other who be mortall, &amp; hath nothing more in nature and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon then we haue? <hi>Paulus Samoſatenus</hi> did affirme it: But he alſo was condemned in the councell of <hi>Antioch</hi> in the tyme of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:1409:64"/> Pope <hi>Dionyſius, Anno Chriſti</hi> 266<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iuxta Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron. vide Euſeb. l 7. cap.</hi> 27.</note>
                  </p>
                  <p>The firſt was. Whether Chriſt were the eternall word of his Father, and of the ſame ſubſtance with him? <hi>Arius</hi> denyed it, affirming that the word of the word not to haue beene from e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternity, but created of God in tyme of<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide duas epiſt. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexan. E. picſ Alex. quarum v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na extat a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pud Socra. lib. 1. c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. altera apud Theod. l. 2. cap.</hi> 4.</note> nothing, and of another ſubſtance from God. And therefore that God was not alwayes a Father, but that there was ſome tyme, when he was not Father. But he was condemned in the firſt ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall Councell of <hi>Nice</hi> in the tyme of Pope <hi>Silueſter,</hi> and <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour, <hi>Anno</hi> 325.</p>
                  <p>The fixt was, whether in Chriſt there be two Perſons, as there are two natures, diuine and human? <hi>Neſtorius</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> did affirme it, but he was likewiſe condemned in the Generall Councell of <hi>Epheſus,</hi> in the tyme of Pope <hi>Celeſtine,</hi> and <hi>Theodoſiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>he Emperour <hi>Anno</hi> 434. and before by <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rill</hi> in the Councell of <hi>Alexandria Anno</hi> 431.</p>
                  <p>The ſeaueth was, whether in Chriſt there be two natures? <hi>Eutiches,</hi> and <hi>Dioſcorus</hi> ſayd, that before the hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaticall
<pb n="113" facs="tcp:1409:64"/> vnion, there was two natures<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Vaſq. tom. 1. in 3. par. D. Thom. in diſp.</hi> 14.</note> diuine and humaine: But after the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that both two came into one, and were made one. But they both were condemned in the generall Councell of Chalcedon, in the tyme of Pope <hi>Leo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> and <hi>Marcian</hi> the Emperour <hi>Anno</hi> 454.</p>
                  <p>The eight, whether there was one will only in Chriſt? <hi>Macarius Patriarch</hi> of <hi>Antioch, Cyrus</hi> of <hi>Alexandria, Sergius</hi> of <hi>Constantinople,</hi> and ſome others although they acknowledged two natures to be in Chriſt, yet they ſayd that there was in him but one will, to wit the diuine,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In 3. p. 1. 18. art.</hi> 1.</note> as is recorded by <hi>S. Thomas,</hi> and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they were called <hi>Monothelites:</hi> this their opinion was condemned in the third generall Councell of Conſtanti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nople vnder Pope <hi>Agatho,</hi> and the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour Conſtantine the 4. in the yeare 679. But whether theſe vnderſtood by<note place="margin">Vide Baro.</note> the name of will, the power or the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration, is to be ſeene in <hi>Gabriel Vaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quez.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The 9. Whether the holy Ghoſt be God, The Macedonians deny it, of<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Tom. 1. diſ. 73. cap.</hi> 1.</note> whome thus writes <hi>S. Auguſtine.</hi> The <hi>Macedonians</hi> came from one Macedonius
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:1409:65"/> who was biſhop of Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinople: theſe of the Greekes are called alſo <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, becauſe they co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tended about the holy Ghoſt. For as concerning the Father and the Sonne, they beleeue aright, that they are of one &amp; the ſame ſubſtance nature and eſſence, but they deny this of the holy Ghoſt, ſaying that he is but a creature. Theſe were condemned in the firſt generall Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell of <hi>Conſtantinople</hi> vnder Pope <hi>Damaſus</hi> and the Emperour <hi>Theodoſius.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The tenth is: Whether baptiſme may be reiterated, or one may be baptized twice? Which controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy may be two waies vnderſtood. Firſt whether baptiſme if it be once giuen well, may be reiterated againe. <hi>Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cion</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Epiph. haer. 42. paulo poſt princip.</note> affirmed it, as <hi>Epiphanius</hi> is witneſſe; for he writeth thus of <hi>Marcion: After he had deflowerd</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>a certaine Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin in the Citty, and was fled away, but yet afterwardes found in that great fault, the cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſener inuented a ſecond lauer to himſelfe, affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming that three were lawfull, to wit, three Baptiſmes for the remiſſion of ſinnes, to the end that if any shall ſinne after the first doing pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, he might take the ſecond, and alſo the
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:1409:65"/> third, if he should be found in fault after the ſecond.</hi> Againe it may be vnderſtood, whether Baptiſme giuen of Heretikes may be reiterated? The Donatiſts affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med it, who did baptize again all thoſe who were baptized of Catholikes, as S. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> doth witneſſe, becauſe they<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug. in l. de haer. cap.</hi> 69.</note> accounted Catholikes for Heretikes, and ſo thought that Baptiſme giuen of Heretikes was of no value, as is to be ſeene in <hi>Vaſquez.</hi> Theſe were condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned<note place="margin">
                        <hi>V<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſq. diſp. 146. c.</hi> 2.</note> in the Roman Councell vnder <hi>Melchiades</hi> the Pope, <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 313.</p>
                  <p>The eleuenth is, whether a man<note place="margin">Apud Baron.</note> without the grace of God can fullfill the Law only by the force of nature, if he be willing. <hi>Pelagius</hi> and <hi>Celeſtius</hi> affirmed it, but they were both con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned in the Councells of <hi>Carthage</hi> and <hi>Mileuitane</hi> in the tyme of Pope <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocentius</hi> the firſt, <hi>Anno 416. iuxta compu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The twelft, whether Children are borne in originall ſinne, and to waſh away the ſame do need Baptiſm? The ſame Authors denyed it <hi>Pelagius</hi> and <hi>Celestius,</hi> as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> doth affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me: <hi>They deny</hi> (ſayth he) <hi>that children borne
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:1409:66"/> carnally of Adam, do contract the infection of the old death in their firſt natiuity. For ſo they affirme, that they are borne without any bond of originall ſinne, as though there were not any thing to be remitted in their ſecond natiuity. But that therefore they are baptized, to the end, that being adopted by regeneration, they maybe admitted to the kingdome of God, as tranſlated from good to better, not being abſolued by this renouation from any euill of the old obligation.</hi> But this errour was condemned in the <hi>Mileuitane</hi> Councell <hi>cap.</hi> 2. and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards of Pope <hi>Zoſinus,</hi> as S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo<note place="margin">Aug. in l. de pecc. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rig. cap. 6. &amp; ſequen.</note> is witneſſe.</p>
                  <p>In theſe and ſuch like Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſyes, which now for breuity I omit, three thinges are to be conſidered. Firſt that one part of them who contended is clearely and manifeſtly condemned. Secondly that this condemnation was vttered &amp; pronounced by the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Church, as iudge: which ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tymes gaue ſentence by the Pope, who is the head and paſtour of the ſame Church, and ſometymes by Councells which repreſent the whole Church. Thirdly, that the Lutherans, and the Caluiniſts doe confeſſe that this con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:1409:66"/> was lawfully pronounced. For they confeſſe, that <hi>Nouatian, Sabelli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us, Samoſatenus, Arius, Neſtorius, Eutiches, &amp; Dioſcorus,</hi> and the <hi>Monothelits,</hi> the <hi>Macedo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nians,</hi> the <hi>Donatiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Pelagians</hi> to haue beene iuſtly condemned, &amp; that they are and ought to be accounted for Heretiks. And that by no other means then by the ſentence of the Catholike Church. For if the Scripture only ſhould haue been Iudge, &amp; the Church ſhould not haue giuen ſentence at all, theſe Controuerſyes would haue con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued euen to this preſent day: nor yet would it euer haue beene cleare &amp; manifeſt to all, that thoſe Authours a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-named were to be had, and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counted for Heretikes. Now ſeeing that they were condemned by the Church, the matter is plaine, &amp; with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out all doubt.</p>
                  <p>Perchance you will ſay, what if the Church her ſelfe ſhould haue er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red in giuing ſentence? I anſwere. This to be iuſt as much, as though one ſhould ſay. What if Chriſt his Apoſtles and Prophets ſhould lye? For they tell vs, that the Church cannot erre, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe,
<pb n="118" facs="tcp:1409:67"/> as Chriſt himſelfe ſayth, his Church is founded vpon a rocke, and<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math. 16. 18. 1. Tim. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>5. Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 54. Ibid. v. 12. Ibid. v.</hi> 17.</note> the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt her. She is the piller and firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of truth to S. <hi>Paul.</hi> And <hi>Iſaias</hi> ſaith ſhe ſhall neuer bluſh, nor be confoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. And in another place: A laſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone is in the defenſe thereof. And a little after: Euery tongue reſiſting in iudgment, ſhall be condemned.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="argument">
                  <head>
                     <hi>THE VI. ARGVMENT,</hi> Drawne from the Analogy and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Ciuill Iudge concerning matters belonging to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon wealth.</head>
                  <p>THIS argument, which may beſt illuſtrate the matter, may well be propounded in this manner. A mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold Analogy, or proportion may be ſeene betweene thinges apertaining to faith and Religion on the one ſide, &amp; thinges meerely Politike, and Ciuill on the other. Firſt, for euen as in poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tike, &amp; Ciuill affaires oftentymes con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſyes,
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:1409:67"/> and contentions do ariſe, which require ſome iudge, who may giue ſentence between the contending partyes; ſo falleth it out in matters of fayth, and religion. 2. As in Ciuill controuerſies, theſe three things are diſtinguiſhed, The Iudge, the written law, and the cuſtome: ſo alſo in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies of faith, theſe three, the Iudge, the whole Scripture of both teſtaments and tradition. 3. As a ſecular Prince or Magiſtrate doth exerciſe the office of a iudge in deciding of Ciuill contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies: ſo alſo the Prince of the Church or Eccleſiaſticall Synod doth exerciſe the like office in decyding controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies of fayth. 4. As the written law is a certaine rule which the ſecular Iudge doth follow in deciding of Ciuill con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentions, ſo alſo the Scripture of both Teſtaments, is a certaine line or rule which the Eccleſiaſticall Iudge doth follow in decyding controuerſies of fayth. 5. As only the written law is not a ſufficient rule for all Ciuill cauſes but the written law and cuſtome with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all: ſo alſo the Scripture only of both Teſtaments, is not a ſufficient and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:1409:68"/> rule of all controuerſies of fayth, vnleſſe tradition be adioyned.</p>
                  <p>Theſe hitherto are manifeſt. Yet leaſt that there be any doubt therein, I will expound them all breifly. And firſt that the ſecular Prince or Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate may vſe the office of a iudge in Ciuill cauſes, needeth no long proofe. For daily experience doth wittneſſe this in all Prouinces and Kingdomes. For in euery place, Ciuill cauſes and contentions are brought to the ſecular Prince or Magiſtrate, whom the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties at variance do acknowledg to be their lawfull Iudge, which is well knowne by the Ciuill and Canon law: for in each of them there are titles con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the ordinary Iudge, and him who is the iudge delegate. Neyther is there any ſo ignorant and fooliſh that by the ordinary or delegate iudge vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtandeth the written law, when it is certaine that he is the ordinary, who hath the ordinary iuriſdiction and power, and him to be a iudge delegate who receauing power of the ordinary ſupplies his office and place.</p>
                  <p>Moreouer that the written law
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:1409:68"/> cannot be iudge may eaſily be proued, and moſt plainly in theſe three caſes. Firſt when it is obſcure and doubtfull; for then there is need of ſome other iudge or interpreter who may expound the meaning of it. Secondly when one law ſeemeth to repugne another which happenth very often: For then a iudge is needfull who may reconcile them together. Thirdly when the words of the law which are generall, ought to be reſtrained in ſome particuler caſe, yet they are in no wiſe limitted. Which then happeneth, when ſome particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler caſe doth occur, which the law did not foreſee might happen. And yet perchance if he had knowne would not haue comprehended it in the law: therefore in ſuch a caſe one muſt iudge againſt the words of the law. But then who ſhalbe iudge? Not the law it ſelfe, for it neuer giueth ſentence againſt it ſelfe. Therefore there muſt be ſome other Iudge beſides the law.</p>
                  <p>Now laſtly, that only the written law cannot be a ſufficient rule for the deciding of all Ciuill controuerſies whatſoeuer, but beſides it, alſo cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:1409:69"/> is to be admitted, is moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine amongſt the Lawyers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in two caſes. Firſt when ſome controuerſy doth ariſe, of the which<note place="margin">Leg. 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. ff. de legibus.</note> there is no written law; for then cuſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ome is to be taken for law, and ought to be no leſſe obſerued, according to that: Thoſe things which are appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by long cuſtome, and obſerued for many yeares as a ſecret agreement of the Citizens, are to be kept no leſſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe things which are written.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, when there is extant in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed a written law, yet there is ſome doubt about the ſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſe or meaning there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which cannot be knowne but by cuſtome or traditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that taketh place of which is ſaid in the law: For then the beſt interpreter of the Lawes is Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome: and that our Emperour Seue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rus hath written, how that in doubts<note place="margin">Leg. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7. ff. de legibus.</note> which proceed from Lawes, either cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome or the authority of things iudged alwaies in the ſame manner ought to haue the force of a law.</p>
                  <p>Perchance you wil ſay: what if ſome controuerſy occur which neither<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ibid. leg.</hi> 38.</note> can be defined out of the written law,
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:1409:69"/> nor out of any cuſtome: what then ſhalbe the rule that the iudge ought to follow? I anſwere: Then the matter muſt be taken vp according to that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity which doth proceed out of the law of nature But this eſpecially hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peneth, when ſome certaine Caſe doth occur, which is vnderſtood according to the wordes of the law, but not to the meaning of the law-giuer, as before was ſaid. For then the Iudge is to giue ſentence according to that which he thinketh to be iuſt and right. The very ſame may happen in Controuerſies of faith. For if any controuerſy ſhould a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe which cannot manifeſtly be deci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded neither by Scripture nor tradition, recourſe preſently were to be made to the help of the holy Ghoſt, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he aſſiſt the Church in al occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, yet in this eſpecially he doth teach her al truth, as Chriſt himſelfe hath promiſed. And this remedy alſo the Apoſtles haue vſed in that Councel of <hi>Hieruſalem,</hi> where they were aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled about circumciſion and the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation of legall rites and ceremonies. Now theſe be the argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts by which
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:1409:70"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:1409:70"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:1409:71"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="123" facs="tcp:1409:71"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="124" facs="tcp:1409:72"/> hitherto hath beene proued, that the Scripture cannot be ludge of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies in faith, but that the Church may. Now it remayneth that we dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently weigh and conſider the teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of Scripture which were propou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded in the beginning, and which are obiected and often repeated by our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries againſt this doctrine, but not in that order as they were propounded, but as they are placed in the Scripture of the old and new teſtament one after another. And truly by the examining of theſe, as I did before inſinuate, it wilbe manifeſt that ſome of them are nothing to the purpoſe, and the reſt ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther make for vs then for them. But to conclude and ſpeake freely as the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is indeede, I affirme, that our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries who alwaies ſo much boaſt &amp; bragge of Scripture, vnderſtand no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing leſſe then the true ſenſe &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Scripture.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="125" facs="tcp:1409:72"/>
               <head>The Testimonies of Scripture brought againſt vs heere are examined.</head>
               <div n="1" type="testimony">
                  <head>THE I. TESTIMONY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOVV shal not ad to the word that I ſpeake to you.</hi> And this alſo. <hi>VVhat I com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maund</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut. 4. 2. Deut.</hi> 12. 32.</note> 
                     <hi>thee, that only do to our Lord, neither ad any thing nor diminish.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Out of which the aduerſaries ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally gather theſe two poynts. Firſt that all Traditions which Catholikes admit ought to be vtterly reiected. But what is their reaſon? Becauſe forſooth nothing is to be added to the written word of God. Secondly that no huma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> precepts (ſuch as are the commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of faſting lent, abſtinence from fleſh on Fryday and Saturday, of the ſingle life of Prieſts &amp; ſuch like) ought to be obſerued. But wherefore? Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe ſay they, that only is to be done which Chriſt hath co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maunded: what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer men commaund is not to be done. Thus they, but very fooliſhly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as I wil ſhew two waies. Firſt by diſpro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb n="126" facs="tcp:1409:73"/> their falſe interpretation. And againe by ſhewing the true ſenſe and meaning of theſe places of Scripture.</p>
                  <p>Now firſt that their interpretati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is falſe, they themſelues cannot deny vnleſſe they will altogeather be accou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                     <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted fooliſh and impudent. For if all tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditions ought to be refuſed, the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle himſelfe muſt be reiected, who ſaith, Hould the Traditions which you<note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 14.</note> haue learned, whether it be by words, or by our Epiſtle. Likewiſe if al human precepts ſhould be contemned, and that only ſhould be done, which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundeth; What ſhould we ſay of the Rechabits, who moſt diligently ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued the precept of their Father <hi>Iona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dab?</hi> did they amiſſe therein? This tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y were to be ſayd according to our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries; but it is far otherwiſe, ſeing that for ſo doing they are commended by God himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>If our Aduerſaries know not this, let them heere <hi>Hieremy</hi> the Prophet ſpeaking in theſe words: <hi>The word that</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>e.</hi> 35. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>was made to<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Ieremy from our Lord in the daies of Ioakim, the Sonne of Ioſias, the King of Iuda, ſaying, Go to the houſe of the Rechabits, &amp; ſpeake
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:1409:73"/> to them, and thou shalt bring them into the howſe of our Lord, into one chamber of the treaſuries, and thou shalt giue them wyne to drinke. And I tooke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ezonias the ſonne of Ieremias, the Sonne of Habſamias and his brethren, and all his ſonnes and the whole howſe of the Rechabites. And I brought them into the howſe of our Lord &amp;c. And I ſet before the ſonnes of the howſe of the Rechabits gobletts full of wyne, and cuppes, and I ſaid to them, drinke wyne: who anſwered we will not drinke wyne, becauſe Ionadab the ſonne of Recab our Father commaunded vs ſaying: you shall not drinke wyne, you and your Children for euer: And yow shall not build howſes &amp; you shall not ſow ſeede, and you shall not plant vineyards nor haue any, but yow shall dwell in tabernacles al your dayes, that yow may liue many dayes vpon the face of the land wherein yow are ſtrangers: we therfore haue obeyed the voice of Ionadab the ſonne of Rechab our Father in all things that he commaunded vs: ſo that we drinke not any wine all our dayes, we and our wiues, our ſonnes and our Daughters: And we builde not howſes to inhabit, and vineyard, and ſeild, and ſeede wee haue not had: but we haue dwelt in taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacles, and we haue beene obedient according to all things that Ionadab our Father commaunded vs &amp;c. And the word of our Lord was to Ieremy
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:1409:74"/> ſaying: Thus ſayth the Lord of Hoſts, the God of Iſraell; go and ſay to the men of Iuda and to the inhabitants of Hieruſalem, VVhy will you not receaue diſcipline, to obey my words, ſayth our Lord; The words of Ionadab the ſonne of Rechab haue preuailed, which he commaunded his ſon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes not to drinke wyne, and they haue not drunke vntill this day, becauſe they haue obeyed the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundement of their Father: but I haue ſpoken to you early riſing, and ſpeaking and you haue not obeyed me. And I haue ſent to you all my ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uants the Prophets riſing earely, and ſending and ſaying: Returne ye euery one from his moſt wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked way, and make your ſtudies good<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> &amp;c. And you haue not enclined your eare nor heard me. The Children therefore of Ionadab the ſonne of Rechab, haue firmely kept the precepts of their Father which he commaunded them: But this people haue not obeyed me. Therefore thus ſayth the Lord of hoſts, the God of Iſraell: behould I will bring vpon Iuda, and vpon all the inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants of Hieruſalem all the affliction, which I haue ſpoken againſt them, becauſe I haue ſpoken to them and they haue not heard: I haue called them and they haue not anſweared me: but to the howſe of the Rechabits Ieremy ſayd: Thus ſayth the Lord of Hoſts, the God of Iſraell: For that yow haue obeyed the commaundment of Ionadab
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:1409:74"/> your Father, and haue kept all his commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and haue done all things that he co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded yow. Therefore thus ſayth the Lord of Hoſts the God of Iſraell: There shall not want a man of the ſtocke of Ionadab the ſonne of Rechab ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in my ſight all dayes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In this example three things are to be noted. Firſt that the precept which was giuen to the Rechabites was moſt hard. For what is harder then that huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bands and wiues, young men, and young maides, not only for a ſhort tyme, as the Nazareans did, but as long as euer they liued ſhould abſtaine from all kynde of wyne, and neuer ſhould dwell in howſes, nor ſow their grounds, nor plant any vineyards? Secondly that this precept was not di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine but humane, it appeareth by the oppoſition which God made. For thus he argueth. The Rechabits did obſerue the precept which they receiued from man; how much more ought the Iewes to keep the precept which they recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from God? Thirdly that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chabits not only did well and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendably in obſeruing the precept of their Father Ionadab, but alſo thereby
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:1409:75"/>
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:1409:75"/>
                     <pb n="128" facs="tcp:1409:76"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="129" facs="tcp:1409:76"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="130" facs="tcp:1409:77"/> deſerued a peculiar bleſſing from God: whereas contrare wiſe the Iewes deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued nothing but great puniſhment. For it is ſayd to the Rechabits. <hi>There shall not want a man of the stocke of Ionadab the ſonne of Rechab ſtanding in my ſight al daies.</hi> But to the Iewes: I <hi>will bring vpon you affliction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now from hence let our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries if they be wiſe infer theſe few ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rities. Firſt that the Catholikes obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing the precepts of the Church, do no leſſe well and laudably then did theRechabites, by keeping the precept of their Father Ionadab. For doubtleſſe it is no leſſe commendable to obey the Church our common mother then it was for them to obey a priuate man their Father. And euen as the Recha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bites did not ſinne againſt that aforſaid place, what I commaund you that only do to our Lord: euen ſo neyther the Catholikes ſinne againſt it. Secondly the cauſe why Catholikes haue conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued and do continue ſtill, is becauſe they keep diligently the commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Church: and how much more diligently one doth obſerue them
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:1409:77"/> ſo many more benefits he ſhall receiue from God, and that ſome others do not proſper, becauſe of the one ſide they contemne the precepts of the Church, in the which they are not ſo perfect as the Rechabits were. And on the other they do not obſerue the tenne com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundments, in the which they are like the Iewes. But that they may pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend ſome kind of excuſe for this their damnable laſineſſe, they hould that the ten commaundement are impoſſible to be kept: In the which they make God a tyrant, as though he would commaund man that which is not in his power to fullfill.</p>
                  <p>But this may ſuffice to ouerthrow their falſe interpretation. The true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpretation therefor is this: <hi>You shall not</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>ad to the word that I ſpeake to you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> neyther shall you take away from it.</hi> Which is generally to be vnderſtood of ceremoniall and iudiciall precepts, which were giuen of God by <hi>Moyſes.</hi> And this is the ſenſe: I haue giuen ceremoniall precepts to you which preſcribe the rites of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhiping God, and Iudiciall which pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe the rites of keeping iuſtice in Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:1409:78"/> matters and thoſe which belong to the Common wealth. Both of which you ought perfectly and entirely to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue: for this is the ſignification of that, <hi>You shall not ad, nor take away.</hi> Which truly in other words, but in the ſame ſenſe is explicated in another place, where it is ſayd, <hi>do not decline eyther from the right</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 14. Deut.</hi> 17. 20.</note> 
                     <hi>hand or the leſt.</hi> And againe. <hi>That he may learne to feare our Lord his God and keepe his wordes and ceremonies, nor decline to the right ſide nor to the left.</hi> And a little after. <hi>For I</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 31. 29.</note> 
                     <hi>know that after my death you will do wickedly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and will decline quickly from the way that I haue commanded you;</hi> and like wiſe in the<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioſue.</hi> 7.</note> booke of Ioſue, <hi>Take courage and be ſtrong, that thou keepe and do all the Law which Moyſes my Seruant hath commaunded thee: decline not from it to the right hand or to the left.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore our of that place ſo vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood, as truly it ought to be vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood, the aduerſaries cannot argue o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe then thus. The Iewes ought to obſerue the precepts of God wholly and entirely, not declining from them neyther to the right hand nor to the left, therefore we Chriſtians, beſides the Scripture, ought not to admit any
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:1409:78"/> tradition which we haue receaued from the Apoſtles, <hi>Spectatum admiſſi &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But that place in Deuteronomy.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 11. 32<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> 
                     <hi>VVhat I commaund thee, this only do to our Lord, neyther add any thing nor diminish,</hi> is eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially vnderſtood of one ceremoniall precept, to wit of the precept of ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficing as appeareth. Of which this is the ſenſe and meaning. When thou comeſt into the land of Paleſtine in the which thou goeſt, and thou ſhalt offer a ſacrifice to thy Lord thy God, thou ſhalt not imitate the Gentills, who offer their ſonnes and daughters to falſe Gods by fyer. But this only thou ſhalt offer, the which I commaund thee, as of Beaſts, Sheepe, Goats, Kidds, Oxen, Calues, Pigeons, Sparowes, and Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle-doues: of fruits of the Earth, Bread, Meale, Salt, Frankincenſe, a bundle of greene eares of Corne, and wheat: of Liquors, Bloud, Wyne, Oyly, and Water. <hi>Do this only,</hi> that is, offer <hi>to our Lord: Neyther ad any thing,</hi> of the ſacrifices of the Gentills, <hi>nor diminish</hi> any thing of them which were now particulerly ſet downe. Now out of this place the
<pb n="134" facs="tcp:1409:79"/> aduerſaries can no otherwiſe conclud then in this manner. The Iewes ought only to offer thoſe things in ſacrifice, which were preſcribed of God: there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we Chriſtians may not keepe the precepts of the Church: which is euen as fooliſh as the former.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="testimony">
                  <head>THE II. TESTIMONY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ISAY 8. 20. Rather to the law, and to the teſtimony.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From hence the aduerſaries gather that the Iewes in the old Teſtament, when any controuerſy did ariſe, were ſent preſently to the law and teſtimony, that is to the Scripture euen as to their iudge. But they erre groſly. Firſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it hath beene ſhewed before, that the Iudge of controuerſies in the old Teſtament was not the Scripture, but the High Prieſt. Secondly, becauſe thoſe words, <hi>to the law and testimony</hi> much other wayes are to be vnderſtood then our aduerſaries ſuppoſe, as appeareth by the precedent words which are theſe: <hi>And when they shall ſay to you: Aske of Pytho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s and of Deuiners, which whiſper in their</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1. <hi>cap.</hi> 8. 19.</note>
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:1409:79"/> 
                     <hi>inchantements: shall not the people aske viſion of their God for the liuing of the dead? To the law rather, and to the teſtimony. And if they ſpeake not according to this word, they shall not haue the morning light.</hi> Where it is plainly ſpoken againſt them who aske counſell of the Pythones and Deuiners, about future euents, and are remitted plainly to the law which forbiddeth it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>VVhen thou art entred the land which our</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>Lord thy God shall giue then, beware thou be not willing to imitate the abhominations of thoſe na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Neither let there be ſound in thee any that conſulteth with Pytho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>s or Deuiners, and ſeeketh the truth of the dead,</hi> partly to the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of the Prophets, who where placed of God, to foretell future things, as in the third of Kings we may ſee. <hi>And Ioſaphat ſaid: is their not heer ſome Prophet</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>g <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ap. 22. v.</hi> 7.</note> 
                     <hi>of our Lord, that we may aske by him?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore the ſenſe of the words <hi>to the law and teſtimony,</hi> is this: If you will be certified of future euents, yow ought not to aske Counſell of the Pythons as<note place="margin">1 <hi>Reg.</hi> 28. 7.</note> Saul did, becauſe God hath forbidden this to be done by his law, vnto the which I remit you: but aske Counſell of the Prophets of our Lord, whoſe
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:1409:80"/> office is to pronounce of future euents. But what is this to the iudge of the Controuerſies? Verily nothing at a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l: Vnleſſe our aduerſaries will argue in this manner: As concerning future euents, it is not lawfull to aske Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Pythones: therefore only the Scripture is the iudge of Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies. Truly moſt fooliſhly, and yet which is to be admired their very cheife Rabbins of all are not aſhamed to vſe ſuch manner of arguing, of whom Chriſt himſelfe hath forewarned vs ſayi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>g: <hi>Let ſuch followes alone, for they are blind themſelues, and leaders of them that are blind.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="testimony">
                  <head>THE III. TESTIMONY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>YOV haue made fruſtrate the commaund<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. Coloſ. 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>et.</hi> 1. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>of God for your owne tradition.</hi> And the other place in S. Paul: <hi>Beware least any man deceaue you by Philoſophy, and vaine fallacy, according to the tradition of men.</hi> And that in S. Peter: <hi>You are redeemed from your vaine conuerſation of your Fathers tradi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>From hence our aduerſaries gather
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:1409:80"/> that all traditions are condemned of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alone is ſufficient. But it is not ſo. For theſe cited places are vnderſtood of the Iewes traditions, which were ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerued of the Phariſies: but not of the traditions of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, which our aduerſaries oppugne, and we defend. But that there were diuers traditions of the Iewes, appeareth out of the Scripture.</p>
                  <p>The firſt was, that their hands were to be waſhed before taking of meat, as in this place: <hi>Then came to him from Hieru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math</hi> 15.</note> 
                     <hi>Scribes and Phariſees ſaying, why do thy diſciples tranſgreſſe the traditions of the ancients? For they wash not their hands when they eate bread.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſecond is, that this waſhing was often to be vſed whylſt they were eating, as in S. Mark: <hi>The Phariſees and all the Iewes, vnleſſe they often wash their hands,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mark.</hi> 7. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>eate not, holding the traditions of the ancients.</hi> Alſo at the marriage in Cana in Galilee <hi>ſix water pots were put according to the purifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of the Iewes.</hi> In the which water potts there was water wherewith they waſhed their hands at dinner.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1409:81"/>
                  <p>The third was, that vnleſſe they ware waſhed they could not take meat coming from the market, as <hi>S. Marck</hi> recordeth: <hi>And from the market vnleſſe they</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Mar.</hi> 7. 4.</note> 
                     <hi>bee washed they eate not:</hi> and many other things there be that were deliuered vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them to obſerue, as the waſhing of Cupps, and Cruſes, and of brazen ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſells, and Bedds.</p>
                  <p>The fourth is, that meate was not to be taken with ſinners, as is written in S. Matth: <hi>And the Phariſies ſeing this ſayd</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 9. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>to his Diſciples, why doth your maister eate with Publicanes and ſinners?</hi> And in S. Luke:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 5. 30.</note> 
                     <hi>The Phariſies and Scribes murmured, ſaying to his Diſciples, why do you eate and drinke with Publicanes and ſinners?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The fifth was that none ſhould be permitted to be touched of ſinners as S. Luke recordeth: <hi>And the Phariſee that</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 7. 39.</note> 
                     <hi>had bid him ſeing it, ſpake within himſelfe, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: this man if were a Prophet would know certes, who and what manner of woman she is which toucheth him, that she is a ſinner.</hi> Where it manifeſtly appeareth, that the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſee wondred, that Chriſt ſhould ſuffer himſelfe to be touched of a woman that was a ſinner, becauſe it was contrary
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:1409:81"/> to the cuſtome and tradition of the Phariſees, whoſe ſpeach was this: <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>part from me, thou shalt not came neere me be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65. 5.</note> 
                     <hi>thou art vncleane.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ſixt was, that vpon the Sabaoth it was not lawfull to cure the ſicke as S. Luke ſayth: <hi>The Scribes and Phariſees</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 6. 7.</note> 
                     <hi>watched if he would cure on the Sab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th, that they might find how to accuſe him.</hi> And likewiſe S. Iohn writeth, <hi>that certaine of the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 9. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>ſayd: This man is not of God, that keepeth not the Saboath.</hi> Where they ſpake of Chriſt, who on the Saboath reſtored ſight to a man that was blind from his natiuity.</p>
                  <p>The ſeauenth was, that thoſe who were hungry, might not gather and eate eares of Corne on the Saboath, as it is ſayd in S. Matth. <hi>Ieſus went through</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 12. 1.</note> 
                     <hi>the Corne on the Saboath, and his diſciples being hungry began to pluck the eares and eate. And the Phariſies ſeing them ſaid to him. Lo thy Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples do that which is not lawfull for them to do on the Saboath day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The eight was, that they ſhould faſt and pray often, as is recorded in S. Math. <hi>VVhy do we and the Phariſees faſt often</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 9. 15.</note> 
                     <hi>but thy Diſciples do not faſt? And</hi> in S. Luke.
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:1409:82"/> 
                     <hi>VVhy do the Diſciples of Iohn faſt often and make</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk</hi> 5. 35.</note> 
                     <hi>obſeruations; but thine do eate and drinke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The ninth was, that the tythes of all things euen of the very leaſt ſhould be offered to God, as we reade in S. Math. that Chriſt ſayd. <hi>VVo to you Scribes</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 23. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>and Phariſees, Hipocrits, becauſe you tith mint and aniſe, and cummin, and haue left the weightier things of the law, iudgment and mercy and fayth, theſe things you ought to haue done and not omitted thoſe.</hi> Heere to tyth is ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for to giue tythes, and this is the true ſenſe: <hi>You Phariſees giue tythes of all thinges whatſoeuer,</hi> euen of the very leaſt of all, which you do not as by a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept in the law of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> but by your one tradition which is not written, and in the meane tyme you omit thoſe things which are commaunded in the law, theſe things you ſhould do, and not omit the other. Where it is to be noted, that there was no precept in the law of <hi>Moyſes,</hi> about giuing of tythes of the leaſt things of which mention is here made, but only of the tythes of wyne, wheat, and oyle. Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Deut.</hi> 14. 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> the Phariſees in this had a peculiar cuſtome and tradition beyond others
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:1409:82"/> of the Iewes, becauſe they gaue the tythes of all kynde of hearbes which<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 11. 42.</note> others did not. For the which cauſe one of the Phariſees did boaſt ſaying, I<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luk.</hi> 18. 11.</note> am not as the reſt of men &amp;c. <hi>I faſt twice a weeke, and I giue tythes of all that I poſſeſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The tenth was, that whoſoeuer<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Vide Ia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſen. in concord Euan. cap.</hi> 84.</note> ſhould ſweare by the Temple or by the Altar, he was not guilty of any fault? But he that ſhould ſweare by gould of the temple, or ſacrifices which were made on the Altar, was guilty, as in S. Matth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> is written. <hi>VVo to you blind guides that ſay, whoſoeuer shall ſweare by the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>Temple, it is nothing, but he that shall ſweare by the gould of the temple, is bound. Ye foolish and blinde, for whether is greater, the gould or the temple which ſanctifieth the gould? And who<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer shall ſweare by the Altar it is nothing, but whoſoeuer shall ſweare by the guift that is vpon it, is bound. You foolish and blinde, for whether is greater the guift, or the Altar that ſanctifieth the guift?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The eleuenth was, that Children were not bound to honour their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, or to be beneficial vnto them, but that it would ſuffice aboundantly to offer ſome guift vnto God as we read in
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:1409:83"/> S. Mathew, <hi>VVhy do you tranſgreſſe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandement of God for your tradition? For God ſayd, honour Father and Mother, &amp; he that shall curſe Father or Mother, dying let him dy. But you ſay, whoſoeuer shall ſay to the Father or Mother, the guift whatſoeuer proceedeth from me shall profit thee, and shall not honour his Father or his Mother, and you haue made fru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate the Commandement of God for your owne tradition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe were the cheife traditions of the Phariſees. For as much as we can gather out of the Ghoſpell. And although ſome of them were good in their kynd, others ill, certaine doub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full or vnprofitable: Yet notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the Phariſees were reprehended in them all for theſe cheife cauſes.</p>
                  <p>Firſt becauſe they by the obſerua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of then ſought vaine glory and to be eſteemed holy amongſt men when they were nothing leſſe then holy and godly as S. Matth. ſpeaketh of them:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 23. 5</note> 
                     <hi>But they do all their workes, for to be ſeene of of men.</hi> And very often, yea and almoſt euery where in the Ghoſpell they are called Hypocrites, and whited Sc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pulchers.</p>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:1409:83"/>
                  <p>Secondly becauſe, out of the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruing of them, they gaped after wealth and riches, eſpecially out of long praiers which they recited to that end, as is ſayd of Chriſt in S. Matth.<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math.</hi> 23. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>VVo to yow Scribes and Phariſees Hipocrits, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe yow deuour widdowes howſes, praying long prayers.</hi> And likewiſe in S. Marke. <hi>Take heede of the Scribes, who denoure widdowes howſes vnder the pretence of long prayer.</hi> Where to eate and deuour widowes howſes is nothing els but to ſpoyle and exhauſt them. For the Widowes came to the Phariſees, euen as vnto holy men (for they fayned ſanctity) and bought their prayers with money.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, becauſe they ſuperſtiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly did obſerue ſome things which were to little purpoſe, and did neglect thoſe which were of greater moment, as we ſhewed a little before. For they gaue tythes of thoſe things which were leaſt of all, and did neglect mercy and iudgment, in iudging of thoſe cauſes which were brought vnto them. And that of S. Matth. may be taken in this ſenſe: <hi>They ſtraine a gnat and ſwallow a Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="144" facs="tcp:1409:84"/>
                  <p>Now out of theſe it appeareth that all the traditions of the Iewes were not reprehended by Chriſt, although the Phariſees were blamed deſeruedly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they made all vſe of them. For one of their traditions was, to tythe mint, rue, and euery hearbe. Which doubtleſſe was good of it ſelfe, for it is very good to giue tythes to God <hi>not only</hi> of ſome things which we haue, <hi>but of</hi> all things wee poſſeſſe. And this is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by Chriſt himſelfe, who ſayth: theſe things yow ought to haue done, and not to haue ommitted thoſe: that is, yow ought to haue kept the precept of iuſtice and mercy, and not omit the tradition of tything mint, and all kynd of hearbes.</p>
                  <p>From whence it directly followeth that the Lutherans and the Caluiniſts ſeing they condemne all Traditions, do condemne the very iudgment of Chriſt who approued ſome of them. For in the iudgement of Chriſt there be ſome traditions which are not to be omitted. But in their opinion all are to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected, and the Scripture only to be ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mited. Theſe two opinions are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:1409:84"/> one to the other. But which of them muſt we imbrace? Chriſts doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe if we be wiſe.</p>
                  <p>Out of which I infer againe, that the Lutherans and the Caluiniſts can conclud out of this no otherwiſe then this. Some traditions of the Iewes were euill, therefore all the traditions of the Chriſtians are euill.</p>
                  <p>Which is no conſequence at all. But this is much better. The Iewes had ſome traditions, beſides the Scripture, which ought not be omitted, therefore alſo the Chriſtians may haue ſome, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there be great difference bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wixt them both. For the traditions of the Chriſtians which we now defend were receaued from Chriſt and his A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles: but ſo were not theſe of the Iewes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="testimony">
                  <head>THE IIII. TESTIMONY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>SEARCH the Scriptures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Lo, ſay our aduerſaries Chriſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitteth<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioan.</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> vs to the Scripture, euen as to the iudge of Controuerſies. This truly they would not ſay, if they vnderſtood
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:1409:85"/> the meanning of Chriſt, for Chriſt in that Chapter diſputeth with the Iewes who denied him to be the Sonne of God, and therefore he proued by foure kynd of teſtimonies that he was. Firſt by the teſtimony of <hi>S. Iohn Baptiſt.</hi> You haue, ſayth he, <hi>ſent to Iohn, and he gaue teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony to the truth.</hi> But this was his teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony. <hi>Behould the Lambe of God, behould</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Iohn.</hi> 1. 34.</note> 
                     <hi>who taketh away<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> the ſinnes of the world.</hi> And againe, <hi>I haue giuen teſtimony, that this is the Sonne of God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly by the teſtimony of thoſe Miracles which he wrought. <hi>I haue</hi> ſayth he, <hi>teſtimony greater then Iohns For the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioan.</hi> 3. 36.</note> 
                     <hi>workes which my Father hath giuen me to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſit them, the very workes themſelues which I do giue teſtimony of me, that the Father hath ſent me.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly by the teſtimony of God the Father. <hi>And the Father that ſent me him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Ioan.</hi> 5 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>7.</note> 
                     <hi>hath giuen teſtimony of me.</hi> As alſo when he ſpake out of heauen. <hi>This is my wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beloued</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Math</hi> 3. 17.</note> 
                     <hi>ſonne in whom I am well pleaſed heare him.</hi> Fourthly by the teſtimony of the old teſtament. <hi>Search the Scripturs, for you thinke in them to haue life euerlaſting, and the ſame are they that giue testimony of me, and you
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:1409:85"/> will not come to me, that you may haue life.</hi> As yf he ſhould ſay. If you will not receaue the three former teſtimonies, which are moſt forcible (otherwiſe I would not haue made mention of them) at leaſt you cannot reiect the teſtimonies of Scriptures, of the which you brag ſo much. And thoſe if you ſearch dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently, giue teſtimony of me, that I am the true Meſſias promiſed of God: Wherefore then do ye not beleeue?</p>
                  <p>Heere hence I conclude that our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries oppugne themſelues more then vs. For they contend that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only is the iudge of Controuerſies and that Chriſt remitteth vs to the Scripture alone. But the quite contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry is true. For Chriſt in the Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſy which he had with the Iews, to wit, whether he were the Sonne of God, ſent them not only to the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture but firſt to the teſtimony of <hi>S. Iohn Baptiſt.</hi> Secondly to the teſtimony of Miracles, which ſhew him to be God. Thirdly to the teſtimony of God the Father, who confirmed the ſame with a voice from heauen. And after al theſe at leaſt he ſends them to the Scriptures.</p>
                  <pb n="148" facs="tcp:1409:86"/>
                  <p>We Catholikes do follow Chriſt in this matter. For in theſe controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies which we haue with our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, not only we vſe the teſtimony of Scripture, but alſo that of the holy Fathers, that of the Church our Mother, and likewiſe that of Miracles, which oftentymes are wrought for the confirmation of our fayth. But our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries, as though they were wiſer then Chriſt, will heare nothing but that which is conteyned in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. In the which they reſemble not a l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>le thoſe Iewes with whom Chriſt had to do. For theſe reiecting all other teſtimonies did only admit the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, the which they neyther then vnderſtood, nor do yet if we may be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue <hi>S. Paul,</hi> for their ſenſes are dulled<note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> ſayth he: &amp; a little after: vntill this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent day when <hi>Moyſes</hi> is read a veyle is put vpon their hart. All this in this caſe may be not vnſittly applied to theſe our moderne aduerſaries, as to faythfull ſchollars, and iuſt coſen-Germans to thoſe moſt ignorant blind &amp; obſtinate Iewes.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="testimony">
                  <pb n="149" facs="tcp:1409:86"/>
                  <head>THE V. TESTIMONY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>DAILY ſearching the Scriptures, if th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ſe</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> 
                     <hi>thinges were ſo.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But heere againe our aduerſaries cry out that the men of <hi>Beroea</hi> did not haſtily and raſhly beleeue thoſe things with the Apoſtles tould them, but exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mined all things according to the rule of the Scripture, and therefore ſay they it is alſo fitting that we ſhould follow their example, and acknowledg the Scripture only to be the rule &amp; iudge. But al this is in vaine, which will eaſily be ſeene if we conſider the matter it ſelfe, whereof they ſpake<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> For thus it was. <hi>S. Paul</hi> the Apoſtle as it is expreſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſhewed in the ſame Chapter, firſt at Theſſalonica, and after with them of Beroea <hi>did diſcourſe out of the Scriptures<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claring and inſinuating that it behoued Chriſt to ſuffer and to riſe againe from the dead, and that this is Ieſus Chriſt whom I preach to you.</hi> But now what did thoſe of Beroea? in the ſelfe ſame place it followeth, <hi>they recea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued the word with all greedineſſe, daily ſearching the Scriptures if theſe things were ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="150" facs="tcp:1409:87"/>
                  <p>This therefore is the true ſenſe of that place. The men of Beroea when they heard <hi>S. Paul</hi> cite certaine teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of the Scripture in the old Teſtament, by the which he affirmed Chriſts death and reſuriection, they ſearched whether the doctrine of <hi>S. Paul</hi> were agreeable to thoſe teſtimonies. Not truly, as though they doubted of the death and reſurrection of Chriſt, for it was ſufficiently confirmed by the force of many Miracles wrought by<note place="margin">1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5.</note> the Apoſtle: But that they might be more ſtedfaſtly confirmed in faith, if they ſhould ſee thoſe things which <hi>S. Paul</hi> had preached to haue beene tould and ſignified long before by the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets.</p>
                  <p>Now what thinke you can our ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſaries conclude by this? Nothing doubtleſſe to the purpoſe. Vnleſſe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture they conclude in this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. The men of Beroea ſearched the teſtimonyes of the Scripture cited of <hi>S. Paul</hi> therefore the Scripture only is the iudge of controuerſies: which is euen like vnto this the: Lutherans ſearch out the teſtimonies of <hi>S. Auguſt.</hi> cited by
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:1409:87"/> 
                     <hi>Bellar.</hi> therefore <hi>S. Aug.</hi> only is the iudge of controuerſies. Or thus. The Clownes ſearch out the teſtimonies of Luther cited by the miniſters, therfore Luther only is the iudge of all Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſies. Or thus. Kemnitius in the examen of the Councell of Trent ſear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth out the traditions alleadged of Catholiks, therefore traditions are the only iudge of Controuerſies. Or Laſtly Schollars ſearch out the teſtimonies of <hi>Cicero</hi> cited of their maiſter: therefore <hi>Cicero</hi> only is the author of the Latin tongue. Away with ſuch conſequences which are not all worth a ruſh. And yet our aduerſaries make great accompt of them becauſe they haue no better.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="testimony">
                  <head>THE VI. TESTIMONY.</head>
                  <p>IT <hi>any euangelize to you beſids that which you</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Galat.</hi> 19.</note> 
                     <hi>haue receaued, be he anathema.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore, ſay our aduerſaries beſids the Ghoſpell we muſt not admit any traditions: but infer the quite contrary in this manner. If any ſhall Euangelize to you any thing beſides that which <hi>S. Paul</hi> hath Euangelized, be he anathema:
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:1409:88"/> But the Lutherans and the Caluiniſts do euangelize ſomething beſides that which <hi>S. Paul</hi> euangelized, becauſe they oppugne traditions, which he hath commaunded when he ſayd, <hi>keepe</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2. 14.</note> 
                     <hi>the traditions,</hi> therefore the Lutherans and the Caluiniſts are anathema.</p>
                  <p>But now let vs ſee the drift of the Apoſtle, for thence it will appeare whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther traditions are altogether to be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned or no. Truly the drift of the Apoſtle is this. The Galathians were taught of <hi>S. Paul</hi> that the ceremonies<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Gal.</hi> 2. 15.</note> of the law of <hi>Moyſes</hi> were abrogated, &amp; that none could be iuſtified by thoſe ceremonies but by fayth in Chriſt: but afterward they were brought from this doctrine by certayne falſe Apoſtles who taught them that they could not be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued by fayth in Chriſt, vnleſſe they were alſo circumciſed, and obſerued the other ceremonies of <hi>Moyſes</hi> law, as is manifeſt by the courſe of the whole Epiſtle, but eſpecially in theſe chapters<note place="margin">1. <hi>v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. &amp;c. 3. v. 1. &amp;. 4 v. 9. &amp;. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. v.</hi> 1.</note> cited in the margent. And againſt theſe falſe Apoſtles doth <hi>S. Paul</hi> here diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pute, when he ſayth. <hi>If any euangelize to you, beſides that which you haue recaued, be he
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:1409:88"/> anathema.</hi> As though he had ſayd: You haue receiued of me, that a man is iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by faith in Chriſt, and not by the obſeruation of the law of <hi>Moyſes.</hi> If any do teach you otherwiſe, affirming that faith in Chriſt doth profit nothing vnleſſe circumciſion, and other legall ceremonies be adioyned, be he anathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma. But from hence it doth not follow that the Apoſtolicall traditions are to be reiected, but rather that they are to be retained, becauſe they are not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to that which <hi>S. Paul</hi> hath euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelized to the Galathians of iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, but rather they are the ſame which he hath euangelized to the Theſſaloni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, when he ſayd, <hi>keep the traditions with you haue learned</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="testimony">
                  <head>THE VII. TESTIMONY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALL Scripture inſpired of God is profitable</hi>
                     <note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 16.</note> 
                     <hi>to teach, to argue, to correct, to instruct in iuſtice, that the man of God may be perfect, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed to euery good worke.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Out of which place our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries argue two waies: Some of them thus. All ſcripture is profitable to teach
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:1409:89"/> and to argue: Therefore traditions are ſuperfluous, which is much like vnto this: All meat is profitable to nouriſh:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc. 11. 41. &amp; Dan.</hi> 4. 24.</note> Therefore drinke is needleſſe: or els thus: All alſmedeedes are profitable to Saluation, therefore prayer is needleſſe, and the Sacraments are needleſſe. Alas who will not pitty ſuch follies.</p>
                  <p>Or thus. All ſcripture is profitable that is ſufficient: therefore traditions are needleſſe. But what an expoſition is this? Is it the ſame to be profitable, and to be ſufficient? if it be ſo, one may alſo interpret that place of <hi>S. Paul</hi> in the<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. 8.</note> ſame place: Piety is profitable to all things, that is, Piety is ſufficient for all things, therefore all other things are needleſſe. And likewiſe that: Take<note place="margin">2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1.</note> Marke, and bring him with thee, for he is profitable to me for the miniſtery, that is, ſufficient: Therefore Timothy Titus, and Oneſimus and all the reſt were needleſſe. But who doth not now euidently perceaue, that if this licence of interpreting the Scripture were once permitted, how eaſy it were to corrupt it all.</p>
                  <p>But that the matter may appeare
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:1409:89"/> more plainly, the text of the Apoſtles is well to be conſidered. For the Apoſtle in the cited Chapter doth exhort Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothy the Biſhop, that he ſhould in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruct his ſubiects in fayth and good workes; and that he ſhould reprehend his aduerſaries who being corrupted in mynd, and reprobate concerning fayth<note place="margin">1. <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 16.</note> did reſiſt the truth. And that he might ſhew that he was able to performe it, he addeth. <hi>But thou continue in thoſe things which</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ibid. pau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lo poſt.</note> 
                     <hi>thou haſt learned, and are commtted to thee: knowing of whome thou haſt learned. And be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe from thine infancy thou haſt knowne the holy Scriptures, which can inſtruct thee to Sal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, by the fayth that is in Chriſt Ieſus. For all Scripture inſpired of God is profitable to teach &amp;c.</hi> Where by the holy Scripturs which he ſayth Timothy to haue knowne, he meaneth the Scripture of the old Teſtament. For at that tyme when Timothy was a Child, the Scripture of the new Teſtament was not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant.</p>
                  <p>Therefore the Apoſtle in that text thus doth argue. <hi>All Scripture inſpired of God is profitable to teach</hi> ſubiects, &amp; repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend aduerſaries. But the Scripture of
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:1409:90"/> the old Teſtament which thou haſt knowne from thy infancy, is inſpired of God. Therefore it is profitable to teach thy ſubiects, and to reprehend thy aduerſaries. And when thou art well inſtructed with the knowledg of that Scripture, thou wilt obtaine great aide thereby to performe that which I haue tould thee.</p>
                  <p>And from the ſame head, one may conclud in this manner: <hi>All Scripture in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpired of God is profitable to teach and argue.</hi> And whoſoeuer is inſtructed with the knowledg of this Scripture, ſhall ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine great aide thereby to performe them both.</p>
                  <p>Now out of both theſe arguments it followeth, that theſe three propoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions are true according to the Apoſtle. 1. All Scripture inſpired of God is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to teach and argue. 2. That the Scripture of the old Teſtament is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitable to teach and to argue. 3. That the Scripture of the new teſtament is profitable to teach, and to argue. As therefore it doth not follow, the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the old Teſtament is profitable, therefore the Scripture of the new
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:1409:90"/> Teſtament is needleſſe &amp; ſuperfluous. Nor the contrary: The Scripture of the New Teſtament is profitable, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Scripture of the old Teſtament is ſuperfluous. So alſo it doth not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low, that tradition is ſuperfluous, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe the old and the new Teſtament are profitable.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="testimony">
                  <head>THE VIII. TESTIMONY.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>FOR I teſtify to euery one hearing the words</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>po.</hi> 22. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>of the Prophecy of this booke. If any man shall add to theſe things, God shall add vpon him the plagues written in this booke. And if any man shall diminish of the word of the booke of this Prophecy, God shall take away his part out of the booke of life.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Heereby our aduerſaries conclude in this manner. If any man ſhall add to the words of this Apocalypticall Prophecy, he ſhalbe puniſhed of God. But the Catholikes add traditions: Therefore the Catholikes ſhalbe puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed of God. They may alſo conclude in this manner. If any man ſhall add to the words of this Apocalipticall prophecy he ſhal be puniſhed of God.
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:1409:91"/> But the Caluiniſts add Ghoſpells, E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſtles of the Apoſtles, the inſtitutions of Caluin, the Cathechiſme of Hidel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berge, Athanaſius Creed, and alſo the firſt foure generall Councells. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Caluiniſts ſhalbe puniſhed of God. Or in this manner: If any man ſhall diminiſh of the words of this A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pocalipticall prophecy, he ſhalbe taken out of the booke of life: But the Luthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rans do not only diminiſh of the words of this Apocalipticall propheſy, but alſo bring it into queſtion whether it be true or no; and not acknowledging it to be diuine and Canonicall, tell vs in plaine termes that it is counterfait &amp; Apocalipticall: Therefore they ſhalbe taken out of the booke of life.</p>
                  <p>But now to the purpoſe. <hi>S. Iohn</hi> for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biddeth nothing els, but onely that the words of the Apocryphall prophecy be not corrupted of any: Which he inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ateth to be done two wayes, firſt by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, as if one ſhould add any thing to the Apocalipticall prophecy, to be as a part of it, which is not. Secondly by diminiſhing, as if one ſhould take ſomething from it, although it did not
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:1409:91"/> belong to it, which certainly doth. The Catholikes do neither. But with an example I will declare it better.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>S. Iohn</hi> foretelleth, that in a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine tyme two Prophets ſhall come, clothed with ſackcloath, who ſhall propheſy a thouſand two hundred ſix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty dayes, and ſhall haue power to ſhut heauen that it raine not in the dayes of their propheſy, and to turne the water into bloud &amp;c. To which prophecy the catholikes ad nothing at all, which doth not belong vnto it, nor take any thing away which is <hi>added therto:</hi> but leaue it whole, as it was propheſied of <hi>S. Iohn.</hi> But our aduerſaries do the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, eſpecially thoſe who ſay that Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Caluin were the two Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets. For theſe, who ſay this muſt of neceſſity diminiſh of the words of this prophecy; ſeing that it is certaine that Luther and Caluin were not cloathed in ſackcloathes, nor had any power of ſhutting heauen, nor alſo had thoſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties which follow.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <pb n="160" facs="tcp:1409:92"/>
               <head>The Concluſion of all that is contained in this Booke.</head>
               <p>TWo things I haue hitherto endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoured to performe. The one is to ſhew that the Scriptures cannot be the iudge of Controuerſies, but the Church. And this I haue declared ſix wayes. Firſt, by the office of the iudge, which is not fitting for the Scripture becauſe the Scripture ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not pronounce ſentence in that manner betweene two at variance ſo that the one party may ſee it is for him, and the other perceaue it is againſt him. Secondly out of the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it ſelfe, in the which two things are to be conſidered, the letter and the ſenſe; The letter killeth as the Apoſtle ſayth, and is cauſe of many hereſies, as was ſhewed by diuers examples. The ſenſe oftentymes is obſcure and doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, both for the apparent contradicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons which are found in euery place, &amp; alſo for many other cauſes which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore were numbred, and therefore there is need of ſome Iudge who may mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly deſine, that this is the lawfull
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:1409:92"/> ſenſe, and that the vnlawfull. Thirdly out of the Controuerſies themſelues, becauſe there are many controuerſies, of the which no mention is made in the Scripture, and ſo conſequently can neyther be defined out of Scripture. Fourthly out of the vſe and cuſtome of the old Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, where the Scripture did not vſe the office of a Iudge, but high Preiſt, who was Prince of the Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nagogue whoſe precept was to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beyed vnder paine of death. Fiftly by the vſe and practiſe of the new Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherein all Controuerſies hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto haue beene decided by the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates of the Church. Sixtly out of the proportion of Ciuill cauſes, which are not decided by the written law, but by the Prince of the Common wealth, nor according to the rule of the written law only, but alſo according to the ancient cuſtomes not written.</p>
               <p>The other is to ſhew that the teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies of Scripture, which are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iected againſt vs, eyther to be nothing to the purpoſe or to be rather for vs the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Iſa.</hi> 8. 20.</note> againſt vs, and not to be expounded truly by them, as for example. To the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:1409:93"/> law &amp; teſtimony, is nothing to the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, becauſe it is not vnderſtood of<note place="margin">
                     <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>an.</hi> 5. 39.</note> Controuerſies of fayth, but of the fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture euents of caſuall things. And alſo that other place, Search the Scriptures doth rather helpe vs then our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries. For Chriſt when he ſayd this to the Iewes did not diſpute with them out of Scripture only (as our aduerſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries would haue vs beleeue) but alſo out of the teſtimony of <hi>S. Iohn Baptist,</hi> to the which he added the teſtimony of Miracles, and alſo the voice of God the Father ſpeaking downe from heauen, therefore he neuer dreamed that Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture only was the Iudge of Controuer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies. The reſt as I haue ſhewed are no better expounded by our aduerſaries, as out of our confutation the Reader if he b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> but indifferent may eaſily perceaue himſelfe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="objection">
               <head>An Obiection of the vulgar people aginst all that hath beene hitherto ſayd.</head>
               <p>MANY that be of the more ſimple <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> thus obiect againſt vs. The Iudge of Controuerſies in matters of
<pb n="163" facs="tcp:1409:93"/> fayth ought to be ſo infallible that he cannot erre. Becauſe if he erre all others following him ſhould be deceaued in imbracing his opinion. But now it is moſt plaine &amp; manifeſt of the one part, that the ſcripture is infallible, ſeing it is the very word of God, which can by no meanes erre, and of the otherſide that no man can be infallible is no leſſe certaine, ſeing that euery man is a lyar and not any one can be found who is<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 3. 4.</note> not ſubiect to errour. According to that of <hi>S. Paul.</hi> God is true, but euery man a lyar. Therefore the Scripture may be an infallible iudge. Men ſeing they be lyars cannot: But the Pope is a man, &amp; the Church is nothing but a congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of men. Therefore the Pope &amp; the Church are lyars and may erre. And ſo conſequently none is ſafe and ſecure in matters of fayth who followeth their doctrine.</p>
               <p>This obiection if there be any force in it, is no leſſle againſt our aduerſaries then againſt vs. For if euery man be a lyar and may erre, it followeth alſo that <hi>Moyſes,</hi> all the Prophets, Apoſtles, Euan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geliſts<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Luther alſo and Caluin &amp; al the
<pb n="164" facs="tcp:1409:94"/> Lutherans and Calumiſticall preachers are lyars and ſubiect to errour, becauſe they are men, therefore they are not to be beleeued or truſted in any thing whatſoeuer, and they ought to bee doubted of, &amp; accounted as vncertaine. Where then is fayth? Neyther doth it help them to ſay, that they preach the word of God and not of man<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> for if they be lyars, euen in ſo ſaying they may ly. Nothing therefore is certaine.</p>
               <p>But God forbid that we ſhould ey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſay ſo, or thinke ſo. For it is far o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe. And firſt we confeſſe that the ſcripture is certaine and infallible, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it is the word of God. But this we add, that ſeing it is obſcure, the law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſenſe thereof is not manifeſt to euery one. And therefore that there is need of ſome other iudge who may infallibly deliuer which is the true and lawfull ſenſe of ſcripture. But euery priuat man cannot be this Iudge, becauſe other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, there would be as many diuers Iudges as there be diuers heads and opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions. And ſo no controuerſy could euer be compoſed. For euery one would ſay that he vnderſtood it rightly, and al
<pb n="165" facs="tcp:1409:94"/> other falſly. Therfore it is neceſſary that there be ſome publique Iudge, who with authority may haue power to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cide, and end the matter betwixt the parties at contention.</p>
               <p>Moreouer we affirme that men may<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Gen. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> pſal.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>. 6.</note> be conſidered two waies. Firſt as they are the Children of <hi>Adam</hi> ſubiect to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers corruptions of nature. And ſo by that meanes may be prone to lying and falſity. Secondly as they are directed &amp; gouerned by the holy Ghoſt for the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of others, and ſo they may be infallible and voyde of all errour. Such an one in the old Teſtament was <hi>Moyſes</hi> and the whole Senate of the Seniors. Such alſo were the high Prieſts who followed the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Such were the Prophets Iſaias, Ieremy, Ezechiel, Daniel, and<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Num. 11. 7. Deut. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Agga. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>0. 7. Ierem.</hi> r. 7. <hi>Ioan. 15. 16. Ioan.</hi> 16. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> others. Such in the new Teſtament were the Apoſtles, to whom it was ſaid of Chriſt: <hi>I will ſend you from my father the ſpirit of truth.</hi> And alſo this: <hi>VVhen that ſpirit of truth shall come, he will teach you all truth.</hi> But where there is all truth, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly there cannot be any falſhood or errour.</p>
               <p>To conclude ſuch hath beene and
<pb n="166" facs="tcp:1409:95"/> at this day is the Church, which by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of the perpetuall aſſiſtance and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of the holy Ghoſt, neuer hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hath erred, nor euer can erre heere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Matth. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>8. 1. Tim. 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Iſa 54. 4. Ibid. v. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#APEX" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>2. Ibid. v.</hi> 17.</note> For it is built vpon a firme rocke and the gates of hell ſhall not preuaile againſt it. It is the pillar and ground of truth. It ſhall neuer be conſounded nor bluſh. The Iaſper ſtone is the munition of it. And it ſhall iudge euery tongue reſiſting it in Iudgment. Therefore it is the infallible Iudge which we ſeeke.</p>
               <p>But now there is a queſtion, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther all who are in the Church, haue ſo much aſſiſtance and direction of the holy Ghoſt that they cannot err, or no. Which truly is very eaſy to be reſolued. For all certainly haue it, but with a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine kynde of dependance from the Church. Therefore as long as they re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maine vnited to the Church, they can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not erre, but if they once depart from it then they beginne to erre, which may be declared with two ſimilitudes: the one is taken from the proportion of a mans body. For if you ſhould aske whether all the members which are in a mans body haue vitall and ſenſible
<pb n="167" facs="tcp:1409:95"/> ſpiritts in them, by the which life in them is preſerued. I anſweare that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed all haue, but with a certaine kynd of dependance from the head and the hart, for theſe ſpirits are deriued from the head and the hart, as from a double origen, ſpring or fountaine into the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther members. From whence it comes that if thoſe pores and paſſages be ſtop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped &amp; intercepted, through the which that diſtribution of ſpirits is made, it followeth alſo that the other members are deſtitute of their ſpirits and cannot exerciſe their office at all, but if they be patent and open, all is well. Euen ſo in the Church all the faythfull who are as members of the Church haue the aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance and direction of the holy Ghoſt, but which a certaine kynd of depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of the Pope who is as the head of the Church: and from the Councells which are as the hart of the Church. As long therefore as they remaine vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the doctrine of the Pope &amp; Cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cells, they are pertakers of the aſſiſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nce and gouernement of the holy Ghoſt, &amp; cannot erre in fayth. But if they once depart by obſtinacy and ſtubborneſſe
<pb n="168" facs="tcp:1409:96"/> then they begin to ſhut vp all their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſages that the diuine aſſiſtance and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be diſtributed vnto them. And ſo they begin to ſwarue from the truth, and become ſubiect to errour which happened to <hi>Arius, Neſtorius, Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedonius, Pelagius</hi> and ſix hundred others<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> And truly leaſt the ſame happen vnto vs, let vs heare the Counſell of the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, who in euery place doth exhort vs, to the agreement and vnity of do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine. As when he writeth thus to the Romains. <hi>And I deſire you brethren</hi> (ſaith he)<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Rom.</hi> 16. 17.</note> 
                  <hi>to marke them that make diſſentions &amp; ſcandalls contrary to the doctrine which you haue learned, and auoyd them.</hi> And to the Corinthians. <hi>I beſeech you brethren by the name of our Lord</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1. 10.</note> 
                  <hi>Ieſus Christ, that you all ſay one thing, and that there be no ſchiſme among you.</hi> And to the Epheſians. <hi>Becarefull to vſe the ſpirit of truth in the bond of peace. One body and one ſpirit, as</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>you are called in one hope of your Saluation: One Lord, one fayth, one Baptiſme.</hi> And likewiſe to the Hebrewes <hi>VVith variances &amp; ſtrang</hi>
                  <note place="margin">
                     <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 9.</note> 
                  <hi>doctrines be not led away.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Another ſimilitude may be bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowed from a flock of ſheepe, which very well doth repreſent the Church.
<pb n="169" facs="tcp:1409:96"/> For as a whole flock being gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether in one fould, or one place, hath the continuall aſſiſtance of their ſhee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheard who doth defend them all with his hooke &amp; his dogge from the cruelty of wolues: eue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> ſo the whole Church of the faythfull being collected in one fayth and in one ſpirit, hath the perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of that diuine ſheepheard.<note place="margin">
                     <hi>Ioan. 10. 14. Matth.</hi> 28. 20.</note> who ſayd, <hi>I am the good Paſtour and I know my sheepe.</hi> And againe: <hi>Behould I am with you all dayes euen to the conſu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>matio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the world.</hi> Alſo, euen as the ſheep as long as they remayne togeather with the flock and their Paſtour, they are ſafe from the bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of wolues: euen ſo all Chriſtians, as long as they remaine vnited with the Church, that is, agreeing with the doctrine of the Church, they are ſafe and ſecure from all dangers of errour and infidelity: And finally, as ſheepe which ſtray from the flock are deſtitute of the protection of their Paſtour, and ſo ſubiect to be deuoured of the raue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning wolues: euen ſo Chriſtians who diſagree from the common ſenſe and doctrine of the Church, are quite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute of the aſſiſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of the holy Ghoſt,
<pb n="170" facs="tcp:1409:97"/> and ſo in danger to fall certainly into peſtiferous &amp; damnable errours. From the which Chriſt free vs all.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:1409:97"/>
            <head>THE CONTENTS OF THIS BOOKE</head>
            <list>
               <item>OF the Iudge of Controuerſies the Preface. Pag. 1.</item>
               <item>The Scripture alone is not the Iudge of Controuerſies, concerning matters of Faith and Religion.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>I. ARGVMENT,</hi> Drawne from the Office of a Iudge. Pag. 6.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>II. ARGVMENT,</hi>
                  <pb facs="tcp:1409:98"/> Drawne out of the Scripture it ſelfe. Pag. 9.
<list>
                     <item>That the Scripture according<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> to the ſenſe and meaning thereof, cannot be Iudge. Pag. 19.</item>
                     <item>That the Scripture often tymes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding vnto the ſenſe, is obſcure and hard to be vnderſtood. Pag. 20.</item>
                     <item>What are the cauſes why the Scripture is obſcure? Pag. 33.</item>
                     <item>Wherefore is it Gods will, that the Scripture ſhould be obſcure? Pag. 58.</item>
                     <item>It followes neceſſarily out of the obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of the Scripture, that many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trouerſies ariſe amongst Chriſtians. Pag. 64.</item>
                     <item>The Scripture cannot be the Iudge of theſe, and the like Controuerſies. Pag. 71.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>THE III. ARGVMENT.</hi> Which is drawne out of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trouerſies themſelues. Pag. 81.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>THE IIII. ARGVMENT.</hi> Which is taken out of the vſe and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe
<pb facs="tcp:1409:98"/> of the old Teſtament, where not the Scripture, but the Biſhop was acknowledged for the Iudge. Pag. 91.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>THE V. ARGVMENT.</hi> Drawne from the cuſtome, vſe, and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe of the new Teſtame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. Pag. 106.</item>
               <item>THE VI. ARGVMENT. Drawne from the Analogy, and propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Ciuill Iudge, concerning matters belonging to the common Wealth. Pag. 118.</item>
               <item>The Teſtimonies of Scripture brought againſt vs heere are examined.
<list>
                     <item>THE I. TESTIMONY. Pag. 125.</item>
                     <item>THE II. TESTIMONY. Pag. 134.</item>
                     <item>THE III. TESTIMONY. Pag. 136.</item>
                     <item>THE IIII. TESTIMONY. Pag. 145.</item>
                     <item>THE V. TESTIMONY. Pag. 149.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:1409:99"/>
                     <item>THE VI. TESTIMONY. Pag. 151.</item>
                     <item>THE VII. TESTIMONY. Pag. 153.</item>
                     <item>THE VIII. TESTIMONY. Pag. 157.</item>
                  </list>
               </item>
               <item>The Concluſion of all that is contained in this Booke. Pag. 160.</item>
               <item>An Obiectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the vulgar people againſt all that hath beene hitherto ſayd. Pag. 162.</item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:1409:99"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
